Их больше, чем вчера.
There are more than yesterday.
هناك أكثر من الأمس.
Он будет читать молитвы в саду. Просто следуйте за остальными.
He will be saying prayers in the garden. Just follow the others.
سيصلي في الحديقة. فقط اتبع الآخرين.
Брат, Бапу уже опаздывает на молитву.
Brother, Bapu is already late for prayers.
أخي، بابو متأخر بالفعل عن الصلاة.
О, Боже!
Oh, God!
يا إلهي!
Объектом этой огромной дани...
The object of this massive tribute...
إن هدف هذه التحية الضخمة...
...умер так же, как и жил всегда:
...died as he had always lived:
...مات كما عاش دائمًا:
Частный человек без богатства...
A private man without wealth...
رجل خاص بلا ثروة...
...без имущества...
...without property...
...بدون ممتلكات...
...без официального титула или должности.
...without official title or office.
... بدون لقب أو منصب رسمي.
Махатма Ганди...
Mahatma Gandhi...
مهاتما غاندي...
...не был командующим армиями...
...was not the commander of armies...
...ولم يكن قائدا للجيوش...
...ни правитель обширных земель.
...nor a ruler of vast lands.
...ولا حاكما لأراضي واسعة.
Он не мог похвастаться никакими научными достижениями...
He could not boast any scientific achievement...
لم يكن بمقدوره أن يفتخر بأي إنجاز علمي...
...или художественный дар.
...or artistic gift.
...أو موهبة فنية.
Но мужчины...
Yet men...
ومع ذلك الرجال...
...правительства, высокопоставленные лица со всего мира...
...governments, dignitaries from all over the world...
...الحكومات وكبار الشخصيات من جميع أنحاء العالم...
...взялись сегодня за руки, чтобы отдать дань уважения...
...have joined hands today to pay homage...
...لقد انضموا إلى أيدينا اليوم لتقديم التحية ...
...этому маленькому смуглому человечку в набедренной повязке...
...to this little brown man in the loincloth...
...إلى هذا الرجل الصغير ذو اللون البني الذي يرتدي مئزرًا...
...который привел свою страну к свободе.
...who led his country to freedom.
...الذي قاد بلاده إلى الحرية.
По словам генерала Джорджа К. Маршалла...
In the words of
General George C. Marshall...
على حد تعبير الجنرال جورج مارشال...
...госсекретарь США:
...the American secretary of state:
... وزير الخارجية الأمريكي:
«Махатма Ганди стал оратором...
"Mahatma Gandhi has become the spokesman...
"أصبح المهاتما غاندي المتحدث الرسمي..."
...для совести всего человечества.
...for the conscience of all mankind.
...من أجل ضمير البشرية جمعاء.
Он был мужчиной...
He was a man...
لقد كان رجلاً...
...который сотворил смирение...
...who made humility...
...الذي صنع التواضع...
...и простая истина...
...and simple truth...
...والحقيقة البسيطة...
...могущественнее империй».
...more powerful than empires."
...أقوى من الإمبراطوريات."
А Альберт Эйнштейн добавил:
And Albert Einstein added:
وأضاف ألبرت أينشتاين:
«Грядущие поколения вряд ли поверят, что такой человек, как этот...
"Generations to come will scarce believe that such a one as this...
"لن تصدق الأجيال القادمة أن شخصًا مثله...
...всегда во плоти и крови...
...ever in flesh and blood...
...أبداً في اللحم والدم...
...ходил по этой земле».
...walked upon this earth."
...مشيت على هذه الأرض."
Скажи мне...
Tell me...
أخبرني...
...вы думаете об аде?
...do you think about hell?
... هل تفكر في الجحيم؟
Нет, я тоже.
No, neither do I.
لا، أنا أيضا لا.
Но этот человек...
But this man here...
ولكن هذا الرجل هنا...
...христианин, и он написал это, чтобы верить...
...is a Christian, and he's written that in order to believe--
...هو مسيحي، وقد كتب أنه من أجل الإيمان--
Извините, сэр.
Excuse me, sir.
عذرا سيدي.
Как долго вы находитесь в Южной Африке?
How long have you been in South Africa?
منذ متى وأنت في جنوب أفريقيا؟
- Неделю. - Не знаю, как ты достал билет.
-A week.
-l don't know how you got a ticket.
-أسبوع. -لا أعرف كيف حصلت على التذكرة.
Что ты делаешь в этой машине, приятель?
Just what are you doing in this car, coolie?
ماذا تفعل في هذه السيارة أيها العامل؟
У меня есть билет.
Why, l have a ticket.
لماذا، لدي تذكرة.
Билет первого класса.
A first-class ticket.
تذكرة الدرجة الأولى.
- Как ты его получил? - Я заказал его по почте.
-How did you get it?
-l sent for it in the post.
-كيف حصلت عليه؟ -أرسلته بالبريد.
Я адвокат. Я не...
I'm an attorney.
I didn't--
أنا محامي. لم أفعل--
В Южной Африке нет цветных адвокатов.
There are no colored attorneys in South Africa.
لا يوجد محامون ملونون في جنوب أفريقيا.
Сидите там, где вам положено!
Sit where you belong!
اجلس حيث تنتمي!
- Я отнесу ваш багаж обратно, сэр. - Нет.
-l'll take your luggage back, sir.
-No.
-سأستعيد أمتعتك، سيدي. -لا.
Минуту, пожалуйста.
Just a moment, please.
لحظة من فضلك.
Понимаете?
You see?
هل ترى؟
Мохандас К. Ганди, адвокат.
Mohandas K. Gandhi, attorney at law.
موهانداس ك. غاندي، محامي.
Я собираюсь вести дело для индийской торговой фирмы.
I'm going to conduct a case for an lndian trading firm.
سأقوم بإجراء دراسة حالة لشركة تجارية هندية.
Ты что, не расслышал? В Южной Африке нет цветных адвокатов.
Didn't you hear me? There are no colored attorneys in South Africa.
ألم تسمعني؟ لا يوجد محامون ملونون في جنوب أفريقيا.
Меня пригласили в коллегию адвокатов в Лондоне...
I was called to the bar in London...
لقد تم استدعائي إلى نقابة المحامين في لندن...
...и поступил на службу в Высокий канцелярский суд.
...and enrolled at the High Court of Chancery.
...وتم تسجيله في المحكمة العليا.
Поэтому я — адвокат.
I am, therefore, an attorney.
أنا، بالتالي، محامي.
И поскольку в твоих глазах я цветной...
And since l am, in your eyes, colored...
وبما أنني في عينيك ملون...
...я думаю, мы можем сделать вывод, что, по крайней мере...
...l think we can deduce there is at least...
...أعتقد أننا يمكن أن نستنتج أن هناك على الأقل...
...один цветной адвокат в Южной Африке.
...one colored attorney in South Africa.
...محامي ملون واحد في جنوب أفريقيا.
Чертов умный кафр!
Smart bloody Kaffir!
كافر ذكي دموي!
Выгоните его.
Throw him out.
اطرده.
Просто перемести свою черную задницу обратно в третий класс...
Just move your black ass back to third class...
فقط قم بإرجاع مؤخرتك السوداء إلى الدرجة الثالثة...
...или я высажу тебя на следующей станции.
...or l'll have you thrown off at the next station.
... أو سأقوم بطردك في المحطة التالية.
Но я всегда летаю первым классом!
But l always go first class!
ولكنني دائمًا أذهب إلى الدرجة الأولى!
Но ты же богатый человек. Зачем терпеть?
But you're a rich man.
Why put up with it?
لكنك رجل غني، فلماذا تصبر على هذا؟
Да, я богат. Но я индиец.
Yes, l am rich. But l am lndian.
نعم، أنا غني. لكنني هندي.
Я не собираюсь путешествовать первым классом.
I do not expect to travel first class.
لا أتوقع أن أسافر في الدرجة الأولى.
-В Англии я был плохим студентом. -Это была Англия.
-ln England, I was a poor student.
-That was England.
-في إنجلترا، كنت طالبًا فقيرًا. -كانت تلك إنجلترا.
Это часть Английской империи.
This is part of England's Empire.
وهذا جزء من إمبراطورية إنجلترا.
Господин Ганди, посмотрите на господина Хана и вы увидите успешного мусульманского торговца.
Mr. Gandhi, you look at Mr. Khan and you see a successful Muslim trader.
السيد غاندي، عندما تنظر إلى السيد خان، تجد تاجرًا مسلمًا ناجحًا.
Большинство южноафриканцев видят в нем просто индийца.
Most South Africans see him simply as an Indian.
معظم سكان جنوب أفريقيا ينظرون إليه باعتباره هنديًا فقط.
И подавляющее большинство индийцев, в основном индуистов, таких как вы...
And the vast majority of Indians, mostly Hindus, like yourself...
والأغلبية العظمى من الهنود، ومعظمهم من الهندوس، مثلك...
...были привезены сюда для работы на шахтах и ​​сбора урожая.
...were brought here to work mines and harvest crops.
...تم جلبهم إلى هنا للعمل في المناجم وحصاد المحاصيل.
Большинство европейцев не хотят, чтобы они занимались чем-то другим.
Most Europeans don't want them doing anything else.
معظم الأوروبيين لا يريدون منهم أن يفعلوا أي شيء آخر.
- Но это очень не по-христиански... - Господин Ганди, в этой стране...
-But that is very unchristian--
-Mr. Gandhi, in this country...
-لكن هذا غير مسيحي تمامًا-- -السيد غاندي، في هذا البلد...
...индейцам не разрешается ходить по тротуару с христианами.
...lndians are not allowed to walk along the pavement with a Christian.
...لا يُسمح للهنود بالسير على الرصيف مع مسيحي.
Вы имеете в виду, что нанимаете мистера Бейкера в качестве своего адвоката...
You mean, you employ Mr. Baker as your attorney...
هل تقصد أنك توظف السيد بيكر كمحاميك؟
...но вы не можете пойти с ним по улице?
...but you can't walk down the street with him?
...ولكن لا يمكنك المشي في الشارع معه؟
Ну, я могу.
Well, l can.
حسنا، أنا أستطيع.
Но я рискую, что кто-нибудь столкнет меня в канаву...
But l risk being kicked into the gutter by someone...
لكنني أخاطر بأن يركلني شخص ما في الحضيض...
...менее свят, чем мистер Бейкер.
...less holy than Mr. Baker.
... أقل قداسة من السيد بيكر.
Ну, тогда с этим нужно бороться.
Well, then it must be fought.
حسنًا، إذن يجب محاربته.
Мы дети Божьи, как и все остальные.
We are children of God like everyone else.
نحن أبناء الله مثل أي شخص آخر.
Слава Аллаху!
Allah be praised!
الحمد لله!
И какие батальоны вы призовете?
And what battalions will you call upon?
وما هي الكتائب التي ستستدعونها؟
Я напишу в прессу...
I will write to the press...
سأكتب للصحافة...
...здесь и в Англии.
...here and in England.
...هنا وفي إنجلترا.
Я обращусь в суд.
I will use the courts.
سأستخدم المحاكم.
Вы создадите много проблем. Наша позиция такова...
You'll cause a lot of trouble.
Our position is--
ستسبب الكثير من المتاعب. موقفنا هو...
Мы — члены Империи.
We are members of the Empire.
نحن أعضاء الإمبراطورية.
И мы происходим из древней цивилизации.
And we come from an ancient civilization.
ونحن نأتي من حضارة قديمة.
Почему бы нам не ходить по тротуарам, как другие люди?
Why should we not walk on the pavements like other men?
لماذا لا نمشي على الأرصفة مثل باقي الرجال؟
Мне больше нравится идея индийского адвоката в Южной Африке.
I rather like the idea of an Indian barrister in South Africa.
أنا أحب فكرة وجود محام هندي في جنوب أفريقيا.
Я уверен, что наше сообщество могло бы обеспечить вас работой на какое-то время...
I'm sure our community could keep you in work for some time...
أنا متأكد من أن مجتمعنا يمكن أن يبقيك في العمل لبعض الوقت...
...даже если вы доставили массу неприятностей.
...even if you caused a good deal of trouble.
... حتى لو تسببت في قدر كبير من المتاعب.
Особенно если вы доставили много неприятностей.
Especially if you caused a good deal of trouble.
وخاصة إذا كنت سبباً في قدر كبير من المتاعب.
Вот английский репортер. Я же говорил, что он придет.
There's the English reporter.
I told you he'd come.
هذا هو المراسل الإنجليزي. قلت لك إنه سيأتي.
Вы также сказали, что ваша статья привлечет тысячу человек.
You also said your article would draw a thousand people.
قلت أيضًا أن مقالتك ستجذب ألف شخص.
По крайней мере некоторые индусы привели с собой своих жен.
At least some of the Hindus brought their wives.
على الأقل بعض الهندوس أحضروا زوجاتهم.
Нет, я попросил жену это организовать.
No, I asked my wife to organize that.
لا، لقد طلبت من زوجتي أن تنظم ذلك.
Некоторые из них уезжают.
Some of them are leaving.
بعضهم يغادرون.
"Дамы и господа...
"Ladies and gentlemen...
"سيداتي وسادتي...
...мы попросили вас собраться здесь, чтобы помочь нам провозгласить наше право...
...we have asked you to gather here to help us proclaim our right...
...لقد طلبنا منكم أن تتجمعوا هنا لمساعدتنا في إعلان حقنا...
...чтобы с нами обращались как с равноправными гражданами Империи.
...to be treated as equal citizens of the Empire.
...أن يتم التعامل معهم كمواطنين متساوين في الإمبراطورية.
Мы не ищем конфликта.
We do not seek conflict.
نحن لا نسعى إلى الصراع.
Мы знаем мощь сил, противостоящих нам...
We know the strength of the forces arrayed against us...
نحن نعلم قوة القوات المصطفة ضدنا...
...знаем, что из-за них мы можем действовать только мирными средствами.
...know that because of them, we can only use peaceful means.
... واعلم أنه بسببهم لا نستطيع أن نستخدم إلا الوسائل السلمية.
Но мы полны решимости восторжествовать.
But we are determined that justice will be done.
لكننا مصممون على تحقيق العدالة.
Символ нашего статуса воплощен в этом пропуске...
The symbol of our status is embodied in this pass...
يتجسد رمز مكانتنا في هذا الممر...
...который мы должны всегда иметь при себе...
...which we must carry at all times...
...والتي يجب علينا أن نحملها في جميع الأوقات...
...но ни одному европейцу это даже не нужно.
...but which no European even has to have.
...ولكن لا ينبغي لأي أوروبي أن يمتلكها.
Первый шаг к изменению нашего статуса...
The first step towards changing our status...
الخطوة الأولى نحو تغيير وضعنا...
...устранить это различие между нами».
...is to eliminate this difference between us."
...هو إزالة هذا الاختلاف بيننا."
Сейчас?
Now?
الآن؟
Вы блестяще пишете, но вам еще многому предстоит научиться в общении с мужчинами.
You write brilliantly, but you have much to learn about handling men.
لقد كتبت بشكل رائع، ولكن لا يزال أمامك الكثير لتتعلمه حول التعامل مع الرجال.
«Мы не хотим разжигать...
"We do not want to ignite...
"نحن لا نريد أن نشعل..."
...страх или ненависть к кому-либо.
...the fear or hatred of anyone.
...الخوف أو الكراهية من أي شخص.
Но мы просим вас...
But we ask you...
ولكننا نسألك...
...индуисты, мусульмане и сикхи...
...Hindu, Muslim and Sikh...
... الهندوس والمسلمين والسيخ...
...чтобы помочь нам осветить небо...
...to help us light up the sky...
...ليساعدنا على إضاءة السماء...
...и умы британских властей...
...and the minds of the British authorities...
...وعقول السلطات البريطانية...
...с нашим вызовом этой несправедливости».
...with our defiance of this injustice."
...مع تحدينا لهذا الظلم."
Теперь мы сожжем пропуска нашего комитета и его сторонников.
We will now burn the passes of our committee and its supporters.
سنقوم الآن بحرق تصاريح لجنتنا وأنصارها.
Мы просим вас сжечь ваши пропуска.
We ask you to put your passes on the fire--
نطلب منكم أن تضعوا بطاقاتكم على النار--
Ты чертов пес!
You bloody dog!
أيها الكلب اللعين!
Эти пропуски...
Those passes...
تلك التمريرات...
...являются государственной собственностью!
...are government property!
...هي ممتلكات حكومية!
И я арестую первого, кто попытается его сжечь!
And l will arrest the first man who tries to burn one!
وسوف أعتقل أول رجل يحاول حرق أحدهم!
Уведите его.
Take him away.
خذه بعيدا.
Ты, маленький...
You little...
أنت صغير...
...Сэмми...
...Sammy...
...سامي...
...сволочь!
...bastard!
...نذل!
Сейчас! Есть еще?
Now! Are there any more?
الآن! هل هناك المزيد؟
Если вам нужны такие неприятности, вы их получите.
If you want this kind of trouble, you can have it.
إذا كنت تريد هذا النوع من المتاعب، يمكنك الحصول عليه.
Отпустите меня!
Let me go!
دعني أذهب!
Останавливаться.
Stop.
قف.
Лондонские газеты прибыли с Мыса.
The London papers have arrived from the Cape.
وصلت الصحف اللندنية من كيب تاون.
Хуже всего было в Daily Mail. Они сказали, что сжигание пропусков...
The worstwas the Daily Mail.
They said the burning of passes...
الأسوأ كان صحيفة ديلي ميل. قالوا إن حرق التمريرات...
-Попросите господина Герцога встретиться со мной. -...был самым значительным актом...
-Ask Mr. Herzog to see me.
-...was the most significant act...
-اطلب من السيد هيرزوغ أن يراني. -...كان هذا هو الفعل الأكثر أهمية...
...в колониальных делах со времени провозглашения независимости.
...in colonial affairs since the Declaration of Independence.
...في الشؤون الاستعمارية منذ إعلان الاستقلال.
Они увидят, что на этот раз мы лучше подготовлены.
They'll find we're better prepared this time.
وسوف يجدون أننا مستعدون بشكل أفضل هذه المرة.
Господин Ганди обнаружит, что ему предстоит долгое время скрываться от реальности.
Mr. Gandhi will find he's on a long hiding to nothing.
سيجد السيد غاندي أنه يختبئ لفترة طويلة دون أن يجد شيئا.
«Судья Высокого суда подтвердил, что г-н Ганди...
"A High Court judge confirmed that Mr. Gandhi...
"أكد أحد قضاة المحكمة العليا أن السيد غاندي...
...он имел бы полное право возбудить уголовное дело за нападение...
...would've been within his rights to prosecute for assault...
...كان من حقه أن يقاضي بتهمة الاعتداء...
...поскольку ни он, ни г-н Хан не оказали сопротивления при аресте».
...since neither he nor Mr. Khan resisted arrest."
...حيث لم يقاوم هو والسيد خان الاعتقال.
Я рассказывал вам об английском праве.
I told you about English law.
لقد أخبرتك عن القانون الإنجليزي.
Как я уже рассказывал вам об английских полицейских.
As l told you about English policemen.
كما أخبرتك عن رجال الشرطة الإنجليز.
Да?
Yes?
نعم؟
Мы очень рады твоему возвращению, папа.
We're very pleased to have you back, Papa.
نحن سعداء جدًا بعودتك يا بابا.
И я рад вернуться.
And l am glad to be back.
وأنا سعيد بالعودة.
Приходить.
Come.
يأتي.
Берегите свое лицо.
Mind your face.
انتبه لوجهك.
Завтра я расскажу вам о своих днях в полицейском госпитале.
Tomorrow l'll tell you about my days in a police hospital.
غدا سأخبركم عن أيامي في مستشفى الشرطة.
Как, как.
Come, come.
كيف، كيف.
Как настоящие английские джентльмены. Я горжусь ими.
Just like proper English gentlemen.
I'm proud of them.
تمامًا مثل السادة الإنجليز. أنا فخور بهم.
Они мальчики и они индийцы.
They're boys and they're lndian.
إنهم أولاد وهم هنود.
Ты снимешь это? Оно жмет каждый раз, когда я говорю.
Will you take this off?
It pinches every time l speak.
هل ستزيل هذا؟ يؤلمني كلما تكلمت.
У меня всё есть.
I've got it.
لقد حصلت عليه.
Вы были бы Ганди.
You'd be Gandhi.
سوف تكون غاندي.
Я думала, ты будешь крупнее.
I thought you'd be bigger.
اعتقدت أنك ستكون أكبر.
- Извините. - Нет, все в порядке.
-l'm sorry.
-No, that's all right.
-أنا آسف. -لا، لا بأس.
Меня зовут Чарли Эндрюс, сэр.
My name is Charlie Andrews, sir.
اسمي تشارلي أندروز، سيدي.
Я приехал из Индии.
I've come from lndia.
لقد جئت من الهند.
Я много читал о вас.
I've read a great deal about you.
لقد قرأت الكثير عنك.
Надеюсь, что-то из этого хорошее.
Some of it good, l hope.
بعضها جيد، آمل ذلك.
Хотите прогуляться?
Would you care to walk?
هل ترغب في المشي؟
- Вы священнослужитель? - Да.
-You're a clergyman?
-Yes.
-أنت رجل دين؟ -نعم.
В Индии я встретил замечательных людей.
I met some remarkable people in India.
لقد التقيت ببعض الأشخاص المميزين في الهند.
И когда я прочитал, чем вы занимаетесь, мне захотелось помочь.
And when I read what you were doing,
I wanted to help.
وعندما قرأت ما كنت تفعله، أردت المساعدة.
- Тебя это удивляет? - Уже нет.
-Does that surprise you?
-Not anymore.
-هل هذا يفاجئك؟ -ليس بعد الآن.
Сначала я был поражен...
At first, I was amazed...
في البداية كنت مندهشا...
...но когда ты сражаешься за правое дело...
...but when you're fighting in a just cause...
...ولكن عندما تقاتل من أجل قضية عادلة...
...люди, как и вы, словно выскакивают прямо из-под тротуара.
...people seem to pop up, like you, right out of the pavement.
...يبدو أن الناس يظهرون فجأة، مثلك، من الرصيف.
Даже если это опасно или...
Even when it's dangerous or....
حتى عندما يكون الأمر خطيرًا أو...
Эй, смотрите, что будет!
Hey, look what's coming!
مهلا، انظر ماذا سيأتي!
Белая овчарка ведет коричневого Сэмми!
A white shepherd leading a brown Sammy!
راعي أبيض يقود سامي بني!
- Возможно, нам следует... - Разве в Новом Завете не сказано:
-Perhaps we should....
-Doesn't the New Testament say:
-ربما ينبغي لنا أن نفعل ذلك....-ألم يقل العهد الجديد:
«Если враг ударит тебя по правой щеке, подставь ему левую»?
"If your enemy strikes you on the right cheek, offer him the left"?
"إذا ضربك عدوك على خدك الأيمن فأدر له الأيسر"؟
Фраза была использована метафорически. Я не думаю, что наш Господь...
The phrase was used metaphorically.
I don't think our Lord--
استُخدمت العبارة مجازيًا. لا أعتقد أن ربنا...
Я не уверен. Я много думал об этом.
I'm not so sure.
I have thought about it a great deal.
لست متأكدًا تمامًا. لقد فكرت في الأمر كثيرًا.
Подозреваю, он имел в виду, что вы должны проявить мужество...
I suspect he meant you must show courage...
أظن أنه يقصد أنه يجب عليك إظهار الشجاعة...
...будьте готовы принять удар, несколько ударов, чтобы показать...
...be willing to take a blow, several blows, to show...
... كن مستعدًا لتلقي ضربة، عدة ضربات، لإظهار...
...ты не нанесешь ответного удара, и тебя не отвратишь.
...you won't strike back, nor will you be turned aside.
... لن تضرب ولن تتراجع.
И когда вы это делаете, это взывает к чему-то в человеческой природе...
And when you do that, it calls on something in human nature...
وعندما تفعل ذلك، فإنك تستدعي شيئًا في الطبيعة البشرية...
...это уменьшит его ненависть к вам и увеличит его уважение.
...that makes his hatred for you decrease and his respect increase.
... مما يجعل كراهيته لك تقل واحترامه لك يزيد.
Я думаю, Христос это понял, и я видел, как это работает.
I think Christ grasped that, and l have seen it work.
أعتقد أن المسيح أدرك ذلك، وقد رأيته يعمل.
Доброе утро.
Good morning.
صباح الخير.
Уйди с тротуара, чертов енот.
Get off the pavement, you bloody coon.
انزل من الرصيف أيها الراكون اللعين.
- Да, отвали. - Кафр!
-Yeah, get off.
-Kaffir!
-نعم، انزل. -كافير!
- Колин, что ты делаешь? - Ничего.
-Colin, what you doing?
-Nothing.
-كولين ماذا تفعل؟ -لا شيء.
Выходи туда, где я тебя вижу!
Come out where l can see you!
تعال إلى حيث أستطيع رؤيتك!
Я спросил: «Что ты делаешь?»
I said, what you doing?
قلت ماذا تفعل؟
Мы просто пытались навести порядок в районе.
We were just trying to clean up the neighborhood.
كنا نحاول فقط تنظيف الحي.
Ты опоздал на работу. Я думал, ты ушёл 10 минут назад.
You're late for work.
I thought you'd gone 1 0 minutes ago.
لقد تأخرت عن العمل. ظننت أنك غادرت منذ ١٠ دقائق.
Ладить!
Get on!
هيا!
Вы увидите, что для нас всех хватит места.
You'll find there's room for us all.
ستجد أن هناك مكانًا لنا جميعًا.
- Вот это удача. - Я думал, ты человек Божий.
-That was lucky.
-l thought you were a man of God.
-لقد كان ذلك محظوظا. -اعتقدت أنك رجل الله.
Да, но я не настолько эгоистичен, чтобы думать...
I am, but l'm not so egotistical as to think...
أنا كذلك، ولكنني لست أنانيًا إلى درجة التفكير...
...он планирует свой день вокруг моих дилемм.
...he plans his day around my dilemmas.
...يخطط يومه حول معضلتي.
Полагаю, это можно назвать коммунальной фермой.
You could call it a communal farm, l suppose.
يمكنك أن تسميها مزرعة مشتركة، على ما أعتقد.
Но вы все пришли к одним и тем же выводам.
But you've all come to the same conclusions.
لكنكم جميعا توصلتم إلى نفس الاستنتاجات.
Наша Гита, Коран мусульман, ваша Библия.
Our Gita, the Muslim's Koran, your Bible.
جيتا لدينا، قرآن المسلمين، الكتاب المقدس الخاص بك.
Простые вещи всегда захватывают дух.
It's always the simple things that catch your breath.
إنها دائمًا الأشياء البسيطة التي تلتقط أنفاسك.
«Возлюби ближнего своего, как самого себя».
"Love thy neighbor as thyself."
"أحب قريبك كنفسك."
Не всегда это практикуется...
Not always practiced...
لا يتم ممارستها دائما...
...но это то, чему мы, индусы, могли бы многому научиться.
...but it's something we Hindus could learn a lot from.
...ولكن هذا شيء يمكننا نحن الهندوس أن نتعلم منه الكثير.
Это то, что вы ищете на этой ферме?
That's the kind of thing you'll be seeking on this farm?
هذا هو نوع الشيء الذي ستبحث عنه في هذه المزرعة؟
Ну что ж, попробуем.
Well, we shall try.
حسنا، سوف نحاول.
Боюсь, у меня плохие новости.
Bad news, I'm afraid.
أخبار سيئة، أخشى ذلك.
Они собираются изменить законы о пропусках.
They're going to change the pass laws.
إنهم سوف يغيرون قوانين المرور.
Это заняло время, но сделать это нужно было справедливо.
It's taken time, but it needed to be done fairly.
لقد استغرق الأمر بعض الوقت، ولكن كان من الضروري القيام به بشكل عادل.
Мы не хотели создавать несправедливость только потому, что г-н Ганди...
We didn't want to create an injustice simply because Mr. Gandhi...
لم نكن نريد أن نخلق ظلمًا لمجرد أن السيد غاندي...
...нарушал наше действующее законодательство.
...was abusing our existing legislation.
... كان يستغل تشريعاتنا الحالية.
Одну минуточку, сэр, пожалуйста.
Just one moment, sir, please.
لحظة واحدة فقط، سيدي، من فضلك.
Извините.
I beg your pardon.
أستميحك عذرا.
Но в короткой поездке...
But on a short trip...
ولكن في رحلة قصيرة...
...я бы не стал тратить слишком много времени на индейский вопрос, мистер Уокер.
...l wouldn't spend too much time on the Indian question, Mr. Walker.
...لن أقضي الكثير من الوقت في الحديث عن المسألة الهندية، يا سيد ووكر.
В Южной Африке это незначительный фактор.
It's a tiny factor in South Africa.
إنه عامل صغير في جنوب أفريقيا.
Ну, на данный момент это новости.
Well, it is news at the moment.
حسنًا، إنه خبر في الوقت الحالي.
Я планирую доложить о состоянии шахт здесь...
I plan to report on the condition of the mines here...
أخطط للإبلاغ عن حالة المناجم هنا...
-...а также экономика. -Хорошо.
-...as well as the economy.
-Good.
-...وكذلك الاقتصاد. -جيد.
Но я хотел бы встретиться с этим мистером Гэндаем.
But l would like to meet this Mr. Gand-eye.
ولكنني أرغب في مقابلة السيد غاند آي هذا.
-Ганди. -Ганди.
-Gandhi.
-غاندي. -غاندي.
Конечно. У нас, западных людей, есть слабость...
Of course.
We Westerners have a weakness...
بالطبع. نحن الغربيون لدينا نقطة ضعف...
...для этих духовно настроенных мужчин Индии.
...for these spiritually inclined men of lndia.
...لهؤلاء الرجال ذوي الميول الروحية في الهند.
Но как старый юрист, позвольте мне вас предупредить.
But as an old lawyer, let me warn you.
ولكن باعتباري محاميًا عجوزًا، اسمح لي أن أحذرك.
Господин Ганди — самый проницательный человек, которого вы когда-либо встречали...
Mr. Gandhi is as shrewd a man as you will ever meet...
السيد غاندي هو رجل ذكي للغاية سوف تقابله على الإطلاق...
...каким бы потусторонним он ни казался.
...however otherworldly he may seem.
... مهما بدا وكأنه من عالم آخر.
Но я уверен, что вы достаточно опытный репортер, чтобы это заметить.
But l'm sure you're enough of a reporter to see that.
ولكنني متأكد من أنك مراسل كافٍ لرؤية ذلك.
Надеюсь. Спасибо за ваше время, сэр.
I hope so.
Thank you for your time, sir.
آمل ذلك. شكرًا لوقتك، سيدي.
Так что это не спиритуализм и не национализм.
So it's not spiritualism or nationalism.
لذا فالأمر لا يتعلق بالروحانية أو القومية.
Мы не сопротивляемся ничему, кроме идеи, что люди не могут жить вместе.
We're not resisting anything but the idea that people can't live together.
نحن لا نقاوم أي شيء سوى فكرة أن الناس لا يستطيعون العيش معًا.
Понимаете?
You see?
هل ترى؟
Индуисты, мусульмане...
Hindus, Muslims...
الهندوس، المسلمون...
...сикхи, евреи...
...Sikhs, Jews...
...السيخ واليهود...
...даже христиане.
...even Christians.
...حتى المسيحيين.
Г-н Уокер из New York Times.
Mr. Walker of the New York Times.
السيد ووكر من صحيفة نيويورك تايمز.
Как дела?
How you doing?
كيف حالك؟
Без бумаги, без какого-либо журнала...
Without a paper, a journal of some kind...
بدون ورقة، أو مجلة من نوع ما...
...вы не можете объединить сообщество.
...you cannot unite a community.
...لا يمكنك توحيد المجتمع.
Вы принадлежите к очень важной профессии.
You belong to a very important profession.
أنت تنتمي إلى مهنة مهمة جدًا.
А что, по-вашему, должен написать важный профессионал...
And what do you think an important professional should write...
وما رأيك أن يكتب شخص محترف مهم...
...о вашей реакции на новейшее законодательство генерала Смэтса?
...about your response to
General Smuts' newest legislation?
... حول ردك على التشريع الأحدث للجنرال سموتس؟
Я не знаю.
I don't know.
لا أعرف.
Я все еще ищу ответ.
I'm still searching for a response.
لا أزال أبحث عن رد.
Вы будете уважать закон?
You will respect the law?
هل ستحترم القانون؟
Существуют несправедливые законы, как и несправедливые люди.
There are unjust laws as there are unjust men.
هناك قوانين ظالمة كما يوجد رجال ظالمون.
Вы — незначительное меньшинство, которое может бросить вызов правительству Южной Африки...
You're a small minority to take on the South African government...
أنتم أقلية صغيرة لتواجهوا الحكومة في جنوب أفريقيا...
-...не говоря уже о Британской империи. -Если вы меньшинство из одного...
-...not to mention the British Empire.
-lf you are a minority of one...
-...ناهيك عن الإمبراطورية البريطانية. -إذا كنت أقلية من شخص واحد...
...правда есть правда.
...the truth is the truth.
...الحقيقة هي الحقيقة.
Герман Калленбах...
Herman Kallenbach...
هيرمان كالينباخ...
...наш главный плотник, а также наш главный благодетель.
...our chief carpenter, also our chief benefactor.
...نجارنا الرئيسي، وهو أيضًا المحسن الرئيسي لدينا.
Винс Уокер, New York Times.
Vince Walker, New York Times.
فينس ووكر، نيويورك تايمز.
У вас тут очень интересное место.
This is quite a place you've got here.
هذا هو المكان الذي حصلت عليه هنا.
И вы называете это ашрамом?
And you call it an ashram?
وتسميها اشرم؟
Правильно. Это слово означает только «сообщество».
That's right.
The word only means "community."
هذا صحيح. الكلمة تعني فقط "المجتمع".
Но это может означать «деревня» или «мир».
But it could stand for
"village" or "the world."
ولكنها قد تعني "القرية" أو "العالم".
Вы амбициозный человек, мистер Ганди.
You're an ambitious man, Mr. Gandhi.
أنت رجل طموح يا سيد غاندي.
Надеюсь, что нет.
I hope not.
آمل أن لا.
Я слышал, что вы также готовите еду и убираете туалеты.
I hear that you also prepare the meals and clean the toilets.
سمعت أنك تقوم أيضًا بإعداد وجبات الطعام وتنظيف المراحيض.
-Это часть эксперимента? -Ба!
-ls that part of the experiment?
-Ba!
-هل هذا جزء من التجربة؟ -با!
Нам понадобится еще одно место для водителя мистера Уокера.
We will need another place set for Mr. Walker's driver.
سوف نحتاج إلى مكان آخر مخصص لسائق السيد ووكر.
Я скажу Таре.
I will tell Tara.
سأخبر تارا.
Да, это один из способов узнать, что труд каждого человека...
Yes, it's one way to learn that each man's labor...
نعم، إنها إحدى الطرق لتعلم أن عمل كل رجل...
...так же важен, как и чей-то другой.
...is as important as another's.
...هو بنفس أهمية الآخرين.
Пока вы это делаете, чистите туалет...
While you're doing it, cleaning the toilet...
بينما تقوم بذلك، تنظيف المرحاض...
...кажется гораздо важнее закона.
...seems far more important than the law.
...يبدو أنه أكثر أهمية من القانون.
Пожалуйста, присоединяйтесь к нам.
Please, come and join us.
من فضلك، تعال وانضم إلينا.
Вам понадобится что-то перед обратным путем.
You'll need something before your journey back.
سوف تحتاج إلى شيء ما قبل رحلة العودة.
- Извините, пожалуйста? - Да, конечно.
-Would you excuse me, please?
-Yeah, sure.
-هل تسمح لي من فضلك؟ -نعم بالتأكيد.
Что это такое?
What is it?
ما هذا؟
Сору послали сказать мне, что я должен...
Sora was sent to tell me l must...
لقد تم إرسال سورا ليخبرني أنني يجب أن ...
...разгрести и засыпать мусором туалет.
...rake and cover the latrine.
...أشعل النار وغطي المرحاض.
Правильно. Каждый делает свою очередь.
That's right.
Everyone takes their turn.
هذا صحيح. الجميع يأخذ دوره.
Это дело рук неприкасаемых!
It is the work of untouchables!
إنه عمل المنبوذين!
В этом месте нет неприкасаемых...
In this place, there are no untouchables...
في هذا المكان لا يوجد أي أحد لا يمكن المساس به...
...и никакая работа не будет ниже чести у нас.
...and no work is beneath any of us.
...ولا يوجد عمل أدنى من أي منا.
Я твоя жена!
I'm your wife!
انا زوجتك!
Тем более есть причины.
All the more reason.
كلما زاد السبب.
Как прикажете.
As you command.
كما تأمر.
Другие могут следовать за вами, но вы забываете...
The others may follow you, but you forget...
قد يتبعك الآخرون، ولكنك تنسى...
...я знал тебя, когда ты был мальчиком.
...l knew you when you were a boy.
... لقد عرفتك عندما كنت صبيا.
Это не я.
It's not me.
إنه ليس أنا.
Это принцип.
It's the principle.
إنه المبدأ.
И вы сделаете это с радостью или не сделаете вообще.
And you will do it with joy or not do it at all.
وسوف تفعل ذلك بفرح أو لا تفعله على الإطلاق.
Тогда нет.
Not at all then.
ليس على الإطلاق إذن.
Ну ладно, иди. Тебе здесь не место!
All right then, go.
You don't belong here!
حسناً إذًا، اذهب. أنت لا تنتمي إلى هنا!
Иди и покинь ашрам вообще. Ты нам не нужен!
Go and leave the ashram altogether.
We don't want you!
اذهب واخرج من الأشرم تمامًا. لا نريدك!
Неужели тебе не стыдно?
Have you no shame?
هل ليس لديك خجل؟
Я твоя жена!
I'm your wife!
انا زوجتك!
Куда, по-вашему, я пойду?
Where do you expect me to go?
أين تتوقع مني أن أذهب؟
Что со мной не так?
What's the matter with me?
ماذا حدث معي؟
Ты человек.
You're human.
أنت إنسان.
Только человек.
Only human.
الإنسان فقط.
А для нас это еще сложнее...
And it's even harder for those of us...
وهو أصعب بالنسبة لنا...
...которые даже не хотят быть такими же хорошими, как вы.
...who do not even want to be as good as you do.
...الذين لا يريدون حتى أن يكونوا جيدين مثلك.
Я прошу прощения.
I apologize.
أنا أعتذر.
Мне нужно вернуться к этому репортеру.
I must get back to that reporter.
يجب أن أعود إلى هذا المراسل.
И я должен...
And l must...
ويجب علي...
...разгрести и засыпать мусором туалет.
...rake and cover the latrine.
...أشعل النار وغطي المرحاض.
Я хочу поприветствовать вас всех.
I want to welcome you all.
أريد أن أرحب بكم جميعا.
Каждый из вас.
Every one of you.
كل واحد منكم.
У нас нет секретов.
We have no secrets.
ليس لدينا أسرار.
Давайте начнем с ясности...
Let us begin by being clear...
دعونا نبدأ بالوضوح...
...о новом законе генерала Смэтса.
...about General Smuts' new law.
...حول قانون الجنرال سموتس الجديد.
Теперь всем индийцам придется сдавать отпечатки пальцев...
All Indians must now be fingerprinted...
يجب الآن على جميع الهنود أن يحصلوا على بصمات الأصابع...
...как преступники.
...like criminals.
... مثل المجرمين.
Мужчины и женщины.
Men and women.
الرجال والنساء.
Никакой другой брак, кроме христианского, не считается действительным.
No marriage other than a Christian marriage is considered valid.
لا يعتبر أي زواج غير الزواج المسيحي صحيحا.
В соответствии с этим законом...
Under this act...
وبموجب هذا القانون...
...наши жены и матери — шлюхи.
...our wives and mothers are whores.
... زوجاتنا وأمهاتنا عاهرات.
И каждый мужчина здесь — ублюдок.
And every man here is a bastard.
وكل رجل هنا هو لقيط.
Он достиг в этом большого успеха.
He has become quite good at this.
لقد أصبح جيدًا جدًا في هذا.
И полицейский...
And a policeman...
وشرطي...
...проходя мимо индейского жилища--
...passing an Indian dwelling--
...مرورًا بمسكن هندي--
Я не буду называть их домами.
I will not call them homes.
لن أسميهم منازل.
--может войти и потребовать карточку у любой индийской женщины, чье жилище там находится.
--may enter and demand the card of any lndian woman whose dwelling it is.
--يجوز له الدخول والمطالبة ببطاقة أي امرأة هندية تسكن في هذا المكان.
Черт бы их побрал!
Goddamn them!
لعنة الله عليهم!
Понимать...
Understand...
يفهم...
...ему не обязательно стоять у двери.
...he does not have to stand at the door.
...لا يجب عليه الوقوف عند الباب.
Он может войти.
He may enter.
يجوز له الدخول.
Я этого не допущу!
I will not allow it!
لن اسمح بذلك!
Клянусь Аллахом.
I swear to Allah.
والله المستعان.
Я убью человека, который оскорбит мой дом и мою жену...
I'll kill the man who offers that insult to my home and my wife...
سأقتل الرجل الذي يقدم هذه الإهانة لبيتي وزوجتي...
...и пусть меня повесят!
...and let them hang me!
...وليشنقوني!
Я говорю, что разговоры ничего не значат!
I say talk means nothing!
أقول أن الحديث لا يعني شيئا!
Убейте нескольких чиновников, прежде чем они опозорят одну индийскую женщину.
Kill a few officials before they disgrace one lndian woman.
اقتل بعض المسؤولين قبل أن يفضحوا امرأة هندية واحدة.
Тогда они, возможно, дважды подумают о принятии таких законов.
Then they might think twice about such laws.
ثم عليهم أن يفكروا مرتين بشأن مثل هذه القوانين.
Ради этого я готов умереть!
In that cause,
I would be willing to die!
وفي سبيل هذا السبب، سأكون على استعداد للموت!
Я восхваляю такую ​​смелость.
I praise such courage.
أشيد بهذه الشجاعة.
Мне нужна такая смелость...
I need such courage...
أحتاج إلى مثل هذه الشجاعة...
...потому что ради этого дела я тоже готов умереть.
...because, in this cause,
I too am prepared to die.
...لأنني في هذه القضية مستعد للموت أيضًا.
Но, мой друг...
But, my friend...
ولكن يا صديقي...
...нет такой причины, за которую я готов убивать.
...there is no cause for which
I am prepared to kill.
...لا يوجد سبب يجعلني مستعدًا للقتل.
Что бы они с нами ни сделали...
Whatever they do to us...
مهما فعلوا بنا...
...мы ни на кого не нападем...
...we will attack no one...
... لن نهاجم أحدا...
...никого не убивать.
...kill no one.
...لا تقتل أحدا.
Но мы не дадим свои отпечатки пальцев, никто из нас.
But we will not give our fingerprints, not one of us.
ولكننا لن نعطي بصماتنا، ولا بصمات أحدنا.
Они посадят нас в тюрьму. Они оштрафуют нас. Они конфискуют наше имущество.
They will imprison us. They will fine us. They will seize our possessions.
سيسجنوننا، سيغرّموننا، سيصادرون ممتلكاتنا.
Но они не могут отнять у нас самоуважение...
But they cannot take away our self-respect...
لكنهم لا يستطيعون أن يسلبوا منا احترامنا لأنفسنا...
...если мы им этого не дадим.
...if we do not give it to them.
...إذا لم نعطيهم إياه.
Вы были в тюрьме?
Have you been to prison?
هل ذهبت إلى السجن؟
Они нас бьют и пытают. Я говорю--
They beat us and torture us.
I say--
لقد ضربونا وعذبونا. أقول-
Я призываю вас бороться.
I am asking you to fight.
أطلب منك القتال.
Бороться с их гневом, а не провоцировать его.
To fight against their anger, not to provoke it.
لمحاربة غضبهم، وليس لإثارته.
Мы не нанесем удара.
We will not strike a blow.
لن نوجه ضربة.
Но мы их примем.
But we will receive them.
ولكننا سوف نستقبلهم.
И сквозь нашу боль...
And through our pain...
ومن خلال آلامنا...
...мы заставим их увидеть свою несправедливость.
...we will make them see their injustice.
...سنريهم ظلمهم.
И это будет больно...
And it will hurt...
وسوف يؤلم...
...так как любая драка причиняет боль.
...as all fighting hurts.
...كما أن كل القتال مؤلم.
Но мы не можем проиграть.
But we cannot lose.
ولكننا لا يمكن أن نخسر.
Мы не можем.
We cannot.
نحن لا نستطيع.
Они могут истязать мое тело...
They may torture my body...
قد يعذبون جسدي...
...сломать мне кости...
...break my bones...
...كسر عظامي...
...даже убить меня. Тогда...
...even kill me. Then...
...حتى اقتلني. ثم...
...они заберут мой труп...
...they will have my dead body...
...سيحصلون على جثتي...
...не мое послушание.
...not my obedience.
...ليس طاعتي.
Мы индуисты и мусульмане...
We are Hindu and Muslim...
نحن هندوس ومسلمون...
...дети Божьи, каждый из нас.
...children of God, each one of us.
...أبناء الله، كل واحد منا.
Давайте принесем торжественную клятву во имя его...
Let us take a solemn oath in his name...
فلنحلف باسمه اليمين المقدس...
...чтобы ни случилось...
...that, come what may...
...هذا، مهما حدث...
...мы не подчинимся этому закону.
...we will not submit to this law.
... لن نخضع لهذا القانون.
Боже, храни нашего милостивого короля.
God save our gracious King
حفظ الله ملكنا الكريم
Боже, храни нашего благородного короля.
God save our noble King
حفظ الله ملكنا النبيل
Боже, храни нашего короля
God save our King
حفظ الله ملكنا
Эти мужчины — наемные рабочие.
These men are contracted laborers.
هؤلاء الرجال هم عمال متعاقدون.
Их место в шахтах.
They belong in the mines.
إنهم ينتمون إلى المناجم.
Вы посадили их товарищей в тюрьму.
You put their comrades in jail.
لقد وضعت رفاقهم في السجن.
Когда вы их освободите...
When you free them...
عندما تحررهم...
...они вернутся к работе.
...they will go back to work.
...سوف يعودون إلى العمل.
Я вас предупреждал.
I've warned you.
لقد حذرتك.
Мы предупредили друг друга.
We've warned each other.
لقد حذرنا بعضنا البعض.
Я не думаю, что это очень хорошо.
I don't think that's very good.
لا أعتقد أن هذا جيد جدًا.
Спокойно, спокойно.
Steady, steady.
ثابت، ثابت.
Останавливаться!
Stop!
قف!
На галопе, в атаку!
At the canter, charge!
عند الركض، هاجم!
Нам следует лечь. Лечь!
We should lie down. Down!
ينبغي علينا الاستلقاء. استلقي!
Лошади нас не растопчут. Ложись!
The horses won't trample on us.
Lie down!
لن تدوسنا الخيول. استلقِ!
Следуй за мной! Следуй за мной!
Follow me! Follow me!
اتبعني! اتبعني!
Что же нам теперь делать?
Now what the hell do we do?
والآن ماذا علينا أن نفعل؟
Пусть маршируют.
Let them march.
دعهم يسيرون.
В наше приятное время, по-нашему приятному пути...
In our own sweet time, in our own sweet way...
في وقتنا الجميل، بطريقتنا الجميلة...
...мы их достанем.
...we'll get them.
...سوف نحصل عليهم.
-Один закон! -Один король!
-One law!
-One king!
-قانون واحد! -ملك واحد!
Некоторые из вас, возможно, радуются тому, что г-на Ганди посадили в тюрьму.
Some of you may be rejoicing that
Mr. Gandhi has been put into prison.
ربما يفرح البعض منكم بسجن السيد غاندي.
Но я хотел бы попросить вас, собравшихся здесь, в этом доме Божьем...
But l would ask you, assembled here in this house of God...
ولكن أود أن أسألكم، المجتمعين هنا في بيت الله هذا...
...осознать, что мы являемся свидетелями чего-то нового...
...to recognize that we are witnessing something new...
...أن ندرك أننا نشهد شيئًا جديدًا...
...что-то настолько неожиданное, настолько необычное...
...something so unexpected, so unusual...
...شيء غير متوقع، غير عادي...
...что неудивительно, что правительство в растерянности.
...that it is not surprising the government is at a loss.
...وليس من المستغرب أن تجد الحكومة نفسها في حيرة من أمرها.
То, что г-н Ганди заставил нас сделать...
What Mr. Gandhi has forced us to do...
ما أجبرنا السيد غاندي على فعله...
...задавать вопросы о себе.
...is ask questions about ourselves.
...هو أن نسأل أسئلة عن أنفسنا.
Нам, христианам, трудно ответить на эти вопросы.
As Christians, those are difficult questions to answer.
باعتبارنا مسيحيين، هذه أسئلة من الصعب الإجابة عليها.
Как мы относимся к мужчинам, которые бросают вызов несправедливому закону...
How do we treat men who defy an unjust law...
كيف نتعامل مع الرجال الذين يتحدون القانون الظالم؟
...кто не будет сражаться...
...who will not fight...
...الذين لن يقاتلوا...
...но не подчинится?
...but will not comply?
...ولكن لن تمتثل؟
Как христиане или как люди, которые не слышали этого слова...
As Christians, or as people who have not heard the word--
كمسيحيين، أو كأشخاص لم يسمعوا الكلمة-
Я вижу, они никого не щадят.
They're sparing no one, l see.
إنهم لا يرحمون أحداً، كما أرى.
Нет, сюрпризом стали вы.
No, you were the surprise.
لا، لقد كنت المفاجأة.
Об этом стало известно по всей тюрьме.
It has been all over the prison.
لقد كان في جميع أنحاء السجن.
Мы думали, что они слишком боятся английской прессы.
We thought they'd be too afraid of the English press.
اعتقدنا أنهم سيكونون خائفين جدًا من الصحافة الإنجليزية.
Так же поступил и я.
So did l.
ففعلت ذلك.
Я не знаю, кого они оставили там, чтобы выполнить эту работу.
I don't know who they've left out there to do the work.
لا أعلم من تركوا هناك للقيام بالعمل.
- Они тронули женщин? - Моя жена публично бросила вызов закону.
-Have they touched the women?
-My wife publicly defied the law.
-هل لمسوا النساء؟ -زوجتي تحدت القانون علناً.
Они арестовали ее и еще четверых.
They've arrested her and four others.
لقد تم القبض عليها وعلى أربعة آخرين.
Это раскололо правительство.
It split the government.
لقد أدى إلى انقسام الحكومة.
Ну что ж, это одна победа.
Well, that's one victory.
حسنا، هذا انتصار واحد.
Если мы проявим твердость, это будет не последний раз.
If we hold firm, it won't be the last.
إذا تمسكنا بموقفنا، فلن يكون هذا هو الأخير.
Не волнуйся.
Don't worry.
لا تقلق.
Я никогда не видел столь решительных мужчин.
I've never seen men so determined.
لم أرى رجالاً مصممين هكذا من قبل.
Вы дали им возможность бороться.
You have given them a way to fight.
لقد أعطيتهم طريقة للقتال.
Ганди!
Gandhi!
غاندي!
Я хочу Ганди!
I want Gandhi!
أريد غاندي!
Какой именно Сэмми?
Which Sammy is it?
أي سامي هذا؟
Господин Ганди.
Mr. Gandhi.
السيد غاندي.
Я подумал, что мы могли бы немного поговорить.
I thought we might have a little talk.
اعتقدت أننا قد نجري محادثة قصيرة.
Спасибо, Дэниелс.
Thank you, Daniels.
شكرا لك، دانييلز.
Хотите бокал хереса?
Will you have a glass of sherry?
هل تريد كأس من الشيري؟
Спасибо, нет.
Thank you, no.
شكرا لك، لا.
- Может быть, чаю? - Я обедал в тюрьме.
-Perhaps some tea?
-l dined at the prison.
-ربما بعض الشاي؟ -تناولت العشاء في السجن.
Пожалуйста, проходите и садитесь.
Please, do come and sit down.
من فضلك تعال واجلس.
Господин Ганди.
Mr. Gandhi.
السيد غاندي.
Я более или менее решил просить Палату отменить этот закон...
I've more or less decided to ask the House to repeal the act...
لقد قررت تقريبًا أن أطلب من مجلس النواب إلغاء القانون ...
...что вызвало у вас такое недовольство.
...that you have taken such exception to.
...أنك اتخذت مثل هذا الاستثناء.
Ну, если вы попросили, генерал Смэтс, я уверен, что это будет сделано.
Well, if you asked, General Smuts,
I'm sure it will be done.
حسنًا، إذا سألت، يا جنرال سموتس، فأنا متأكد من أنه سيتم ذلك.
Все не так просто.
It's not quite that simple.
إن الأمر ليس بهذه البساطة.
Почему-то я этого не ожидал.
Somehow, I expected not.
بطريقة ما، لم أتوقع ذلك.
Я думал о создании королевской комиссии...
I thought of calling for a royal commission...
فكرت في المطالبة بتشكيل لجنة ملكية...
...для изучения нового законодательства.
...to investigate the new legislation.
...للتحقيق في التشريع الجديد.
Думаю, я могу гарантировать, что они порекомендуют отменить этот закон.
I think I could guarantee they would recommend the act be repealed.
أعتقد أنني أستطيع أن أضمن أنهم سيوصون بإلغاء القانون.
Я поздравляю их.
I congratulate them.
أهنئهم.
Но они также могут порекомендовать...
But they might also recommend...
ولكن قد يوصون أيضًا بـ...
...чтобы вся будущая иммиграция из Индии была строго ограничена...
...that all future lndian immigration be severely restricted...
...أن يتم تقييد جميع الهجرة الهندية المستقبلية بشكل صارم...
...даже остановился.
...even stopped.
...حتى توقفت.
Иммиграция не была тем вопросом, по которому мы боролись.
Immigration was not an issue on which we fought.
ولم تكن الهجرة قضية نناضل من أجلها.
Было бы неправильно с нашей стороны сделать его таковым теперь, когда мы...
It would be wrong of us to make it one, now that we....
سيكون من الخطأ أن نجعله كذلك، الآن وقد أصبحنا...
Мы находимся в выгодном положении.
We are in a position of advantage.
نحن في وضع مميز.
Я приказываю освободить всех заключенных в течение следующих 24 часов.
I'm ordering the release of all prisoners within the next 24 hours.
أمرت بالإفراج عن جميع السجناء خلال الـ24 ساعة القادمة.
С этого момента вы сами свободны.
You yourself are free as from this moment.
أنت حر نفسك اعتبارًا من هذه اللحظة.
Предположим, мы пришли к согласию.
Assuming we are in agreement.
على افتراض أننا متفقون.
Да, да.
Yes, yes.
نعم نعم.
Просто в этой одежде я бы предпочел поехать на такси.
It's just that in these clothes,
I would prefer to go by taxi.
فقط بهذه الملابس أفضّل أن أذهب بسيارة أجرة.
Ладно. Хорошо.
All right. Fine.
حسناً.
Боюсь, у меня нет денег.
I'm afraid I have no money.
أخشى أن ليس لدي مال.
Я тоже.
Neither have l.
لا يوجد لدي أي شيء.
Мне очень жаль.
I'm awfully sorry.
أنا آسف جدًا.
Дэниелс...
Daniels...
دانييلز...
...не одолжите ли вы мистеру Ганди шиллинг на такси?
...will you lend Mr. Gandhi a shilling for a taxi?
...هل تقرض السيد غاندي شلنًا لشراء سيارة أجرة؟
Прошу прощения, сэр?
I beg your pardon, sir?
أرجو المعذرة سيدي؟
Как далеко ты зайдешь, Ганди?
How far will you be going, Gandhi?
إلى أي مدى ستذهب يا غاندي؟
Теперь, когда все улажено, я серьезно задумался о возвращении в Индию.
Now that this is settled, l'd thought seriously of going back to lndia.
الآن بعد أن تم تسوية هذا الأمر، فكرت جديا في العودة إلى الهند.
Но на данный момент шиллинга будет вполне достаточно.
But a shilling will do splendidly for the moment.
لكن الشلن سيكون كافيا في الوقت الراهن.
Спасибо.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Я очень признателен, мистер Дэниелс...
I'm obliged, Mr. Daniels...
أنا ملتزم بذلك، السيد دانييلز...
...но я могу найти выход сам.
...but l can find my own way out.
...ولكنني أستطيع أن أجد طريقي للخروج.
Почетный караул!
Guard of honor!
حرس الشرف!
Внимание!
Attention!
انتباه!
Предъявить оружие!
Present arms!
الأسلحة الحاضرة!
- Боже мой, ему это нравится! - Я уверен, что он это ненавидит.
-My God, he loves it!
-l'm sure he hates it.
-يا إلهي، إنه يحبه! -أنا متأكد من أنه يكرهه.
Сегодня во Франции репутация генералов создается...
Generals' reputations are being made in France today...
تتم صناعة سمعة الجنرالات في فرنسا اليوم...
...боевые действия на Западном фронте.
...fighting on the Western front.
...القتال على الجبهة الغربية.
Не как военные губернаторы в Индии.
Not as military governors in lndia.
ليس كحكام عسكريين في الهند.
Что, черт возьми, там происходит?
What the devil's going on back there?
ماذا يحدث هناك بالخلف؟
Должно быть, это тот индеец, который наделал столько шума в Африке.
Must be that lndian who made all that fuss in Africa.
لا بد أن يكون هذا الهندي هو الذي أحدث كل هذه الضجة في أفريقيا.
Мой юнга сказал мне, что он на борту.
My cabin boy told me he was onboard.
أخبرني خادم المقصورة أنه كان على متن السفينة.
Вот он.
There he is.
ها هو ذا.
Боже, он одет как кули!
God, he's dressed like a coolie!
يا إلهي، إنه يرتدي ملابس مثل الكولي!
Я думал, он юрист.
I thought he was a lawyer.
اعتقدت أنه كان محاميا.
Господин Ганди, вы отказались носить европейскую одежду?
Mr. Gandhi, have you refused to wear European clothes?
سيد غاندي هل رفضت ارتداء الملابس الأوروبية؟
Нет, я не отказался.
No, I haven't refused.
لا، لم أرفض.
Мне просто хотелось одеваться так, как одеваются мои товарищи по тюрьме.
I simply wanted to dress the way my comrades in prison dress.
أردت فقط أن أرتدي ملابس مثل ملابس زملائي في السجن.
Поддержите ли вы военные действия?
Will you support the war effort?
هل ستدعم المجهود الحربي؟
Если я хочу пользоваться благами и защитой Британской империи...
If l wish to enjoy the benefits and protection of the British Empire...
إذا كنت أرغب في التمتع بفوائد وحماية الإمبراطورية البريطانية...
...было бы неправильно с моей стороны не помочь в его защите.
...it would be wrong of me not to help in its defense.
...سيكون من الخطأ من جانبي ألا أساعد في الدفاع عنه.
Теперь, когда вы вернулись в Индию, что вы будете делать?
Now that you're back in lndia, what will you do?
الآن بعد أن عدت إلى الهند، ماذا ستفعل؟
Я не знаю.
I don't know.
لا أعرف.
-Я не знаю. -Еще один вопрос.
-l don't know.
-One more question.
-لا أعلم. -سؤال آخر.
Как вы, индийская женщина, можете смириться с унижением тюрьмы?
As an lndian woman, how could you accept the indignity of prison?
كيف يمكنك، كإمرأة هندية، أن تقبلي إهانة السجن؟
Мое достоинство исходит из следования за мужем.
My dignity comes from following my husband.
كرامتي تأتي من اتباع زوجي.
Большое спасибо.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
Еще несколько слов, и мы доставим вас в цивилизацию.
Just a few words, then we'll get you to civilization.
بضع كلمات فقط، ثم سنوصلك إلى الحضارة.
Могу ли я?
May I?
ربما أنا؟
Я рад вернуться домой...
I'm glad to be home...
أنا سعيد لوجودي في المنزل...
...и я благодарю вас за приветствие.
...and l thank you for your greeting.
...وشكرًا لك على تحيتك.
Я последую за вами вместе с вашей женой.
I'll follow with your wife.
سأتابع مع زوجتك.
Не волнуйтесь. Все устроено.
Don't worry.
Everything's arranged.
لا تقلق، كل شيء مُرتّب.
-Кто этот молодой человек? -Это молодой Неру.
-Who's that young man?
-That's young Nehru.
-من هذا الشاب؟ -هذا هو الشاب نهرو.
У него интеллект отца и красота матери...
He's got his father's intellect, his mother's good looks...
لقد حصل على ذكاء والده، ومظهر والدته الجيد...
...и обаяние самого дьявола.
...and the devil's own charm.
...وسحر الشيطان نفسه.
Если они не погубят его в Кембридже... Машем, машем!
If they don't ruin him at Cambridge--
Wave, wave!
إذا لم يدمروه في كامبريدج--لوحوا، لوحوا!
--он мог бы чего-то достичь.
--he might amount to something.
--قد يصل إلى شيء ما.
Должен сказать, когда я впервые увидел тебя, неуклюжего адвоката здесь, в Бомбее...
I must say, when l first saw you as a bumbling lawyer here in Bombay...
يجب أن أقول، عندما رأيتك لأول مرة محاميًا فاشلًا هنا في بومباي...
...Я никогда не думал, что встречу тебя как национального героя.
...l never thought l'd greet you as a national hero.
... لم أكن أتوقع أبدًا أن أحييك كبطل وطني.
Я вряд ли таков, мистер Патель.
I'm hardly that, Mr. Patel.
أنا لست كذلك تقريبًا، سيد باتيل.
Да, вы!
Yes, you are!
نعم أنت على حق!
Прошло 200 лет с тех пор, как индеец показал на меня нос...
It's been 200 years since an Indian cocked a snook...
لقد مرت 200 سنة منذ أن قام أحد الهنود بصيد سمكة سنوك...
...на Британскую империю и избежал наказания.
...at the British Empire and got away with it.
...في الإمبراطورية البريطانية ونجح في الإفلات من العقاب.
И перестаньте называть меня мистером Патель. Вы больше не младший клерк.
And stop calling me Mr. Patel.
You're not a junior clerk anymore.
وتوقف عن مناداتي بالسيد باتيل. أنت لم تعد كاتبًا مبتدئًا.
На этом корабле находился новый военный губернатор Северо-Западной провинции.
The new military governor of the
Northwest Province was on that ship.
وكان الحاكم العسكري الجديد لمقاطعة الشمال الغربي على متن تلك السفينة.
Жаль, что ты вернулся третьим классом.
Too bad you came back third class.
من المؤسف أنك عدت في الدرجة الثالثة.
Возможно, он был впечатлен...
He might have been impressed...
ربما كان معجبا...
...успешным адвокатом, который перехитрил генерала Смэтса.
...by a successful barrister who'd outmaneuvered General Smuts.
... بواسطة محامٍ ناجح تمكن من التفوق على الجنرال سموتس.
Да, я уверен.
Yes, l'm sure.
نعم، أنا متأكد.
Вы тоже в этом участвуете, г-жа Неру?
Are you involved too, Mrs. Nehru?
هل أنت متورطة أيضًا، السيدة نهرو؟
Нет. Практические вопросы я оставляю мужу...
No. I leave practical matters to my husband...
لا، أترك الأمور العملية لزوجي...
...и революцию моему сыну.
...and revolution to my son.
...والثورة لابني.
Господин Ганди, я хотел бы познакомить вас с господином Джинной, нашим общим хозяином...
Mr. Gandhi, l'd like you to meet
Mr. Jinnah, our joint host...
السيد غاندي، أود منك أن تلتقي بالسيد جناح، مضيفنا المشترك...
...член конгресса и лидер Мусульманской лиги.
...member of congress and leader of the Muslim League.
...عضو في المؤتمر وزعيم الرابطة الإسلامية.
Как дела?
How do you do?
كيف حالك؟
И мистер Пракаш, который, я боюсь...
And Mr. Prakash, who, l fear...
والسيد براكاش، الذي، أنا خائف...
...ожидает суда за подстрекательство к мятежу и склонение к убийству.
...is awaiting trial for sedition and inducement to murder.
...ينتظر المحاكمة بتهمة التحريض على القتل والتحريض على القتل.
На самом деле я не нажимал на курок, мистер Ганди.
I have not actually pulled the trigger, Mr. Gandhi.
أنا لم أسحب الزناد فعليا، يا سيد غاندي.
Я просто написал...
I have simply written...
لقد كتبت ببساطة...
...если англичанин убьет индейца за неподчинение его закону...
...if an Englishman kills an Indian for disobeying his law...
...إذا قتل إنجليزي هنديًا لمخالفته قانونه...
...долг индейца - убить англичанина...
...it is an lndian's duty to kill an Englishman...
...من واجب الهندي أن يقتل رجلاً إنجليزياً...
...за применение своего закона на земле, которая ему не принадлежит.
...for enforcing his law in a land that is not his.
...لتنفيذ قانونه في أرض ليست له.
Это умный аргумент. Он может не привести к желаемому результату.
It's a clever argument. lt may not produce the end you desire.
إنها حجة ذكية. لكنها قد لا تؤدي إلى النتيجة التي ترغب بها.
Мы надеемся, что вы присоединитесь к нам в нашей борьбе за самоуправление, г-н Ганди.
We hope you'll join us in our struggle for home rule, Mr. Gandhi.
نأمل أن تنضم إلينا في نضالنا من أجل الحكم الذاتي، السيد غاندي.
Извините. Можно, Мохан? Я хотел бы познакомить его с кем-то.
Excuse me. May l, Mohan?
There's someone I'd like him to meet.
معذرةً. هل يمكنني ذلك يا موهان؟ هناك شخصٌ أودّ أن يقابله.
Прошу прощения.
Excuse me.
اعذرني.
Извините, что тороплю вас.
Sorry to rush you.
آسف على التسرع.
Он заявил прессе, что поддержит британцев в войне.
He told the press he'd support the British in the war.
وقال للصحافة أنه سيدعم البريطانيين في الحرب.
Вот это и есть ненасилие.
That's nonviolence for you.
هذا هو اللاعنف بالنسبة لك.
Знаешь, Мохан...
You know, Mohan...
هل تعلم يا موهان...
...теперь мне нужно признаться.
...now l have a confession to make.
... الآن لدي اعتراف أريد أن أقوله.
Я не принимал решения приехать в Южную Африку.
I didn't decide to come to South Africa.
لم أقرر المجيء إلى جنوب أفريقيا.
Меня послал профессор Гокхале.
Professor Gokhale sent me.
لقد أرسلني البروفيسور جوكهالي.
Мы пытаемся создать нацию, Ганди.
We are trying to make a nation, Gandhi.
نحن نحاول أن نصنع أمة، غاندي.
Но британцы продолжают пытаться нас разлучить...
But the British keep trying to break us up...
لكن البريطانيين يواصلون محاولتهم لتفريقنا...
...на религии, княжества, провинции.
...into religions, principalities, provinces.
...إلى الديانات والإمارات والمقاطعات.
То, что вы писали в Южной Африке...
What you were writing in South Africa...
ما كنت تكتبه في جنوب أفريقيا...
...вот что нам здесь нужно.
...that's what we need here.
...هذا ما نحتاجه هنا.
Мне еще так много предстоит узнать об Индии.
I have so much to learn about India.
لدي الكثير لأتعلمه عن الهند.
И мне придется снова начать свою практику. Чтобы вести журнал, нужны деньги.
And l have to begin my practice again.
One needs money to run a journal.
ويجب عليّ أن أبدأ ممارستي من جديد. أحتاج إلى المال لإدارة مجلتي.
Глупости. Продолжай, Чарли. Это индийский разговор.
Nonsense. Go on, Charlie.
This is lndian talk.
كلام فارغ. هيا يا تشارلي. هذا كلام هندي.
Мы не хотим видеть здесь никого из вас, империалистов.
We want none of you imperialists here.
نحن لا نريد أيًا منكم الإمبرياليين هنا.
Хорошо, я пойду и напишу отчет вице-королю.
All right, l'll go and write my report to the viceroy.
حسنًا، سأذهب وأكتب تقريري إلى نائب الملك.
Иди и найди симпатичную индуистку...
You go and find a pretty Hindu woman...
تذهب وتجد امرأة هندوسية جميلة...
...и обратить ее в христианство.
...and convert her to Christianity.
...وتحويلها إلى المسيحية.
Это все, что вам позволено.
That's as much mischief as you're allowed.
هذا هو أقصى قدر من الأذى المسموح لك به.
Пойдем, найдем тихий уголок.
Come, let's find a quiet corner.
تعالوا نبحث عن ركن هادئ.
Теперь вы забываете о своей практике.
Now, you forget about your practice.
الآن، نسيت ممارستك.
У тебя есть и другие дела.
You have other things to do.
لديك أشياء أخرى للقيام بها.
В Индии много мужчин с огромным богатством.
India has many men with too much wealth.
الهند لديها العديد من الرجال الذين لديهم الكثير من الثروة.
И их привилегия — подпитывать усилия немногих...
And it's their privilege to nourish the effort of the few...
ومن امتيازهم أن يغذوا جهود القليل من الناس...
...кто может вывести Индию из рабства и апатии.
...who can raise lndia from servitude and apathy.
...من يستطيع أن ينتشل الهند من العبودية واللامبالاة؟
Я об этом прослежу.
I'll see to it.
سأرى ذلك.
Вы начинаете вести свой дневник.
You begin your journal.
تبدأ يومياتك.
Мне мало что можно сказать.
I have little to say.
ليس لدي ما أقوله.
Давайте присядем.
Come, let's sit down.
تعالوا لنجلس.
Индия для меня чужая страна.
India is an alien country to me.
الهند بلد غريب بالنسبة لي.
Измените это.
Change that.
غيّر ذلك.
Иди и найди Индию.
Go and find lndia.
اذهب وابحث عن الهند.
Не то, что вы здесь видите...
Not what you see here...
ليس ما تراه هنا...
...а настоящая Индия.
...but the real India.
...ولكن الهند الحقيقية.
Вы увидите, что нужно сказать...
You'll see what needs to be said...
سوف ترى ما يجب أن يقال...
...то, что нам нужно услышать.
...what we need to hear.
... ما نحتاج إلى سماعه.
Когда я увидел тебя в этой тунике, я понял.
When I saw you in that tunic, l knew.
عندما رأيتك في هذا القميص، عرفت.
Я знал, что смогу умереть спокойно.
I knew l could die in peace.
لقد عرفت أنني أستطيع أن أموت بسلام.
Пусть Индия гордится собой.
Make India proud of herself.
اجعل الهند فخورة بنفسها.
Чарли, пожалуйста. Вы оба глупые.
Charlie, please.
You're both being foolish.
تشارلي، من فضلك. كلاكما تتصرفان بحماقة.
Но воздух там прекрасный. В любом случае, там нет места.
But the air is lovely.
Anyway, there's no room in there.
لكن الهواء جميل. على أي حال، لا يوجد مكان هناك.
Пожалуйста! Входите.
Please! Come in.
من فضلك ادخل.
Пожалуйста, без насилия.
No violence, please.
لا للعنف من فضلك.
Дай мне держаться двумя руками, иначе я упаду.
Let me hang on with two hands or l will fall.
دعني أتمسك بيديّ الاثنتين وإلا سأسقط.
Англичанин, сахиб!
Englishman, sahib!
الإنجليزي، صاحب!
Идите сюда, здесь есть место!
Come, there is room up here!
تعال، هناك مكان هنا!
Поставь ногу на окно. Иди!
Put your foot on the window. Come!
ضع قدمك على النافذة. تعال!
- Что ты делаешь? - Я иду ближе к Богу.
-What are you doing?
-l'm going nearer to God.
-ماذا تفعل؟ -أنا أقترب من الله.
Чарли! Будь осторожен!
Charlie! Be careful!
تشارلي! كن حذرا!
Отпусти. Отпусти!
Let go. Let go!
دعها تذهب. دعها تذهب!
-Отпусти! -О, боже!
-Let go!
-Oh, dear!
-اتركه!-يا عزيزي!
Привет.
Hello.
مرحبًا.
Видите? Это очень удобно.
You see?
It is most comfortable.
هل ترى؟ إنه مريح للغاية.
Владелец?
Sahib?
مالك؟
Вы христианин?
Are you a Christian?
هل أنت مسيحي؟
Да, я христианин.
Yes, l'm a Christian.
نعم أنا مسيحي.
Я знаю одного христианина.
I know a Christian.
أنا أعرف مسيحيًا.
Она пьет кровь.
She drinks blood.
إنها تشرب الدماء.
Кровь Христа. Каждое воскресенье.
Blood of Christ. Every Sunday.
دم المسيح. كل يوم أحد.
Чарли!
Charlie!
تشارلي!
Все в порядке, сахиб. Это очень безопасно.
It's all right, sahib.
It's very safe.
لا بأس يا صاحب، الوضع آمن جدًا.
Сгибать!
Bend!
يلوي!
Молись Богу, сахиб. Сейчас самое время быть индуистом.
Pray to God, sahib.
Now is when it is best to be Hindu.
صلِّ إلى الله يا صاحب. الآن هو الوقت الأمثل لتكون هندوسيًا.
Я согласен с Джинной.
I agree with Jinnah.
أنا أتفق مع جناح.
Теперь, когда в игру вступили американцы, война скоро закончится.
Now that the Americans are in, the war will be over soon.
الآن بعد أن أصبح الأميركيون في الداخل، فإن الحرب ستنتهي قريبا.
Немцы и так измотаны.
The Germans are worn out as it is.
الألمان منهكون كما هو الحال.
И нашим первым действием должно быть...
And our first act should be...
وينبغي أن يكون أول عمل لدينا هو...
...созвать съезд партии конгресса...
...to convene a congress party convention...
...لعقد مؤتمر لحزب المؤتمر...
...и требовать независимости.
...and demand independence.
...والمطالبة بالاستقلال.
И мы будем говорить единым голосом, сообща.
And we will speak with one voice, united.
وسنتحدث بصوت واحد متحدين.
И нам следует пригласить Ганди.
And we should invite Gandhi.
ويجب علينا أن ندعو غاندي.
Что, черт возьми, с ним случилось?
What the devil's happened to him?
ماذا حدث له بحق الشيطان؟
Он открывает Индию.
He's discovering lndia.
إنه يكتشف الهند.
Это лучше, чем создавать проблемы там, где это необходимо.
Which is better than making trouble where it matters.
وهذا أفضل من إثارة المشاكل حيث يكون الأمر مهمًا.
Пригласите его, пусть он расскажет свою статью о Южной Африке...
Invite him, let him say his piece about South Africa...
ادعوه ليقول رأيه في جنوب أفريقيا...
...а затем позвольте ему кануть в небытие.
...then let him slip into oblivion.
...ثم دعه ينزلق إلى النسيان.
Повстанцы.
Insurgents.
المتمردون.
Они пустили под откос воинский эшелон.
They've derailed a troop train.
لقد قاموا بإخراج قطار القوات عن مساره.
Держись подальше! Давай.
Keep clear! Come on.
ابقى واضحا! هيا.
Они убили английского солдата.
They've killed an English soldier.
لقد قتلوا جنديًا إنجليزيًا.
Нас просили о терпимости.
We were asked for toleration.
لقد طلب منا التسامح.
Нас попросили проявить терпение.
We were asked for patience.
لقد طلب منا الصبر.
Некоторые из нас дали это...
Some of us gave it...
بعضنا أعطاها...
...а некоторые нет.
...and some did not.
...وبعضهم لم يفعل.
Что ж, их война окончена.
Well, their war is over.
حسنًا، لقد انتهت حربهم.
И те из нас, кто это поддержал...
And those of us who supported it...
وأولئك منا الذين أيدوها...
...и те из нас, кто отказался...
...and those of us who refused...
...ومنهم من رفض...
...должны забыть наши разногласия.
...must forget our differences.
...يجب أن ننسى اختلافاتنا.
И никаких оправданий быть не может...
And there can be no excuses...
ولا يمكن أن يكون هناك أي أعذار...
...теперь уже из Британии.
...from the British now.
...من البريطانيين الآن.
Индия хочет...
India wants...
الهند تريد...
...домашнее правило.
...home rule.
...حكم ذاتي.
Индия...
India...
الهند...
...требует самоуправления!
...demands home rule!
...يطالب بالحكم الذاتي!
Поздравляю.
Congratulations.
مبروك.
И пусть никто не задается вопросом...
And let no one question...
ولا يتساءل أحد...
...что говорит г-н Джинна...
...that Mr. Jinnah speaks...
...أن السيد جناح يتحدث...
...не только для мусульман...
...not just for the Muslims...
... ليس فقط للمسلمين...
...но для всей Индии!
...but for all lndia!
...ولكن بالنسبة لجميع الهند!
А теперь...
And now...
والآن...
...я познакомлю вас...
...l'm going to introduce to you...
...سأقدم لكم...
...человек, чьи произведения...
...a man whose writings...
...رجل كتاباته...
...мы все начинаем с этим знакомиться.
...we are all becoming familiar with.
...نحن جميعا نصبح على دراية به.
Человек, который пользовался большим уважением у нашего любимого Гокхале.
A man who stood in high esteem with our own beloved Gokhale.
رجل كان له مكانة عالية بين شعبنا الحبيب جوكهالي.
Человек, чьи достижения в Южной Африке...
A man whose accomplishments in South Africa...
رجل كانت إنجازاته في جنوب أفريقيا...
...будут помниться всегда.
...will always be remembered.
...سوف نتذكر دائما.
Господин Мохандас Ганди!
Mr. Mohandas Gandhi!
السيد موهانداس غاندي!
Ваш журнал оказал большое влияние.
Your journal has made great impact.
لقد أحدثت مجلتك تأثيرًا كبيرًا.
Мне польщен мистер Патель.
I'm flattered by Mr. Patel.
أنا مسرور بالسيد باتيل.
Я был бы еще более польщен, если бы то, что он сказал, было правдой.
I would be even more flattered if what he said were true.
سوف أكون أكثر سعادة لو كان ما قاله صحيحا.
Но это правда.
But it is true.
ولكن هذا صحيح.
Я читаю. Часто!
I read it. Often!
أقرأه. في كثير من الأحيان!
С тех пор, как я вернулся из Южной Африки...
Since I returned from South Africa...
منذ عودتي من جنوب أفريقيا...
...я объездил большую часть Индии.
...l've traveled over much of India.
... لقد سافرت إلى أجزاء كثيرة من الهند.
И я знаю, что мог бы путешествовать еще много лет...
And l know that l could travel for many more years...
وأنا أعلم أنني قد أتمكن من السفر لسنوات عديدة أخرى...
...и все равно вижу только малую ее часть.
...and still only see a small part of her.
...ولا أزال أرى جزءًا صغيرًا منها فقط.
И все же, я уже знаю...
And yet, l already know...
ولكنني أعلم بالفعل...
...это то, что мы здесь говорим...
...that what we say here...
...هذا ما نقوله هنا...
...ничего не значит для масс нашей страны.
...means nothing to the masses of our country.
...لا يعني شيئا بالنسبة لجماهير بلدنا.
Здесь мы произносим речи друг за друга...
Here, we make speeches for each other...
هنا، نلقي خطابات لبعضنا البعض...
...и те английские либеральные журналы, которые могут посвятить нам несколько строк.
...and those English liberal magazines that may grant us a few lines.
... وتلك المجلات الليبرالية الإنجليزية التي قد تمنحنا بضعة أسطر.
Но народ Индии...
But the people of lndia...
لكن شعب الهند...
...являются...
...are...
...نكون...
...нетронутый.
...untouched.
...لم يمسها.
Их политика ограничивается хлебом...
Their politics are confined to bread...
سياستهم تقتصر على الخبز...
...и соль.
...and salt.
...والملح.
Они, может, и неграмотны, но не слепы.
Illiterate they may be, but they're not blind.
قد يكونون أميين، ولكنهم ليسوا عميانًا.
Они не видят причин отдавать свою лояльность богатым и влиятельным людям...
They see no reason to give their loyalty to rich and powerful men...
لا يرون سبباً لإعطاء ولائهم للرجال الأثرياء والأقوياء...
...которые просто хотят взять на себя роль британцев...
...who simply want to take over the role of the British...
...الذين يريدون ببساطة الاستيلاء على دور البريطانيين...
...во имя свободы.
...in the name of freedom.
...بإسم الحرية.
Этот конгресс говорит миру...
This congress tells the world...
هذا المؤتمر يخبر العالم...
...он представляет Индию.
...it represents lndia.
...إنه يمثل الهند.
Братья мои...
My brothers...
إخوتي...
...Индия...
...lndia...
...الهند...
...это 700 000 деревень...
...is 700,000 villages...
...700 ألف قرية...
...несколько сотен юристов в Дели...
...not a few hundred lawyers in Delhi...
...ليس هناك بضع مئات من المحامين في دلهي...
...и Бомбей.
...and Bombay.
...وبومباي.
Пока мы не окажемся в полях...
Until we stand in the fields...
حتى نقف في الحقول...
...с миллионами, которые каждый день трудятся под палящим солнцем...
...with the millions that toil each day under the hot sun...
...مع الملايين الذين يتعبون كل يوم تحت أشعة الشمس الحارقة...
...мы не будем представлять Индию.
...we will not represent India.
...نحن لن نمثل الهند.
Мы никогда не сможем бросить вызов британцам...
Nor will we ever be able to challenge the British...
ولن نكون قادرين على تحدي البريطانيين أبدًا...
...как одна нация.
...as one nation.
...كأمة واحدة.
Вы читали его журнал?
Have you read his magazine?
هل قرأت مجلته؟
Нет.
No.
لا.
Но я думаю, что я это сделаю.
But l think I'm going to.
ولكن أعتقد أنني سأفعل ذلك.
Перетягивать.
Pull over.
قف بجانب الطريق.
Так быть не может.
This can't be the way.
لا يمكن أن يكون هذا هو الطريق.
Да, я уверен, что Индия движется именно в этом направлении.
Yes, l'm sure this is the direction lndia is taking.
نعم، أنا متأكد من أن هذا هو الاتجاه الذي تتخذه الهند.
Подумать только, я почти воодушевился из-за мистера Джинны...
To think I almost got excited by Mr. Jinnah...
أعتقد أنني شعرت بالإثارة تقريبًا تجاه السيد جناح ...
...когда все это меня ждало.
...when all this was awaiting me.
...عندما كان كل هذا في انتظاري.
Мы ищем мистера Ганди.
We're looking for Mr. Gandhi.
نحن نبحث عن السيد غاندي.
- Вы найдете его под тем деревом. - Спасибо.
-You'll find him under that tree.
-Thank you.
-ستجده تحت تلك الشجرة. -شكرا لك.
Я с нетерпением жду встречи с этой новой силой.
I'm anxious to meet this new force.
أنا متشوق للقاء هذه القوة الجديدة.
Как видите, я стараюсь жить как индиец.
I try to live like an Indian, as you see.
أحاول أن أعيش مثل الهنود، كما ترى.
Конечно, это глупо.
It's stupid, of course.
إنه أمر غبي، بالطبع.
Потому что в нашей стране...
Because in our country...
لأن في بلادنا...
...именно британцы решают, как жить индийцу...
...it is the British who decide how an lndian lives...
...إن البريطانيين هم الذين يقررون كيف يعيش الهندي...
...что он может купить, что он может продать.
...what he may buy, what he may sell.
...ما يجوز له أن يشتريه، وما يجوز له أن يبيعه.
И от их роскоши...
And from their luxury...
ومن رفاهيتهم...
...среди нашей ужасной нищеты...
...in the midst of our terrible poverty...
...في خضم فقرنا المروع...
...они учат нас, что такое справедливость, а что такое подстрекательство к мятежу.
...they instruct us on what is justice, what is sedition.
...يعلموننا ما هو العدل وما هو الفتنة.
Поэтому вполне естественно, что наши лучшие молодые умы...
So it's only natural that our best young minds...
لذا فمن الطبيعي أن أفضل عقولنا الشابة...
...принять вид восточного достоинства...
...assume an air of Eastern dignity...
...تبدو وكأنها تتمتع بهواء من الكرامة الشرقية...
...жадно ассимилируя...
...while greedily assimilating...
...بينما يستوعب بجشع...
...каждую слабость Запада, как только они смогут ее усвоить.
...every Western weakness as quickly as they can acquire it.
...كل نقاط الضعف الغربية بأسرع ما يمكن أن يكتسبوها.
Если у нас будет самоуправление...
If we have home rule...
إذا كان لدينا حكم منزلي...
...это изменится.
...that'll change.
...هذا سوف يتغير.
Пожалуйста, не могли бы вы?
Would you, please?
هل يمكنك ذلك من فضلك؟
Почему британцы должны предоставить нам самоуправление?
Why should the British grant us home rule?
لماذا يجب على البريطانيين أن يمنحونا الحكم الذاتي؟
Очистки надо отнести козам.
We must take the peelings to the goats.
علينا أن نأخذ القشور إلى الماعز.
Мы только произносим дикие речи или совершаем еще более дикие акты терроризма.
We only make wild speeches or perform even wilder acts of terrorism.
نحن لا نلقي إلا الخطب الجامحة أو نرتكب أفعالاً إرهابية أعنف.
Мы воспитали армию анархистов...
We've bred an army of anarchists...
لقد أنشأنا جيشًا من الفوضويين...
...но ни одной группы, способной сражаться с британцами где бы то ни было, нет.
...but not one group that can fight the British anywhere.
...ولكن لا توجد مجموعة واحدة قادرة على محاربة البريطانيين في أي مكان.
Привет! Привет!
Hello! Hello!
مرحبا! مرحبا!
Но я думал, ты против драк.
But l thought you were against fighting.
ولكنني اعتقدت أنك ضد القتال.
Теперь просто распространите это.
Now just spread it around.
الآن فقط قم بنشره حولك.
Вот и всё.
There you are.
ها أنت ذا.
Им нравится смешивать свежие обрезки с гниющими.
They like the new peelings mixed in with the rotting ones.
إنهم يحبون القشور الجديدة المختلطة بالقشور المتعفنة.
Я всегда верил, что там, где есть несправедливость, нужно бороться.
Where there's injustice,
I always believed in fighting.
حيثما كان هناك ظلم، كنت أؤمن دائمًا بالقتال.
Вопрос в том, боретесь ли вы ради того, чтобы что-то изменить или ради того, чтобы наказать?
The question is, do you fight to change things or to punish?
السؤال هو، هل تقاتل من أجل تغيير الأمور أم من أجل العقاب؟
Я понял, что мы все такие грешники, что должны предоставить наказание Богу.
I've found we're all such sinners, we should leave punishment to God.
لقد وجدت أننا جميعًا خاطئون، ويجب أن نترك العقاب لله.
И если мы действительно хотим что-то изменить...
And if we really want to change things...
وإذا أردنا حقا تغيير الأمور...
...есть лучшие способы сделать это...
...there are better ways of doing it...
...هناك طرق أفضل للقيام بذلك...
...чем пускать поезда под откос или кромсать кого-то мечом.
...than derailing trains or slashing someone with a sword.
...من إخراج القطارات عن مسارها أو تقطيع شخص ما بالسيف.
Огонь готов.
The fire is ready.
النار جاهزة
Видите ли, даже здесь...
You see, even here...
كما ترى، حتى هنا...
...мы живем под тиранией.
...we live under tyranny.
...نحن نعيش تحت الاستبداد.
Что я тебе говорил? Посмотри на него!
What did l tell you?
Look at him!
ماذا قلت لك؟ انظر إليه!
Я уже вижу, как трясутся британцы.
I can see the British shaking now.
أستطيع أن أرى البريطانيين يهتزون الآن.
Привет!
Hello!
مرحبًا!
Я ищу мистера Ганди.
I'm looking for Mr. Gandhi.
أبحث عن السيد غاندي.
Я уже долгое время пытаюсь с вами поговорить.
I've been trying to speak to you for a long time.
لقد كنت أحاول التحدث معك لفترة طويلة.
Наши урожаи.
Our crops.
محاصيلنا.
Мы не можем их продать.
We cannot sell them.
لا يمكننا بيعها.
У нас нет денег.
We have no money.
ليس لدينا مال.
Однако арендодатели по-прежнему требуют ту же арендную плату.
But the landlords still demand the same rent.
لكن أصحاب العقارات لا زالوا يطالبون بنفس الإيجار.
У нас ничего не осталось.
We have nothing left.
لم يبق لدينا شيء.
Мистер Тейлор, сэр. Здесь наверху!
Mr. Taylor, sir. Up here!
السيد تايلور، سيدي. هنا!
Иисус!
Jesus!
عيسى!
Что, черт возьми, происходит?
What the hell is going on?
ماذا يحدث بحق الجحيم؟
Я не знаю, сэр.
I don't know, sir.
لا أعلم سيدي.
Агент получил телеграмму.
The agent got a telegram.
تلقى الوكيل برقية.
А там просто было написано: «Он идет», и указано время прибытия поезда.
And it just said, "He is coming," and gave the time of the train.
وقالت فقط، "إنه قادم"، وأعطت وقت القطار.
Кто, черт возьми, этот «он»?
Who the hell is "he"?
من هو "هو"؟
Я не знаю, сэр.
I don't know, sir.
لا أعلم سيدي.
Прочь с дороги. Давай, ты!
Out of the way.
Come on, you!
ابتعد عن الطريق. هيا يا أنت!
-Кто ты, черт возьми? -Меня зовут Мохандас К. Ганди.
-Who the devil are you?
-My name is Mohandas K. Gandhi.
-من أنت بحق الجحيم؟- اسمي موهانداس ك. غاندي.
Кем бы вы ни были, мы не хотим, чтобы вы здесь были.
Whoever you are, we don't want you here.
من أنت، فنحن لا نريدك هنا.
Предлагаю вам вернуться в поезд, пока он не ушел.
I suggest you get back on that train before it leaves.
أقترح عليك العودة إلى هذا القطار قبل مغادرته.
Кажется, они хотят меня.
They seem to want me.
يبدو أنهم يريدوني.
Теперь посмотрите сюда.
Now, look here.
الآن، انظر هنا.
Если хотите, я вас арестую.
I'll put you under arrest if you'd prefer.
سأضعك تحت الإعتقال إذا كنت تفضل ذلك.
По какому обвинению?
On what charge?
بأي تهمة؟
Мне не нужны неприятности.
I don't want any trouble.
لا أريد أي مشاكل.
Я индиец, путешествующий по своей стране. Я не вижу причин для беспокойства.
I'm an lndian traveling in my own country. I see no reason for trouble.
أنا هندي أسافر في بلدي، ولا أرى أي سبب للمشاكل.
Ну, лучше бы этого не было.
Well, there had better not be.
حسنًا، من الأفضل أن لا يكون هناك شيء.
Дайте дорогу офицеру.
Make way for the officer.
افسح المجال للضابط.
В течение многих лет...
For years...
منذ سنوات...
...хозяева приказали нам...
...the landlords have ordered us...
...أصحاب الأرض أمرونا...
...выращивать индиго...
...to grow indigo...
...لزراعة النيلي...
...для окрашивания тканей.
...for dyeing cloth.
...لصبغ القماش.
Часть урожая они всегда забирали в качестве ренты.
Always, they took part of the crop as rent.
وكانوا دائمًا يأخذون جزءًا من المحصول كإيجار.
Но теперь...
But now...
ولكن الآن...
...все покупают ткани в Англии.
...everyone buys their cloth from England.
... الجميع يشترون قماشهم من إنجلترا.
Поэтому никто не хочет...
So no one wants...
لذلك لا أحد يريد...
...наш индиго.
...our indigo.
...نيلينا.
Хозяева...
The landlords...
الملاك...
...говорят, что мы должны платить за аренду...
...say we must pay our rent...
...نقول أننا يجب أن ندفع الإيجار...
...наличными.
...in cash.
...نقدا.
Что мы могли бы...
What we could...
ما يمكننا...
...мы продали.
...we sold.
... بعنا.
Остальных забрала полиция.
The police have taken the rest.
وقد قامت الشرطة بأخذ الباقي.
Есть...
There is...
هنالك...
...нет еды.
...no food.
...لا يوجد طعام.
Я понимаю.
I understand.
أفهم.
Хозяева — британцы?
The landlords are British?
هل أصحاب العقارات بريطانيون؟
Что мы можем сделать, мы постараемся сделать.
What we can do, we will try to do.
ما يمكننا فعله، سنحاول القيام به.
Шукла...
Shukla...
شوكلا...
...весь Чампаран такой?
...is all Champaran like this?
...هل كل شامباران مثل هذا؟
Да, Бапу.
Yes, Bapu.
نعم يا بابو.
Весь регион.
The whole region.
المنطقة بأكملها.
Сотни. Тысячи.
Hundreds. Thousands.
مئات. آلاف.
Некоторые арендодатели пытались помочь.
Some landlords have tried to help.
وقد حاول بعض أصحاب العقارات تقديم المساعدة.
Но что они могут сделать?
But what can they do?
ولكن ماذا يستطيعون أن يفعلوا؟
-Вы мистер М.К. Ганди? -Да.
-Are you Mr. M.K. Gandhi?
-Yes.
-هل أنت السيد م.ك. غاندي؟ -نعم.
Извините, вы арестованы.
I'm sorry, you're under arrest.
أنا آسف، أنت تحت الإعتقال.
Мне совсем не жаль.
I'm not sorry at all.
أنا لست آسف على الإطلاق.
Кто, вы сказали, будет покупать напитки?
Who did you say would be buying the drinks?
من قلت أنه سيشتري المشروبات؟
О, нет!
Oh, no!
أوه لا!
Знаете ли вы, что это были мои лучшие иннинги со времен Оксфорда.
Wouldn't you know, that's the best innings I've had since Oxford.
ألا تعتقد أن هذه هي أفضل جولة لي منذ أكسفورد؟
- Индия полна горя, старик. - Понятия не имею.
-lndia's full of grief, old man.
-l've got no idea.
-الهند مليئة بالحزن، أيها الرجل العجوز. -ليس لدي أي فكرة.
Все, что я знаю, это то, что в Мотихари в Чампаране произошел какой-то бунт или что-то в этом роде.
All I know is there's a riot or something at Motihari in Champaran.
كل ما أعرفه هو أن هناك أعمال شغب أو شيء من هذا القبيل في موتيهاري في شامباران.
Вся рота отправлена ​​в отставку.
The whole company's ordered out.
تم إصدار أمر للشركة بأكملها.
Я хотел бы увидеть заключенного.
I would like to see the prisoner.
أريد رؤية السجين.
Слева, сэр.
On the left, sir.
على اليسار يا سيدي.
-Чарли. -Оттенки Южной Африки.
-Charlie.
-Shades of South Africa.
-تشارلي. -ظلال جنوب أفريقيا.
Не совсем.
Not quite.
ليس تماما.
Они только держат меня...
They're only holding me...
إنهم يمسكون بي فقط...
...до слушания дела мировым судьей.
...until the magistrate's hearing.
...حتى جلسة القاضي.
Тогда это будет тюрьма.
Then it will be prison.
ثم سيكون السجن.
Они забрали твою одежду?
Did they take your clothes?
هل أخذوا ملابسك؟
Теперь это моя одежда.
These are my clothes now.
هذه ملابسي الآن.
У тебя всегда были пуритански настроены черты, Мохан.
You always had a puritanical streak, Mohan.
لقد كان لديك دائمًا نزعة متشددة، موهان.
Если я хочу быть единым целым с ними...
If l want to be one with them...
إذا أردت أن أكون واحداً منهم...
...мне придется жить как они.
...l have to live like them.
...يجب علي أن أعيش مثلهم.
Да, я так думаю.
Yes, l think you do.
نعم، أعتقد ذلك.
Но слава богу, мы все этого не делаем.
But thank God we all don't.
ولكن الحمد لله أننا لا نفعل ذلك جميعًا.
Мой пуританизм проявляется в другом.
My puritanism runs in a different way.
إن تطهيريتي تسير بطريقة مختلفة.
Я слишком скромен для такого показа.
I'm far too modest for such a display.
أنا متواضع للغاية بالنسبة لمثل هذا العرض.
Меня нельзя было пустить вместе с заключенным? Я священнослужитель.
Couldn't I be let in with the prisoner? I am a clergyman.
ألا يُمكنني الدخول مع السجين؟ أنا رجل دين.
Они называют тебя «Бапу».
They're calling you "Bapu."
إنهم ينادونك "بابو".
Я думал, это означает «отец».
I thought it meant "father."
اعتقدت أنها تعني "الأب".
Это так.
It does.
إنه كذلك.
Мы, наверное, стареем, Чарли.
We must be getting old, Charlie.
لا بد أننا أصبحنا كبارًا في السن، تشارلي.
Что вы хотите, чтобы я сделал?
What do you want me to do?
ماذا تريدني أن أفعل؟
Я думаю, что вы можете нам больше всего помочь...
I think that you can help us most...
أعتقد أنك تستطيع مساعدتنا أكثر...
...приняв предложенное вам задание на Фиджи.
...by taking that assignment you've been offered in Fiji.
...من خلال قبول هذه المهمة التي عُرضت عليك في فيجي.
Я должен быть уверен...
I have to be sure--
يجب أن أكون متأكدًا--
Они должны быть уверены, что то, что мы делаем...
They have to be sure that what we do...
يتعين عليهم التأكد من أن ما نقوم به...
...можно сделать только индийцам.
...can be done by Indians alone.
...يمكن أن يتم ذلك من قبل الهنود وحدهم.
Но вы знаете стратегию.
But you know the strategy.
ولكنك تعرف الاستراتيجية.
В мире полно людей, которые будут презирать то, что здесь происходит.
The world is full of people who will despise what's happening here.
العالم مليء بالأشخاص الذين سوف يحتقرون ما يحدث هنا.
Именно их сила нам нужна.
It is their strength that we need.
إن ما نحتاجه هو قوتهم.
Прежде чем уйти...
Before you go...
قبل أن تذهب...
...вы могли бы направить нас в правильном направлении.
...you could start us in the right direction.
...يمكنك أن تبدأ بنا في الاتجاه الصحيح.
Я должен уехать из Калькутты...
I must leave from Calcutta...
يجب أن أغادر كالكوتا...
...и так далее.
...and soon.
...و قريبا.
Попрощайся за меня с Ба.
Say goodbye to Ba for me.
قل وداعا لبا بالنسبة لي.
Ну, я...
Well, l....
حسنا، أنا....
Для нас нет прощаний, Чарли.
There are no goodbyes for us, Charlie.
لا يوجد وداع لنا يا تشارلي.
Где бы ты ни был, ты всегда будешь в моем сердце.
Wherever you are, you will always be in my heart.
أينما كنت، سوف تكون دائما في قلبي.
- Я собираюсь очистить зал суда. - Я не уверен, что мы сможем это сделать.
-l'm going to clear the courtroom.
-l'm not sure we'd be able to.
-سأقوم بإخلاء قاعة المحكمة. -لست متأكدًا من أننا سنكون قادرين على ذلك.
Это первое слушание. Оно должно быть публичным.
It is a first hearing.
It's supposed to be public.
إنها جلسة استماع أولى، ومن المفترض أن تكون علنية.
И он юрист.
And he's a lawyer.
وهو محامي.
Не знаю, где они нашли наглость.
I don't know where they found the nerve.
لا أعلم أين وجدوا العصب.
Я тоже нет, но войска прибудут только завтра.
I don't either, but the troops won't be here till tomorrow.
أنا أيضًا لا أعتقد ذلك، لكن القوات لن تكون هنا حتى الغد.
Как пресса оказалась здесь раньше военных?
How did the press get here before the military?
كيف وصلت الصحافة إلى هنا قبل العسكر؟
Вчера этот английский священник отправил несколько телеграмм.
That English clergyman sent a number of telegrams yesterday.
أرسل رجل الدين الإنجليزي عددًا من البرقيات أمس.
Насколько я знаю, один из них даже отправился к вице-королю.
I understand one of them even went to the viceroy.
وأفهم أن أحدهم ذهب إلى نائب الملك.
Вам приказано покинуть провинцию...
You have been ordered out of the province...
لقد تم إصدار أمر لك بالخروج من المقاطعة...
...по причине нарушения общественного порядка.
...on the grounds of disturbing the peace.
... على خلفية الإخلال بالسلم العام.
При всем уважении, я отказываюсь идти.
With respect, l refuse to go.
مع الاحترام، أرفض الذهاب.
Ты хочешь попасть в тюрьму?
Do you want to go to jail?
هل تريد الذهاب إلى السجن؟
Как хочешь.
As you wish.
كما تريد.
Все в порядке.
All right.
حسنًا.
Я освобожу вас под залог...
I will release you on bail...
سأطلق سراحك بكفالة...
...100 рупий, пока не вынесу приговор.
...of 1 00 rupees until I reach a sentence.
... من 100 روبية حتى أصل إلى جملة.
Я отказываюсь платить 100 рупий.
I refuse to pay 1 00 rupees.
أرفض أن أدفع 100 روبية.
Тогда я освобожу вас под залог...
Then l will grant release on bail...
ثم سأمنح الإفراج بكفالة...
...без оплаты, пока я не приму решение.
...without payment until I reach a decision.
...بدون دفع حتى أتوصل إلى قرار.
Гандиджи! Гандиджи!
Gandhiji! Gandhiji!
غاندي! غاندي!
Мы из Бихара.
We are from Bihar.
نحن من بيهار.
Мы получили телеграмму от старого друга...
We received a cable from an old friend...
لقد تلقينا برقية من صديق قديم...
...который был с нами в Кембридже.
...who was at Cambridge with us.
...الذي كان معنا في كامبريدج.
Его зовут Неру.
His name is Nehru.
اسمه نهرو.
- Я думаю, ты его знаешь. - Действительно.
-l believe you know him.
-lndeed.
-أعتقد أنك تعرفه. -بالفعل.
Он говорит нам, что вам нужна помощь, и мы пришли, чтобы ее оказать.
He tells us you need help, and we have come to give it.
يخبرنا أنك بحاجة إلى المساعدة، وقد أتينا لنقدمها لك.
Я хочу холодно и рационально документировать то, что здесь делается.
I want to document coldly, rationally, what is being done here.
أريد أن أوثق بشكل بارد وعقلاني ما يتم فعله هنا.
Это может занять месяцы.
It may take months.
ربما يستغرق الأمر أشهرًا.
У нас нет никаких неотложных дел.
We have no pressing engagements.
ليس لدينا أي التزامات ملحة.
Вам придется жить с крестьянами.
You will have to live with the peasants.
سوف يتوجب عليك العيش مع الفلاحين.
Риски будут.
There will be risks.
سيكون هناك مخاطر.
Я не знаю, куда катится эта страна.
I don't know what this country's coming to.
لا أعلم ماذا سيحدث لهذا البلد.
Но Боже мой, чувак!
But good God, man!
ولكن يا إلهي، أيها الرجل!
Вы сами подняли арендную плату просто для того, чтобы профинансировать охотничью экспедицию.
You yourself raised the rent simply to finance a hunting expedition.
لقد قمت برفع الإيجار بنفسك فقط لتمويل رحلة صيد.
И некоторые из этих других: избиения, незаконные захваты...
And some of these others: beatings, illegal seizures...
وبعض هذه الأمور الأخرى: الضرب، والمصادرة غير القانونية...
...требование услуг без оплаты.
...demanding services without pay.
...المطالبة بالخدمات دون أجر.
Даже отказать им в воде.
Even refusing them water.
حتى رفضهم الماء.
В Индии!
In lndia!
في الهند!
Никто не знает, что значит заставить этих людей работать.
Nobody knows what it is to try to get these people to work.
لا أحد يعرف ما يعنيه محاولة جعل هؤلاء الأشخاص يعملون.
Ты сделал этого полуголого, как его там...
You've made this half-naked whatever-he-is...
لقد جعلت هذا نصف عارٍ مهما كان...
...в международного героя.
...into an international hero.
...إلى بطل دولي.
«Одинокий человек, шагающий по пыльным дорогам, вооруженный только честностью...
"One lone man, marching dusty roads, armed only with honesty...
"رجل وحيد يسير في الطرقات المتربة، مسلحًا بالصدق فقط...
...и бамбуковый посох, сражающийся с Британской империей».
...and a bamboo staff, doing battle with the British Empire."
...وعصا من الخيزران، تخوض معركة مع الإمبراطورية البريطانية.
Дома дети пишут о нем сочинения.
At home, children are writing essays about him.
وفي المنزل، يكتب الأطفال مقالات عنه.
Чего они хотят?
What do they want?
ماذا يريدون؟
Гарет!
Gareth!
غاريث!
Да, сэр.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Предоставляется скидка на уплаченную арендную плату.
There's a rebate on rents paid.
هناك خصم على الإيجارات المدفوعة.
Они должны иметь возможность выращивать урожай по своему выбору.
They're to be free to grow crops of their own choice.
ويجب أن يكونوا أحرارًا في زراعة المحاصيل التي يختارونها.
И комиссия, частично состоящая из индейцев, для рассмотрения жалоб.
And a commission, part lndian, to hear grievances.
ولجنة، جزء منها هندي، لسماع المظالم.
Это его удовлетворит?
That would satisfy him?
هل هذا من شأنه أن يرضيه؟
И правительство Его Величества.
And His Majesty's government.
وحكومة جلالته.
Для арендодателей нужна только ваша подпись.
It only needs your signature for the landlords.
كل ما يحتاجه هو توقيعك لأصحاب العقارات.
Стоит взглянуть на его спину.
It'll be worth it to see the back of him.
سيكون من المفيد رؤية ظهره.
Благодарю вас, сэр.
Thank you, sir.
شكرا لك سيدي.
- Мы слишком чертовски либеральны. - Возможно.
-We're too damned liberal.
-Perhaps.
-نحن ليبراليون للغاية. -ربما.
По крайней мере, это заставило правительство осознать, что мужчины...
At least this has made the government see some sense about what men...
على الأقل هذا جعل الحكومة تدرك بعض الأمور حول ما يفعله الرجال...
...например, г-ну Ганди следует разрешить что-то, а в чем-то им следует отказать.
...like Mr. Gandhi should be allowed, and what they should be denied.
...كما ينبغي أن يُسمح للسيد غاندي، وما ينبغي أن يُحرموا منه.
Где мистер Ганди?
Where is Mr. Gandhi?
أين السيد غاندي؟
Он сказал, что предпочитает идти пешком, сэр.
He said he preferred to walk, sir.
قال أنه يفضل المشي يا سيدي.
Я следовал за ним большую часть пути. Он только что повернул за угол.
I followed him most of the way.
He's just turned the corner.
تبعته معظم الطريق. لقد وصل للتو إلى المنعطف.
Он приехал третьим классом.
He came third class.
لقد جاء في الدرجة الثالثة.
Боже, дай мне терпения.
God, give me patience.
اللهم أعطني الصبر.
Мой дом удостоен чести.
My house is honored.
بيتي مشرف.
Это наша честь.
The honor is ours.
الشرف لنا.
Я хотел бы познакомить вас с доктором Калленбахом, моим старым другом.
I'd like you to meet
Dr. Kallenbach, an old friend.
أود منك أن تلتقي بالدكتور كالينباخ، وهو صديق قديم.
Он интересуется цветами. Я сказала ему, что он может побродить по твоему саду.
He's interested in flowers. l told him he could wander your garden.
إنه مهتم بالزهور. أخبرته أنه يستطيع التجول في حديقتك.
Я пошлю за своим садовником. Вам будет что обсудить.
I'll send for my gardener.
You'll have plenty to discuss.
سأطلب بستاني. سيكون لديك الكثير لتناقشه.
Спасибо.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Господа, герой Чампарана.
Gentlemen, the hero of Champaran.
أيها السادة، بطل شامباران.
Только упрямый человек из Чампарана.
Only the stubborn man of Champaran.
فقط الرجل العنيد من شامباران.
Господин Патель, вы знаете.
Mr. Patel you know.
السيد باتيل كما تعلم.
Маулана Азад, мой коллега и мусульманин...
Maulana Azad, my colleague and a fellow Muslim...
مولانا آزاد، زميلي وزميلي المسلم...
...и совсем недавно освободился из тюрьмы.
...and just recently released from prison.
... وأُطلق سراحه مؤخرًا من السجن.
Г-н Крипалани.
Mr. Kripalani.
السيد كريبالاني.
И, конечно же, вы знаете господина Неру.
And of course, you know Mr. Nehru.
وبالطبع، أنتم تعرفون السيد نهرو.
Я начинаю узнавать господина Неру.
I'm beginning to know Mr. Nehru.
بدأت أعرف السيد نهرو.
Пожалуйста, садитесь. Садитесь.
Please sit down. Do sit down.
من فضلك اجلس. اجلس.
Господа, я попросил вас приехать сюда по доброте господина Джинны...
Gentlemen, l've asked you to come here through Mr. Jinnah's kindness...
أيها السادة، لقد طلبت منكم الحضور إلى هنا بفضل لطف السيد جناح...
...потому что у меня была возможность ознакомиться с законодательством.
...because I've had the chance to see the legislation.
...لأنني حصلت على فرصة لرؤية التشريع.
И это именно то, о чем шла речь.
And it is exactly as was rumored.
وهو بالضبط كما أشيع.
Арест без ордера и автоматическое тюремное заключение...
Arrest without warrant, and automatic imprisonment...
الاعتقال بدون مذكرة، والسجن التلقائي...
...за хранение материалов, считающихся подрывными.
...for possession of materials considered seditious.
...لحيازة مواد تعتبر مثيرة للفتنة.
И ваши труды особо отмечены.
And your writings are specifically listed.
وكتاباتك مدرجة بشكل خاص.
Вот вам и помощь им в Великой войне.
So much for helping them in the Great War.
وهذا كل ما ساعدهم في الحرب العظمى.
Ответ только один. Прямое действие в масштабе...
There is only one answer.
Direct action on a scale...
هناك إجابة واحدة فقط: العمل المباشر على نطاق واسع...
...они никогда не смогут справиться.
...they can never handle.
...لا يمكنهم التعامل معها أبدًا.
Я так не думаю.
I don't think so.
أنا لا أعتقد ذلك.
Терроризм лишь оправдал бы их репрессии.
Terrorism would only justify their repression.
إن الإرهاب لن يكون سوى مبرر لقمعهم.
И каких лидеров это породит?
And what kind of leaders would it throw up?
وأي نوع من القادة ستنتجه؟
Хотели бы мы видеть таких людей во главе нашей страны?
Are they men that we'd want at the head of our country?
هل هم الرجال الذين نريدهم على رأس بلادنا؟
Я тоже читал труды г-на Ганди...
I too have read
Mr. Gandhi's writings...
لقد قرأت أيضًا كتابات السيد غاندي...
...но я бы предпочел, чтобы мной правил индийский террорист, чем английский.
...but l'd rather be ruled by an
Indian terrorist than an English one.
...لكنني أفضّل أن يحكمني إرهابي هندي بدلاً من إرهابي إنجليزي.
И я не намерен подчиняться такому закону.
And l don't intend to submit to that kind of law.
ولا أنوي الخضوع لهذا النوع من القانون.
Должен сказать, мне кажется...
I must say, it seems to me...
يجب أن أقول، يبدو لي...
...что это уже вышло за рамки таких средств, как пассивное сопротивление.
...that it's gone beyond remedies like passive resistance.
...أن الأمر قد تجاوز مجرد علاجات مثل المقاومة السلبية.
Если позволите...
If l may...
إذا أمكنني...
...я, например, никогда не выступал за пассивность.
...l, for one, have never advocated passive anything.
...أنا شخصياً لم أؤيد أبداً أي شيء سلبي.
Я с господином Джинной. Мы никогда не должны подчиняться таким законам...
I'm with Mr. Jinnah.
We must never submit to such laws...
أنا مع السيد جناح. يجب ألا نخضع لمثل هذه القوانين أبدًا...
...всегда.
...ever.
...أبدًا.
И я думаю, что наше сопротивление должно быть активным и провокационным.
And l think our resistance must be active and provocative.
وأعتقد أن مقاومتنا يجب أن تكون فعالة واستفزازية.
Могу ли я?
May I?
ربما أنا؟
Я хочу пристыдить всех тех, кто хочет обращаться с нами как с рабами.
I want to embarrass all those who wish to treat us as slaves.
أريد أن أحرج كل أولئك الذين يرغبون في معاملتنا كعبيد.
Спасибо.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Все они.
All of them.
كلهم.
-Простите мою глупую иллюстрацию. -Позвольте мне.
-Forgive my stupid illustration.
-Allow me.
-سامحني على التوضيح الغبي. -اسمح لي.
Нет, пожалуйста.
No, please.
لا من فضلك.
Но я хочу изменить их мнение...
But l want to change their minds...
ولكنني أريد أن أغير رأيهم...
...а не убивать их за слабости, которые есть у всех нас.
...not kill them for weaknesses we all possess.
...لا نقتلهم بسبب نقاط الضعف التي نمتلكها جميعًا.
А какое сопротивление вы бы оказали?
And what resistance would you offer?
وما هي المقاومة التي ستقدمها؟
Закон должен вступить в силу с 6 апреля.
The law is due to take effect from April 6.
ومن المقرر أن يدخل القانون حيز التنفيذ في السادس من أبريل/نيسان المقبل.
Я хочу обратиться к нации...
I want to call upon the nation...
أريد أن أدعو الأمة...
...сделать этот день днем ​​молитвы и поста.
...to make that a day of prayer and fasting.
...لجعله يوم صلاة وصيام.
Всеобщая забастовка?
A general strike?
إضراب عام؟
Я имею в виду день молитвы и поста.
I mean a day of prayer and fasting.
أقصد يوم للصلاة والصيام.
Конечно, никакой работы не было. Никаких автобусов.
Of course, no work could be done.
No buses.
بالطبع، لم يكن من الممكن إنجاز أي عمل. لم تكن هناك حافلات.
Поездов нет.
No trains.
لا يوجد قطارات.
Никаких заводов.
No factories.
لا مصانع.
Никакого администрирования.
No administration.
لا يوجد إدارة.
Страна остановится.
The country would stop.
البلد سوف تتوقف.
Боже мой, как бы это их напугало!
My God, it would terrify them!
يا إلهي، هذا سوف يرعبهم!
350 миллионов человек молятся?
350 million people at prayer?
350 مليون شخص يصلون؟
Даже английским газетам пришлось бы сообщить об этом...
Even the English newspapers would have to report that...
حتى الصحف الانجليزية ستضطر إلى الإبلاغ عن ذلك...
...и объясните почему.
...and explain why.
...ووضح السبب.
- Но сможем ли мы заставить людей это сделать? - Почему бы и нет?
-But could we get people to do it?
-Why not?
-ولكن هل يمكننا أن نجعل الناس يفعلون ذلك؟ -لماذا لا؟
Чампаран всколыхнул всю страну.
Champaran stirred the whole country.
أثار شامباران البلاد بأكملها.
Спасибо.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Они называют тебя «Махатмой».
They're calling you "Mahatma."
إنهم ينادونك بـ "المهاتما".
«Великая Душа».
"Great Soul."
"الروح العظيمة."
К счастью, до места, где я живу, такие новости доходят очень медленно.
Fortunately, such news comes very slowly to where l live.
ولحسن الحظ، فإن مثل هذه الأخبار تصل ببطء شديد إلى حيث أعيش.
Я думаю, если бы мы все работали над тем, чтобы это стало достоянием общественности...
I think if we all worked to publicize it...
أعتقد لو عملنا جميعًا على نشره...
...весь конгресс...
...all of congress...
...كل أعضاء الكونجرس...
...каждый известный нам путь....
...every avenue we know....
...كل الطرق التي نعرفها...
Я мог бы напечатать статьи в большинстве газет Дели и Бомбея.
I could get articles printed in most of the papers in Delhi and Bombay.
كان بإمكاني نشر المقالات في معظم الصحف في دلهي وبومباي.
Только гражданские лица посетят. Вы так не думаете, Ваше Высочество?
Only civilians will visit.
Don't you think so, Your Highness?
لن يزورنا إلا المدنيون. ألا تعتقد ذلك يا صاحب السمو؟
Конечно, армия всегда будет лояльна.
Of course, the army will always be loyal.
وبطبيعة الحال، فإن الجيش سيكون مخلصا دائما.
К вашему сведению, у нас 500 солдат.
I'll have you know, we've got 500 troops.
أريدك أن تعلم أن لدينا 500 جندي.
К утру они будут чертовски голодны, это я вам скажу.
They'll be damn hungry by morning,
I'll tell you that.
سوف يكونون جائعين للغاية بحلول الصباح، سأخبرك بذلك.
Извините, Ваше Превосходительство, г-н Киннох.
Excuse me, Your Excellency.
Mr. Kinnoch.
عذراً، يا صاحب السعادة، السيد كينوش.
Сэр, боюсь, это подтвердилось.
Sir, l'm afraid it's confirmed.
سيدي، أخشى أن الأمر مؤكد.
Ничего не работает, сэр.
Nothing's working, sir.
لا شيء يعمل، سيدي.
Автобусы, поезда, рынки.
The buses, the trains, the markets.
الحافلات والقطارات والأسواق.
Здесь даже нет обычного гражданского персонала, сэр.
There's not even any ordinary civilian staff here, sir.
لا يوجد حتى أي موظف مدني عادي هنا، يا سيدي.
Это только Дели и Бомбей?
Is it simply Delhi and Bombay?
هل الأمر يقتصر فقط على دلهي وبومباي؟
Карачи, Калькутта, Мадрас, Бангалор. Это тотально.
Karachi, Calcutta, Madras, Bangalore.
It's total.
كراتشي، كلكتا، مدراس، بنغالور. إنها كاملة.
Армии пришлось взять под контроль телеграф...
The army had to take over the telegraph...
كان على الجيش أن يستولي على التلغراف...
...иначе мы были бы отрезаны от мира.
...or we'd be cut off from the world.
...أو سنكون منفصلين عن العالم.
Я не могу в это поверить.
I can't believe it.
لا أستطيع أن أصدق ذلك.
Завтра он собирается продавать свою собственную газету в Бомбее, сэр.
He's going to sell his own paper tomorrow in Bombay, sir.
إنه سيقوم ببيع جريدته الخاصة غدًا في بومباي، يا سيدي.
Они призвали провести парад на Виктория-роуд.
They've called for a parade on Victoria Road.
لقد طالبوا بمسيرة في شارع فيكتوريا.
Арестуйте его.
Arrest him.
إعتقلوه
Ему нужно пойти в комнату для посетителей.
He's to go to the visitors' room.
سيذهب إلى غرفة الزوار.
Бапу.
Bapu.
بابو.
Ты тоже?
You too?
أنت أيضاً؟
Кажется, это менее официально, чем Махатма.
It seems less formal than Mahatma.
يبدو أقل رسمية من المهاتما.
После вашего ареста беспорядки практически не прекратились.
Since your arrest, the riots have hardly stopped.
منذ اعتقالك، لم تتوقف أعمال الشغب تقريبًا.
Не большие, но они продолжают вырываться.
Not big, but they keep breaking out.
ليست كبيرة، ولكنها تستمر في الظهور.
Я хочу остановить их.
I want to stop them.
أريد أن أوقفهم.
А Патель и Крипалани никогда не знают покоя.
And Patel and Kripalani, they're never at rest.
وباتيل وكريبالاني، لا يرتاحان أبدًا.
Однако некоторые английские мирные жители были убиты.
But some English civilians have been killed.
لكن بعض المدنيين الإنجليز قُتلوا.
А армия нападает на толпу с дубинками.
And the army is attacking crowds with clubs.
والجيش يهاجم الحشود بالهراوات.
Иногда хуже.
Sometimes worse.
في بعض الأحيان أسوأ.
Возможно, я ошибаюсь.
Maybe I'm wrong.
ربما أكون مخطئا.
Возможно, мы еще не готовы.
Maybe we're not ready yet.
ربما لسنا مستعدين بعد.
В Южной Африке нас было немного.
In South Africa, our numbers were small.
في جنوب أفريقيا، كان عددنا صغيرا.
Правительство напугано. Они не знают, что делать.
The government's afraid.
They don't know what to do.
الحكومة خائفة، لا تعرف ماذا تفعل.
Они больше боятся терроризма, чем вас.
They're more afraid of terrorism than of you.
إنهم يخافون من الإرهاب أكثر منك.
Вице-король согласился на ваше освобождение, если вы выступите за ненасилие.
The viceroy's agreed to your release if you will speak for nonviolence.
لقد وافق نائب الملك على إطلاق سراحك إذا تحدثت عن اللاعنف.
Я никогда не выступал ни за что другое.
I've never spoken for anything else.
لم أتحدث عن أي شيء آخر أبدًا.
Англия...
England...
إنجلترا...
...настолько мощный.
...is so powerful.
...قوية جدًا.
Его армия...
Its army...
جيشها...
...и его флот...
...and its navy...
...وبحريتها...
...все его современное оружие....
...all its modern weapons....
...كل أسلحتها الحديثة....
Но когда такая великая держава...
But when a great power like that...
ولكن عندما تكون هناك قوة عظيمة مثل تلك...
...бьет беззащитных людей...
...strikes defenseless people...
...يضرب الناس العزل...
...показывает свою жестокость...
...it shows its brutality...
...يظهر وحشيته...
...своей собственной слабости.
...its own weakness.
...ضعفه الخاص.
Особенно, когда эти люди не наносят ответный удар.
Especially when those people do not strike back.
وخاصة عندما لا يقوم هؤلاء الأشخاص بالرد.
Сопротивление не сработает.
Fighting back will not work.
لن تنجح المقاومة.
И вот почему Махатма...
And that is why the Mahatma...
ولهذا السبب المهاتما...
...умоляет нас встать на путь ненасилия.
...begs us to take the course of nonviolence.
...يطلب منا أن نتخذ مسار اللاعنف.
Назад! Назад!
Back away! Back away!
ابتعد! ابتعد!
Но если мы взбунтуемся...
But if we riot...
ولكن إذا قمنا بالشغب...
...если мы дадим отпор...
...if we fight back...
...إذا قاومنا...
...мы становимся вандалами...
...we become the vandals...
...نصبح المخربين...
...и они становятся законом.
...and they become the law.
... ويصبحون القانون.
Если мы выдержим их удары, то они — вандалы.
If we bear their blows, they are the vandals.
إذا تحملنا ضرباتهم فهم المخربون.
Бог и его закон на нас...
God and his law are on our--
الله وشريعته علينا--
Первая шеренга, встаньте на колени!
Front rank, kneel in position!
الصف الأمامي، اركع في وضعك!
Мы...
We...
نحن...
...нужно иметь смелость...
...must have the courage...
...يجب أن يكون لديك الشجاعة...
...чтобы принять их гнев.
...to take their anger.
...لأخذ غضبهم.
Стоит ли нам вынести предупреждение, сэр?
Should we issue a warning, sir?
هل يجب علينا إصدار تحذير يا سيدي؟
Их предупредили:
They've had their warning:
لقد تلقوا تحذيرهم:
Никаких встреч.
No meetings.
لا اجتماعات.
Огонь!
Fire!
نار!
Не торопись!
Take your time!
خذ وقتك!
Капрал!
Corporal!
عريف!
Слева от вас.
To your left.
على يسارك.
Генерал Дайер...
General Dyer...
الجنرال داير...
...правильно ли, что вы приказали своим войскам стрелять...
...is it correct that you ordered your troops to fire...
...هل صحيح أنك أمرت قواتك بإطلاق النار...
...в самой гуще толпы?
...at the thickest part of the crowd?
...في الجزء الأكثر كثافة من الحشد؟
Это так.
That is so.
وهذا صحيح.
1 51 6 жертв с...
1 51 6 casualties with...
1 51 6 ضحايا مع ...
...1 650 пуль.
...1 650 bullets.
...1650 رصاصة.
Моим намерением было преподать урок...
My intention was to inflict a lesson...
كان قصدي أن أعطي درسًا...
...это имело бы влияние на всю Индию.
...that would have an impact throughout all lndia.
... وهذا من شأنه أن يكون له تأثير في جميع أنحاء الهند.
Общий...
General...
عام...
...если бы вы смогли взять с собой бронированную машину...
...had you been able to take in the armored car...
...هل تمكنت من دخول السيارة المدرعة...
...вы бы открыли огонь из пулемета?
...would you have opened fire with the machine gun?
...هل كنت ستفتح النار بالرشاش؟
Я думаю, что, скорее всего, да.
I think, probably, yes.
أعتقد، ربما، نعم.
Генерал, вы знали, что в толпе были дети и женщины?
General, did you realize there were children and women in the crowd?
سيدي الجنرال، هل لاحظت أن هناك أطفال ونساء في الحشد؟
Я сделал.
I did.
فعلتُ.
Но это не имеет отношения к сути, которую вы хотели донести?
But that was irrelevant to the point you were making?
ولكن هذا كان غير ذي صلة بالنقطة التي كنت تثيرها؟
Это верно.
That is correct.
هذا صحيح.
Могу ли я спросить вас, какие меры вы приняли для раненых?
Could l ask you what provision you made for the wounded?
هل يمكنني أن أسألك ما هي التدابير التي اتخذتها للجرحى؟
Я был готов помочь любому, кто обратится.
I was ready to help any who applied.
لقد كنت مستعدًا لمساعدة أي شخص يتقدم بطلب.
Генерал, как ребенок...
General, how does a child...
سيدي الجنرال، كيف يمكن للطفل...
...застрелен из .303 Lee-Enfield...
...shot with a .303 Lee-Enfield...
...تم إطلاق النار عليه باستخدام .303 Lee-Enfield...
...обратиться за помощью?
...apply for help?
...التقدم بطلب للحصول على المساعدة؟
Простите, господа, но вы должны понять...
Forgive me, gentlemen, but you must understand...
سامحوني أيها السادة، ولكن يجب أن تفهموا...
...которые правительство Его Величества и британский народ отвергают...
...that His Majesty's government and the British people repudiate...
...أن حكومة جلالته والشعب البريطاني يرفضان...
...как резня, так и философия, которая ее подтолкнула.
...both the massacre and the philosophy that prompted it.
...المذبحة والفلسفة التي أدت إليها.
Сейчас...
Now...
الآن...
...что бы я хотел сделать...
...what l would like to do...
...ما أود أن أفعله...
...прийти к какому-то компромиссу по новому...
...is to come to some compromise over the new--
... هو التوصل إلى حل وسط بشأن الجديد--
Если позволите, Ваше Превосходительство...
If you will excuse me,
Your Excellency...
إذا سمحت لي يا صاحب السعادة...
...мы считаем, что дело вышло за рамки законодательства.
...it is our view that matters have gone beyond legislation.
...إن وجهة نظرنا هي أن الأمور قد تجاوزت التشريع.
Мы думаем, что пришло время вам признать...
We think it is time you recognized...
نعتقد أن الوقت قد حان لتدرك...
...что вы хозяева в чужом доме.
...that you are masters in someone else's home.
...أنكم سادة في بيت شخص آخر.
Несмотря на самые лучшие намерения лучших из вас...
Despite the best intentions of the best of you...
على الرغم من أفضل النوايا من أفضلكم...
...вам, по природе вещей, приходится унижать нас, чтобы контролировать нас.
...you must, in the nature of things, humiliate us to control us.
...يجب عليك، في طبيعة الأشياء، أن تهيننا لكي تسيطر علينا.
Генерал Дайер — лишь крайний пример этого принципа.
General Dyer is but an extreme example of the principle.
إن الجنرال داير ما هو إلا مثال متطرف لهذا المبدأ.
Тебе пора уходить.
It is time you left.
لقد حان الوقت لرحيلك.
С уважением, г-н Ганди...
With respect, Mr. Gandhi...
مع الاحترام السيد غاندي...
...без британского управления...
...without British administration...
...بدون الإدارة البريطانية...
...эта страна погрузится в хаос.
...this country would be reduced to chaos.
...هذا البلد سوف يتحول إلى حالة من الفوضى.
Мистер Киннох...
Mr. Kinnoch...
السيد كينوش...
...прошу вас признать, что нет людей...
...l beg you to accept that there is no people...
...أرجوك أن تقبل أنه لا يوجد شعب...
...которые не предпочли бы свое собственное плохое правительство...
...who would not prefer their own bad government...
...الذين لا يفضلون حكومتهم السيئة...
...хорошему правительству чужой державы.
...to the good government of an alien power.
...إلى الحكومة الصالحة لقوة أجنبية.
Мой дорогой сэр, Индия — британская страна.
My dear sir, India is British.
سيدي العزيز، الهند بريطانية.
Мы вряд ли являемся инопланетной державой.
We're hardly an alien power.
نحن لسنا قوة غريبة.
Господин Ганди.
Mr. Gandhi.
السيد غاندي.
Даже если бы Его Величество мог отказаться от всех других соображений...
Even if His Majesty could waive all other considerations...
حتى لو كان جلالته قادرا على التنازل عن جميع الاعتبارات الأخرى...
...у него есть долг перед миллионами его мусульманских подданных...
...he has a duty to the millions of his Muslim subjects...
...فإنه عليه واجب تجاه الملايين من رعيته المسلمين...
...которые составляют меньшинство в этой сфере.
...who are a minority in this realm.
...الذين هم أقلية في هذا المجال.
И опыт подсказывает, что его войска...
And experience suggests that his troops...
وتشير التجربة إلى أن قواته...
...и его администрация имеют важное значение...
...and his administration are essential...
...وإدارته ضرورية...
...чтобы обеспечить мир.
...in order to secure the peace.
...من أجل تأمين السلام.
Во всех странах есть религиозные меньшинства.
All nations contain religious minorities.
تحتوي جميع الدول على أقليات دينية.
Как и в других странах, у нас будут свои проблемы.
Like other countries, ours will have its problems.
كما هو الحال مع البلدان الأخرى، فإن بلدنا سوف يواجه مشاكله.
Но они будут нашими...
But they will be ours...
ولكنها ستكون لنا...
...не твое.
...not yours.
...ليس لك.
Как вы предлагаете сделать их своими?
How do you propose to make them yours?
كيف تقترح أن تجعلهم ملكك؟
Вы же не думаете, что мы просто уйдем из Индии?
You don't think we're just going to walk out of lndia.
لا تظن أننا سنخرج من الهند بسهولة.
Да.
Yes.
نعم.
В конце концов, вы уйдете...
In the end, you will walk out...
في النهاية سوف تخرج...
...потому что 100 000 англичан просто не могут контролировать...
...because 1 00,000 Englishmen simply cannot control...
...لأن 100 ألف إنجليزي لا يستطيعون السيطرة على...
...350 миллионов индийцев, если эти индийцы откажутся...
...350 million lndians if those Indians refuse...
...350 مليون هندي إذا رفض هؤلاء الهنود...
...сотрудничать.
...to cooperate.
...للتعاون.
И именно этого мы намерены добиться.
And that is what we intend to achieve.
وهذا ما نعتزم تحقيقه.
Мирное, ненасильственное несотрудничество...
Peaceful, nonviolent noncooperation...
عدم التعاون السلمي وغير العنيف...
...пока вы сами не увидите мудрость ухода...
...till you yourself see the wisdom of leaving...
...حتى ترى بنفسك حكمة الرحيل...
...Ваше Превосходительство.
...Your Excellency.
...صاحب السعادة.
Я сказал ему: «Вы же не ждете, что мы просто уйдем?»
I said to him, "You don't expect us just to walk out."
قلت له: "لا تتوقع منا أن نخرج هكذا".
И он сказал: «Да».
And he said, "Yes."
فقال: نعم.
Какой необычный человечек, не правда ли?
What an extraordinary little man, isn't he?
يا له من رجل صغير غير عادي، أليس كذلك؟
«Ненасилие, отказ от сотрудничества».
"Nonviolence, noncooperation."
"اللاعنف، عدم التعاون."
На мгновение я испугался, что они действительно собираются что-то сделать.
For a moment, I was afraid they were actually gonna do something.
لفترة من الوقت، كنت خائفة من أنهم سوف يفعلون شيئا فعلا.
Да, но я думаю, что было бы разумно какое-то время проявлять большую осторожность.
Yes, but l think it would be wise to be very cautious for a time.
نعم، ولكن أعتقد أنه من الحكمة أن نكون حذرين للغاية لبعض الوقت.
Закон о борьбе с терроризмом останется в законодательстве...
The Antiterrorist Act will remain on the statutes...
قانون مكافحة الإرهاب سيبقى على حاله
...но Ганди ни в коем случае не должен быть арестован.
...but on no account is Gandhi to be arrested.
...ولكن لا يجوز اعتقال غاندي بأي حال من الأحوال.
Какую бы беду он ни причинил...
Whatever mischief he causes...
مهما كان الضرر الذي يسببه...
...я не собираюсь делать из него мученика.
...l have no intention of making a martyr of him.
... ليس لدي أي نية لجعله شهيدًا.
Но сейчас происходит нечто худшее.
But now something worse is happening.
لكن الآن يحدث شيء أسوأ.
Когда Ганди и я росли...
When Gandhiji and I were growing up...
عندما كنت أنا وغاندي نكبر...
...женщины ткали свою собственную ткань.
...women wove their own cloth.
...كانت النساء ينسجن قماشهن بأنفسهن.
Но сейчас у миллионов людей нет работы...
But now there are millions who have no work...
لكن الآن هناك الملايين الذين ليس لديهم عمل...
...потому что те, кто может купить все необходимое в Англии.
...because those who can buy all they need from England.
...لأن أولئك الذين يستطيعون شراء كل ما يحتاجونه من إنجلترا.
Я говорю вместе с Ганди:
I say with Gandhiji:
أقول مع غاندي:
В самой лучшей ткани нет красоты...
There is no beauty in the finest cloth...
لا يوجد جمال في أرقى أنواع القماش...
...если это вызывает голод и несчастье.
...if it makes hunger and unhappiness.
...إذا كان يسبب الجوع والشقاء.
Мое сообщение вам...
My message to you...
رسالتي لك...
...это послание, которое я передал вашим братьям повсюду.
...is the message l have given to your brothers everywhere.
...هذه هي الرسالة التي وجهتها لإخوانكم في كل مكان.
Чтобы обрести независимость...
To gain independence...
للحصول على الاستقلال...
...мы должны доказать, что достойны этого.
...we must prove worthy of it.
...علينا أن نثبت جدارتنا بذلك.
Единство между индуистами и мусульманами должно быть всегда.
There must be
Hindu-Muslim unity always.
يجب أن تكون هناك وحدة هندوسية-إسلامية دائمًا.
Второй:
Second:
ثانية:
Ни с одним индийцем нельзя обращаться так, как с нами обращаются англичане.
No Indian must be treated as the English treat us.
لا ينبغي أن يعامل أي هندي كما يعاملنا الإنجليز.
Мы должны устранить неприкасаемость...
We must remove untouchability...
يجب علينا إزالة التمييز العنصري...
...из наших сердец и из наших жизней.
...from our hearts and from our lives.
...من قلوبنا ومن حياتنا.
Третий:
Third:
ثالث:
Мы должны бросить вызов британцам.
We must defy the British.
يجب علينا أن نتحدى البريطانيين.
Не насилием, которое воспламенит их волю...
Not with violence that will inflame their will...
لا بالعنف الذي من شأنه أن يشعل إرادتهم...
...но с твердостью, которая откроет им глаза.
...but with a firmness that will open their eyes.
...ولكن بحزم يفتح أعينهم.
Английские фабрики производят ткань...
English factories make the cloth...
المصانع الإنجليزية تصنع القماش...
...это и есть наша бедность.
...that makes our poverty.
...هذا ما يجعلنا فقراء.
Все те, кто хочет, чтобы англичане увидели...
All those who wish to make the English see...
كل من يرغب في جعل الإنجليز يرون...
...привези мне ткань из Манчестера и Лидса, которую ты носишь сегодня...
...bring me the cloth from Manchester and Leeds that you wear today...
...أحضر لي القماش الذي ترتديه اليوم من مانشستر وليدز...
...и мы зажжем огонь, который будет виден в Дели...
...and we will light a fire that will be seen in Delhi...
...وسنشعل ناراً ستُرى في دلهي...
...и в Лондоне.
...and in London.
...وفي لندن.
И если...
And if...
وإذا...
...как я...
...like me...
...مثلي...
...у вас останется только один кусок домотканой ткани...
...you are left with only one piece of homespun...
...لم يتبق لك سوى قطعة واحدة من القماش المنسوج منزليًا...
...носите его с достоинством.
...wear it with dignity.
...ارتديها بكرامة.
Большое спасибо.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
Нет, спасибо, я справлюсь.
No, thank you, I can manage.
لا، شكرا لك، أستطيع أن أتدبر الأمر.
Не разрушай мои благие намерения. Я и так чувствую себя виноватым...
Don't destroy my good intentions.
I already feel guilty...
لا تُفسدوا نواياي الطيبة. أشعر بالذنب بالفعل...
-...о путешествии вторым классом. -Вы заслужили несколько поблажек.
-...about traveling second class.
-You've earned a few indulgences.
-...بخصوص السفر بالدرجة الثانية. -لقد حصلت على بعض التنازلات.
Возможно, но Маулана сделан из более прочного материала.
Perhaps, but Maulana's made of sterner stuff.
ربما، ولكن المولانا مصنوع من أشياء أكثر صلابة.
Наши поезда встретились в Бомбее.
Our trains met in Bombay.
التقت قطاراتنا في بومباي.
И вот он снова здесь, образцовый ученик.
And there he is, back in that lot, the model disciple.
وهناك هو، مرة أخرى في تلك المجموعة، التلميذ النموذجي.
Есть еще один пассажир.
There's another passenger.
هناك راكب آخر.
Мисс Слейд из Лондона. Она писала Гандиджи много лет.
A Miss Slade from London. She's been writing to Gandhiji for years.
آنسة سليد من لندن. تكتب إلى غاندي منذ سنوات.
Она дочь английского адмирала.
She's the daughter of an English admiral.
إنها ابنة أميرال إنجليزي.
Что вы думаете о дочери английского адмирала...
What do you think the daughter of an English admiral...
ماذا تعتقد أن ابنة أميرال إنجليزي...
...предлагает сделать в нашем ашраме?
...proposes to do in our ashram?
...يقترح القيام بذلك في اشرمنا؟
- Потопить нас? - Судя по багажу, да.
-Sink us?
-From the looks of the luggage, yes.
-تغرقنا؟ -من مظهر الأمتعة، نعم.
Она хочет поселиться у нас. И Гандиджи согласился.
She wants to make her home with us.
And Gandhiji has agreed.
إنها تريد أن تجعل بيتها معنا. وقد وافق غاندي.
Мисс Слэйд!
Miss Slade!
آنسة سليد!
Вы были бы мистером Калленбахом.
You'd be Mr. Kallenbach.
سوف تكون السيد كالينباخ.
А вы будете мисс Слэйд?
And you would be Miss Slade?
وهل ستكونين السيدة سليد؟
Я предпочитаю имя, которое дал мне Гандиджи:
I prefer the name
Gandhiji has given me:
أفضّل الاسم الذي أعطاني إياه غاندي:
Мирабен.
Mirabehn.
ميرابين.
Не тяни так быстро. Ты снова его сломаешь.
Don't pull it so fast.
You'll break it again.
لا تسحبه بسرعة، ستكسره مرة أخرى.
Оставь это. Оставь это.
Leave it. Leave it.
اتركه. اتركه.
Бог дал тебе 10 больших пальцев.
God gave you 1 0 thumbs.
لقد أعطاك الله 10 إبهام.
Одиннадцать.
Eleven.
أحد عشر.
Сардар!
Sardar!
سردار!
Мирабен!
Mirabehn!
ميرابين!
Как, как.
Come, come.
كيف، كيف.
Ты будешь моей дочерью.
You will be my daughter.
سوف تكوني ابنتي.
Но потом...
But then...
ولكن بعد ذلك...
...начались беспорядки...
...some rioting broke out...
...اندلعت بعض أعمال الشغب...
...между индуистами и мусульманами.
...between Hindus and Muslims.
...بين الهندوس والمسلمين.
Жестокий, ужасный.
Violent, terrible.
عنيف، رهيب.
Было ли это спровоцировано...
Whether it was provoked...
سواء كان استفزازا...
...я не знаю.
...l don't know.
...لا أعلم.
Но это дало им повод ввести военное положение по всей Бенгалии.
But it gave them an excuse to impose martial law throughout Bengal.
لكن ذلك أعطاهم ذريعة لفرض الأحكام العرفية في جميع أنحاء البنغال.
Некоторые из действий военных...
Some of the things the military have done....
بعض الأشياء التي قام بها الجيش...
Ослабевает ли кампания?
Is the campaign weakening?
هل تضعف الحملة؟
Марши и протесты стали еще масштабнее.
The marches and protests are bigger, if anything.
المسيرات والاحتجاجات أكبر، إن لم يكن أكبر.
Но с учетом цензуры здесь...
But with the censorship here...
ولكن مع الرقابة هنا...
...в Англии знают больше, чем мы.
...they know more in England than we do.
...إنهم يعرفون في إنجلترا أكثر مما نعرفه.
Мысль о том, что ты можешь страдать в одиночестве, подрывает мужество.
It saps the courage to think you may be suffering alone.
إن التفكير بأنك قد تعاني وحدك يستنزف شجاعتك.
Они не одиноки.
They are not alone.
وهم ليسوا وحيدين.
А военное положение лишь показывает, в каком отчаянном положении находятся британцы.
And martial law only shows how desperate the British are.
والأحكام العرفية لا تظهر إلا مدى يأس البريطانيين.
Это домотканое?
Is that homespun?
هل هذا محلي الصنع؟
Я послал за ним отсюда. Я сам его покрасил.
I sent for it from here.
I dyed it myself.
لقد طلبته من هنا. لقد صبغته بنفسي.
Как рабочие в Англии относятся к тому, что мы делаем?
What do the workers in England make of what we're doing?
ماذا يفعل العمال في إنجلترا بما نقوم به؟
Это наверняка создало трудности.
It must have produced hardship.
لا بد أن يكون قد تسبب في مشقة.
Он имеет...
It has...
لقد كان لديه...
...но вы удивитесь. Они понимают.
...but you'd be surprised.
They do understand.
...لكنك ستُفاجأ. إنهم يفهمون.
Хороший.
Good.
جيد.
Ба придется научить тебя еще и прясть.
Ba will have to teach you to spin too.
سيتعين على با أن يعلمك كيفية الدوران أيضًا.
- Я бы лучше пошёл маршем. - Сначала покружись!
-l'd rather march.
-First, spin!
-أفضل أن أسير. -أولا، أدور!
Пусть остальные пока помаршируют.
Let the others march for a time.
دع الآخرين يسيرون لبعض الوقت.
Я научу тебя всем нашим глупостям.
I'll teach you all our foolishness.
سأعلمك كل حماقاتنا.
И ты должен научить меня своему.
And you must teach me yours.
ويجب عليك أن تعلميني خاصتك.
Мы сжигаем британское сукно! Мы сжигаем британское сукно!
We burn British cloth!
نحرق القماش البريطاني! نحرق القماش البريطاني!
Да здравствует Ганди! Да здравствует Ганди!
Long live Gandhiji!
عاش غاندي! عاش غاندي!
Британское правление должно уйти! Британское правление должно уйти!
British rule must go!
يجب أن يرحل الحكم البريطاني! يجب أن يرحل الحكم البريطاني!
Я засуну это тебе в глотку!
I'll stuff it down your damn throat!
سأضعه في حلقك اللعين!
Помогите нам!
Help us!
ساعدونا!
Оставьте нас в покое! Мы вам не причиним вреда.
Leave us alone!
We're not harming you.
اتركونا وشأننا! نحن لا نؤذيك.
Иди своей дорогой. Иди своей дорогой!
Go on your way. On your way!
إستمر ​​في طريقك.إستمر ​​في طريقك!
Вернись!
Come back!
عد!
Помогите нам! Помогите нам!
Help us! Help us!
ساعدونا! ساعدونا!
Помогите! Помогите!
Help! Help!
مساعدة! مساعدة!
Это единственная новость, которую они не подвергли цензуре.
That's one bit of news they haven't censored.
هذا هو أحد الأخبار التي لم تخضع للرقابة.
Теперь это по всему миру.
Now it's all over the world.
والآن أصبح في جميع أنحاء العالم.
«Ненасилие» в Индии.
India's "nonviolence."
"اللاعنف" في الهند
Что мы можем сделать?
What can we do?
ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل؟
Мы должны положить конец кампании.
We must end the campaign.
يجب علينا إنهاء الحملة.
После того, что они сделали во время бойни? Это только око за око.
After what they did at the massacre?
It's only an eye for an eye.
بعد ما فعلوه في المجزرة؟ العين بالعين فقط.
Принцип «око за око» в конечном итоге приведет к тому, что весь мир ослепнет.
An eye for an eye only ends up making the whole world blind.
إن مبدأ العين بالعين لا يؤدي إلا إلى جعل العالم كله أعمى.
Знаете ли вы, на какие жертвы пошли люди?
Do you know the sacrifices people have made?
هل تعلم التضحيات التي قدمها الناس؟
Мы больше никогда не получим такой же преданности делу.
We'd never get the same commitment again, ever.
لن نحصل على نفس الالتزام مرة أخرى أبدًا.
Вся Индия в движении!
The whole of India is on the move!
الهند بأكملها في حالة تحرك!
Да, но в каком направлении?
Yes, but in what direction?
نعم ولكن في أي إتجاه؟
Если мы обретем свободу ценой убийств и кровопролития, я не хочу в этом участвовать.
If we obtain our freedom by murder and bloodshed, l want no part of it.
إذا حصلنا على حريتنا بالقتل وإراقة الدماء، فلن أكون جزءًا منها.
Бапу, ты отец нации.
Bapu, you are the father of the nation.
بابو، أنت والد الأمة.
Сегодня я не вижу в этом никаких оснований, кроме стыда.
Today, l see no ground in that for anything but shame.
اليوم، لا أرى أي أساس لذلك إلا العار.
Это был один инцидент.
This was one incident.
كان هذا حادثا واحدا.
Расскажите это семьям погибших полицейских.
Tell that to the families of the policemen who died.
أخبروا ذلك لعائلات رجال الشرطة الذين ماتوا.
Бапу, вся нация марширует.
Bapu, the whole nation is marching.
بابو، الأمة بأكملها تسير.
Они не остановятся, даже если мы их попросим.
They wouldn't stop, even if we asked them to.
لن يتوقفوا حتى لو طلبنا منهم ذلك.
Я спрошу.
I will ask.
سأسأل.
И я буду поститься в качестве покаяния за то, что я вызвал такие эмоции.
And l will fast as a penance for my part in arousing such emotions.
وسأصوم تكفيراً عن دوري في إثارة مثل هذه المشاعر.
И я не остановлюсь, пока они не остановятся.
And l will not stop until they stop.
ولن أتوقف حتى يتوقفوا.
Но....
But....
لكن....
Боже! Можете быть уверены, британцы не будут это цензурировать.
God! You can be sure the British won't censor that.
يا إلهي! كن على يقين أن البريطانيين لن يحظروا هذا.
Они повесят его на каждом углу.
They'll put it on every street corner.
سيضعونها على زاوية كل شارع.
Ганди, люди возбуждены.
Gandhiji, people are aroused.
غاندي، الناس متحمسون.
Они не остановятся!
They won't stop!
لن يتوقفوا!
Если я умру, возможно, они остановятся.
If l die, perhaps they will stop.
إذا مت، ربما سيتوقفون.
Мне нужно подготовиться к утренней молитве.
I must get ready for morning prayers.
يجب أن أستعد لصلاة الصباح.
Мирабен здесь.
Mirabehn is here.
ميرابين هنا.
Я принесла вам питьевую воду.
I've brought your drinking water.
لقد أحضرت لك مياه الشرب.
Там есть немного лимонного сока. Вот и все.
There's a little lemon juice in it.
That's all.
فيه قليل من عصير الليمون، هذا كل شيء.
Герман отправился на встречу с Пандитом Неру.
Herman has gone to meet Pandit Nehru.
ذهب هيرمان لمقابلة البانديت نهرو.
Пришла телеграмма.
There was a telegram.
وكان هناك برقية.
Почти везде это прекратилось.
Almost everywhere, it has stopped.
لقد توقف الأمر في كل مكان تقريبًا.
Когда оно повсюду...
When it is everywhere...
عندما يكون في كل مكان...
...тогда мои молитвы будут услышаны.
...then my prayers will be answered.
...ثم سيتم الرد على صلاتي.
Вы считаете меня упрямым?
Do you find me stubborn?
هل تجدني عنيدًا؟
Я не знаю.
I don't know.
لا أعرف.
Я знаю, что ты прав.
I know that you are right.
أعلم أنك على حق.
Я не знаю, правильно ли это.
I don't know that this is right.
لا أعلم أن هذا صحيح.
Могу ли я вас повернуть?
May I turn you?
هل يمكنني أن أحولك؟
Когда я отчаиваюсь...
When I despair...
عندما أشعر باليأس...
...я помню это на протяжении всей истории...
...l remember that all through history...
...أتذكر ذلك طوال التاريخ...
...путь истины и любви всегда побеждал.
...the way of truth and love has always won.
...إن طريق الحقيقة والحب قد انتصر دائمًا.
Были тираны и убийцы...
There have been tyrants and murderers...
لقد كان هناك طغاة و قتلة...
...и какое-то время они могут казаться непобедимыми.
...and, for a time, they can seem invincible.
... ولفترة من الوقت، قد يبدو الأمر وكأنهم لا يقهرون.
Но в конце концов они всегда падают.
But in the end, they always fall.
ولكن في النهاية، فإنهم يسقطون دائمًا.
Подумайте об этом.
Think of it.
فكر في الأمر.
Всегда.
Always.
دائماً.
Всякий раз, когда вы сомневаетесь, что это Божий путь...
Whenever you are in doubt that that is God's way...
كلما كنت في شك بأن هذه هي طريقة الله...
...каким должен быть мир...
...the way the world is meant to be...
...الطريقة التي من المفترض أن يكون عليها العالم...
...подумайте об этом...
...think of that...
...فكر في ذلك...
...а затем попытаться сделать по-своему.
...and then try to do it his way.
...ثم حاول أن تفعل ذلك بطريقته.
А теперь, можно мне еще порцию лимонного сока?
And now, could l have another feast of lemon juice?
والآن، هل يمكنني أن أستمتع بوجبة أخرى من عصير الليمون؟
Пандитджи!
Panditji!
بانديتجي!
Джинна...
Jinnah...
جناح...
...Патель...
...Patel...
...باتيل...
...весь конгресс призвал положить конец несотрудничеству.
...all of congress has called for the end of noncooperation.
...لقد دعا الكونجرس بأكمله إلى إنهاء عدم التعاون.
Не было ни одной демонстрации.
There's not been one demonstration.
ولم تكن هناك أية مظاهرة.
По всей Индии люди молятся о том, чтобы вы прекратили пост.
All over lndia, people are praying that you will end the fast.
في جميع أنحاء الهند، الناس يصلون من أجل إنهاء الصيام.
Они ходят по улицам...
They're walking in the streets...
إنهم يمشون في الشوارع...
...преподнесение гирлянд полиции...
...offering garlands to the police...
...تقديم أكاليل الزهور للشرطة...
...и британские солдаты.
...and British soldiers.
...والجنود البريطانيين.
Возможно, я перестарался.
Perhaps I have overdone it.
ربما أنني بالغت في الأمر.
-Доброе утро, Бапу. -Доброе утро.
-Good morning, Bapu.
-Good morning.
-صباح الخير، بابو. -صباح الخير.
Не отпускай его. Если он меня ударит, мне конец.
Don't let him go.
If he bumps me, I'm done for.
لا تدعه يذهب. إذا صدمني، سأنتهي.
Не волнуйся, я его не отпущу.
Don't worry, l won't let him go.
لا تقلق، لن أسمح له بالذهاب.
Извините, мистер Ганди, сэр...
I'm sorry, Mr. Gandhi, sir...
أنا آسف يا سيد غاندي، سيدي...
...но вы арестованы.
...but you're under arrest.
...ولكنك تحت الإعتقال.
По какому обвинению?
On what charge?
بأي تهمة؟
Подстрекательство к мятежу.
Sedition.
الفتنة.
Вы не можете быть серьезны.
You can't be serious.
لا يمكنك أن تكون جديا.
Этот человек только что остановил революцию.
This man has just stopped a revolution.
لقد أوقف هذا الرجل الثورة للتو.
Это может быть так.
That's as may be.
وهذا ما قد يكون.
Я знаю только то, что мне поручено выполнить.
I only know what
I am charged to perform.
أنا أعرف فقط ما أنا مكلف بأدائه.
Я не верю!
I don't believe it!
انا لا اصدق ذلك!
Даже британцы не могут быть такими глупыми.
Even the British can't be that stupid.
حتى البريطانيون لا يمكن أن يكونوا أغبياء إلى هذه الدرجة.
Помогите мне, пожалуйста.
Help me, please.
ساعدني من فضلك.
Мира, ты должна присмотреть за Ба.
Mira, you must look after Ba.
ميرا، يجب عليك الاعتناء ببا.
Если случится хоть один протест, хоть один бунт, хоть какой-то позор...
If there is one protest, one riot, a disgrace of any kind...
إذا كان هناك احتجاج واحد، شغب واحد، عار من أي نوع...
...я снова буду поститься.
...l will fast again.
...سوف أصوم مرة أخرى.
Герман.
Herman.
هيرمان.
Я был во многих поездках.
I have been on many trips.
لقد قمت بالعديد من الرحلات.
Мир.
Monda.
عالم.
Это просто очередное путешествие.
This is just another trip.
هذه مجرد رحلة أخرى.
Я в вашем распоряжении.
I am at your command.
أنا تحت أمرك.
Я знаю, что мы не готовы к моей независимости.
I know we are not ready for my kind of independence.
أعلم أننا لسنا مستعدين لهذا النوع من الاستقلال.
Если меня посадят в тюрьму, возможно, это будет лучшим протестом...
If l'm sent to jail, perhaps that is the best protest...
إذا تم إرسالي إلى السجن، ربما يكون هذا أفضل احتجاج...
...наша страна может сделать в это время.
...our country can make at this time.
...بلدنا قادر على ذلك في هذا الوقت.
И если это поможет Индии, я никогда не отказывал Его Величеству в гостеприимстве.
And if it helps lndia, l've never refused His Majesty's hospitality.
وإذا كان ذلك يساعد الهند، فأنا لم أرفض أبدًا ضيافة جلالته.
Позовите заключенного в бар.
Call the prisoner to the bar.
استدعاء السجين إلى البار.
«Отказ от сотрудничества имеет одну цель:
"Noncooperation has one aim:
"إن عدم التعاون له هدف واحد:
Свержение правительства.
The overthrow of the government.
اسقاط الحكومة
Подстрекательство к мятежу должно стать нашим кредо.
Sedition must become our creed.
يجب أن تصبح الفتنة عقيدتنا.
Мы не должны давать пощады...
We must give no quarter...
لا ينبغي لنا أن نعطي أي ربع...
...и мы не можем ожидать ничего подобного."
...nor can we expect any."
...ولا يمكننا أن نتوقع أي شيء."
- Вы отрицаете, что написали это? - Вовсе нет.
-Do you deny writing it?
-Not at all.
-هل تنكر كتابته؟ -لا إطلاقا.
И я сэкономлю время суда...
And l will save the court's time...
وسأوفر وقت المحكمة...
...мой господин, заявляя под присягой, что по сей день...
...my lord, by stating under oath that, to this day...
... سيدي، من خلال التصريح تحت القسم أنه، إلى يومنا هذا...
...я считаю, что отказ от сотрудничества со злом — это долг...
...l believe noncooperation with evil is a duty...
...أعتقد أن عدم التعاون مع الشر هو واجب...
...и что британское правление в Индии - зло.
...and that British rule of lndia is evil.
...وأن الحكم البريطاني للهند شرير.
Обвинение окончено, милорд.
The prosecution rests, my lord.
لقد انتهى الإدعاء يا سيدي.
Полагаю, вы сами себя защищаете, г-н Ганди.
I presume you are conducting your own defense, Mr. Gandhi.
أفترض أنك تقوم بالدفاع عن نفسك، السيد غاندي.
У меня нет защиты, милорд. Я виновен в том, в чем меня обвиняют.
I have no defense, my lord.
I am guilty as charged.
ليس لدي أي دفاع يا سيدي. أنا مذنب كما هو متهم.
И если вы действительно верите в свою правовую систему...
And if you truly believe in your system of law...
وإذا كنت تؤمن حقا بنظامك القانوني...
...вы должны подвергнуть меня самому суровому наказанию.
...you must inflict on me the severest penalty possible.
...يجب أن تفرض علي أقصى عقوبة ممكنة.
Я не могу игнорировать тот факт, что вы относитесь к другой категории...
It is impossible for me to ignore that you're in a different category...
من المستحيل بالنسبة لي أن أتجاهل أنك في فئة مختلفة...
...от любого человека, которого я когда-либо пробовал...
...from any person
I have ever tried...
...من أي شخص سبق أن حاولته...
...или, скорее всего, попытаюсь.
...or am likely to try.
...أو من المرجح أن أحاول.
Тем не менее, мой долг вынести вам приговор...
Nevertheless, it is my duty to sentence you...
ومع ذلك، فمن واجبي أن أحكم عليك...
...к шести годам лишения свободы.
...to six years' imprisonment.
...إلى ست سنوات سجنًا.
Однако, если правительство Его Величества когда-нибудь позднее...
If, however, His Majesty's government should, at some later date...
ولكن إذا ما قررت حكومة جلالته في وقت لاحق...
...считаю целесообразным сократить срок...
...see fit to reduce the term...
... أرى أنه من المناسب تقليص المدة...
...никто не будет более доволен, чем я.
...no one will be better pleased than I.
... لن يكون أحد أكثر سعادة مني.
Да, я уверен, что именно на это они и надеялись.
Yes, l'm sure that's exactly what they hoped.
نعم، أنا متأكد من أن هذا هو بالضبط ما كانوا يأملونه.
Посадить его на несколько лет в тюрьму. Если повезет, его забудут.
Put him in prison a few years.
With luck, he'd be forgotten.
ضعوه في السجن لبضع سنوات. مع قليل من الحظ، سيُنسى.
Возможно, они даже смогут его усмирить.
Maybe they could even subdue him.
ربما يمكنهم حتى إخضاعه.
Ну, его, конечно, не забыли.
Well, he certainly wasn't forgotten.
حسنًا، لم يُنسى بالتأكيد.
Как только он вышел, он снова принялся бродить по сельской местности...
As soon as he got out, he was back tramping the countryside...
بمجرد خروجه، عاد للتجوال في الريف...
...проповедуя ненасилие и требуя свободной Индии.
...preaching nonviolence and demanding a free lndia.
...الدعوة إلى اللاعنف والمطالبة بالهند الحرة.
Все знают, что грядет очередная схватка.
Everyone knows another showdown's coming.
الجميع يعلم أن هناك مواجهة أخرى قادمة.
Как американский журналист в Центральной Америке...
How does an American journalist in Central America...
كيف يعمل الصحفي الأمريكي في أمريكا الوسطى؟
...узнать, что Ганди все равно родился в Порбандаре?
...learn that Gandhi was born in Porbandar anyway?
... هل تعلم أن غاندي ولد في بوربندر على أي حال؟
Я знаю о нем уже давно.
I've been aware of him for a long time.
لقد كنت على علم به منذ فترة طويلة.
Он, безусловно, делает хорошие копии.
He certainly makes good copy.
إنه بالتأكيد يصنع نسخة جيدة.
На днях Уинстон Черчилль назвал его полуголым индийским факиром.
The other day, Winston Churchill called him a half-naked Indian fakir.
في يوم آخر، وصفه ونستون تشرشل بأنه فقير هندي نصف عارٍ.
Я встречался с ним однажды.
I met him once.
لقد التقيت به مرة واحدة.
- Что, ты имеешь в виду Ганди? - Да.
-What, you mean Gandhi?
-Yeah.
-ماذا تقصد غاندي؟ -نعم.
Южная Африка, давным-давно.
South Africa, a long time ago.
جنوب أفريقيا، منذ زمن طويل.
Интересно, узнает ли он меня.
I wonder if he'll recognize me.
أتساءل عما إذا كان سيتعرف علي.
Каким он был?
What was he like?
كيف كان؟
Тогда у него была густая шевелюра.
He had a full head of hair then.
وكان رأسه ممتلئا بالشعر حينها.
Мы были как студенты колледжа, пытающиеся во всем разобраться.
We were like college students, trying to figure everything out.
كنا مثل طلاب الجامعة، نحاول معرفة كل شيء.
Что ж, он, должно быть, нашел некоторые ответы.
Well, he must have found some of the answers.
حسنًا، لا بد أنه وجد بعض الإجابات.
Я буду твоим помощником в каждом твоем достойном желании.
In every worthy wish of yours,
I shall be your helpmate.
في كل رغبة تستحقها، سأكون مساعدك.
Помощник.
Helpmate.
رفيق.
Сделайте четвертый шаг, чтобы мы всегда были полны радости.
Take the fourth step, that we may be ever full ofjoy.
اتخذ الخطوة الرابعة، حتى نكون ممتلئين بالفرح إلى الأبد.
Я всегда буду жить преданной тебе...
I will ever live devoted to you...
سوف أعيش مخلصًا لك إلى الأبد...
...говорить слова любви и молиться за ваше счастье.
...speaking words of love and praying for your happiness.
... التحدث بكلمات الحب والصلاة من أجل سعادتك.
Сделайте пятый шаг...
Take the fifth step...
اتخذ الخطوة الخامسة...
...хождение вокруг костра...
...the walking around a fire...
...المشي حول النار...
...чтобы мы могли служить людям.
...that we may serve the people.
...حتى نتمكن من خدمة الشعب.
Я последую за тобой...
I will follow close behind you...
سأتبعك عن كثب...
...и помогать служить людям.
...and help to serve the people.
...والمساعدة في خدمة الناس.
Сделайте шестой шаг...
Take the sixth step...
اتخذ الخطوة السادسة...
...чтобы мы могли следовать нашим обетам в жизни.
...that we may follow our vows in life.
...حتى نتمكن من اتباع عهودنا في الحياة.
Я последую за тобой во всех наших обетах и ​​обязанностях.
I will follow you in all our vows and duties.
سأتبعك في جميع عهودنا وواجباتنا.
Сделайте седьмой шаг...
Take the seventh step...
اتخذ الخطوة السابعة...
...чтобы мы могли когда-нибудь жить как друзья.
...that we may ever live as friends.
...أن نعيش كأصدقاء إلى الأبد.
Ты мой лучший друг...
You are my best friend...
أنت أفضل صديق لي...
...мой высший гуру...
...my highest guru...
...معلمي الأعلى...
...и мой суверенный господин.
...and my sovereign lord.
... وسيدي صاحب السيادة.
А потом я положил ей в рот сладкую пшеничную лепешку.
And then I put a sweetened wheat cake in her mouth.
وبعد ذلك وضعت كعكة القمح المحلاة في فمها.
И я положил ему в рот сладкую пшеничную лепешку.
And l put a sweetened wheat cake in his mouth.
وأضع كعكة القمح المحلاة في فمه.
И с этим нас объявили...
And with that, we were pronounced...
ومع هذا تم إعلاننا...
...муж и жена.
...man and wife.
...الرجل وزوجته.
Нам обоим было по 13 лет.
We were both 1 3.
كنا كلينا 1 3.
Это красиво.
It's beautiful.
إنه جميل.
Даже будучи мальчиком...
Even as a boy...
حتى عندما كنت صبيا...
...я так и думал.
...l thought so.
...لقد اعتقدت ذلك.
Спасибо.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Пытаться угнаться за вами — все равно что гоняться за зайцем.
Trying to keep up with you is like chasing a jackrabbit.
إن محاولة مواكبتك هي مثل مطاردة أرنب بري.
Вы пришли, потому что думаете, что что-то произойдет.
You've come because you think something is going to happen.
لقد أتيت لأنك تعتقد أن شيئًا ما سيحدث.
- Так ли это? - Возможно.
-ls it?
-Perhaps.
-هل هو كذلك؟ -ربما.
Я пришел сюда, чтобы подумать об этом.
I've come here to think about it.
لقد جئت إلى هنا للتفكير في الأمر.
Вы хорошо помните Южную Африку?
Do you remember much of South Africa?
هل تتذكر الكثير عن جنوب أفريقيا؟
О, да. Отличная сделка.
Oh, yes. A great deal.
أوه نعم، صفقة رائعة.
Я путешествовал так далеко...
I've traveled so far...
لقد سافرت حتى الآن...
...и так много думал.
...and thought so much.
...وفكرت كثيرا.
Как видите, мой город — морской.
As you can see, my city is a sea city.
كما ترون، مدينتي هي مدينة بحرية.
Всегда полно индусов...
Always full of Hindus...
دائما مليئة بالهندوس...
...мусульмане...
...Muslims...
...المسلمين...
...сикхи, евреи, персы.
...Sikhs, Jews, Persians.
...السيخ واليهود والفرس.
Секта моей семьи называлась Пранами.
My family's sect was the Pranami.
كانت طائفة عائلتي هي البرانامي.
Конечно, индуист.
Hindu, of course.
هندوسي، بالطبع.
Но в нашем храме священник читал...
But in our temple, the priest used to read...
ولكن في معبدنا كان الكاهن يقرأ...
...из мусульманского Корана...
...from the Muslim Koran...
...من القرآن الكريم...
...и индуистская Гита, переходя от одного к другому...
...and the Hindu Gita, moving from one to the other...
...والهندو جيتا، تنتقل من واحدة إلى الأخرى...
...как будто не имеет значения, какая книга прочитана...
...as if it mattered not which book was read...
... كما لو أن الأمر لا يهم أي كتاب تمت قراءته...
...до тех пор, пока поклонялись Богу.
...as long as God was worshiped.
...ما دام الله يعبد.
Когда я был мальчиком...
When I was a boy...
عندما كنت صغيرا...
...я пел песню в храме.
...l used to sing a song in the temple.
...كنت أغني أغنية في المعبد.
Истинный ученик знает чужие беды.
A true disciple
Knows another's woes
التلميذ الحقيقي يعرف مشاكل الآخرين
Как его собственный
As his own
كما هو خاص به
Он кланяется всем...
He bows to all...
ينحني للجميع...
...и никого не презирает.
...and despises none.
...ولا يحتقر أحدا.
Как и все остальные мальчики...
Like all other boys...
مثل كل الأولاد الآخرين...
...я спел слова...
...l sang the words...
...غنيت الكلمات...
...не думая о том, что они имели в виду или как они могли бы на меня повлиять.
...not thinking what they meant or how they might influence me.
... دون أن أفكر فيما تعنيه أو كيف يمكن أن تؤثر علي.
Я проделал большой путь.
I've traveled so far.
لقد سافرت حتى الآن.
И все, что я сделал, это вернулся...
And all l've done is come back...
وكل ما فعلته هو العودة...
...дом.
...home.
...بيت.
Подождите минуту.
Wait a minute.
انتظر دقيقة.
- Знаешь, что ты сделаешь? - Это было бы невежливо с моей стороны...
-You know what you're gonna do?
-lt would have been uncivil of me...
- هل تعلم ماذا ستفعل؟ - لقد كان ذلك سيكون غير لائق مني...
...позволить вам совершить столь дальнюю поездку просто так.
...to let you make such a long trip for nothing.
...أن تسمح لك بالقيام برحلة طويلة كهذه من أجل لا شيء.
-Куда ты идёшь? -Пошли.
-Where are you going?
-Come.
-إلى أين أنت ذاهب؟ -تعال.
-Куда мы идем? -Обратно в ашрам.
-Where are we going?
-Back to the ashram.
-إلى أين نحن ذاهبون؟ -العودة إلى الأشرم.
Затем, чтобы доказать новому вице-королю...
Then to prove to the new viceroy...
ثم لإثبات ذلك للحاكم الجديد...
...что указ короля больше не действует в Индии.
...that the king's writ no longer runs in lndia.
...أن أمر الملك لم يعد يسري في الهند.
Соль?
Salt?
ملح؟
Да, сэр. Он собирается пойти к морю и добыть соль.
Yes, sir. He's going to march to the sea and make salt.
نعم سيدي. سيذهب إلى البحر ويصنع الملح.
На производство соли действует королевская монополия.
There's a royal monopoly on the manufacture of salt.
هناك احتكار ملكي لتصنيع الملح.
Изготавливать и продавать его без государственной лицензии незаконно.
It's illegal to make it or sell it without a government license.
من غير القانوني تصنيعه أو بيعه دون ترخيص حكومي.
Хорошо, он нарушает закон.
All right, he's breaking the law.
حسنًا، إنه يخالف القانون.
Чего это нас лишит? Двух рупий налога на соль?
What will that deprive us of?
Two rupees of salt tax?
ماذا سيحرمنا هذا؟ روبيتين ضريبة ملح؟
Это не серьезная атака на доходы. Ее основное значение — символическое.
It's not a serious attack on the revenue.
Its primary importance is symbolic.
ليس هجومًا خطيرًا على الإيرادات، بل إن أهميته رمزية بالدرجة الأولى.
- Не надо меня опекать, Чарльз. - Нет, сэр, я...
-Don't patronize me, Charles.
-No, sir, l....
-لا تتعامل معي بتعالٍ يا تشارلز. -لا يا سيدي، أنا...
В этом климате ничто не может существовать без воды и соли.
In this climate, nothing lives without water or salt.
في هذا المناخ لا شيء يعيش بدون ماء أو ملح.
Наш абсолютный контроль над ним — это контроль над пульсом Индии.
Our absolute control of it is a control on the pulse of India.
إن سيطرتنا المطلقة عليها هي بمثابة سيطرة على نبض الهند.
И это основа этой декларации независимости?
And that's the basis of this declaration of independence?
وهذا هو أساس إعلان الاستقلال هذا؟
В тот день, когда он отправится...
The day he sets off...
اليوم الذي ينطلق فيه...
...каждый должен поднять флаг «Свободной Индии».
...everyone is supposed to raise the flag of "Free lndia."
...من المفترض أن يرفع الجميع علم "الهند الحرة".
А затем он идет пешком около 240 миль к морю и добывает соль.
And then he walks some 240 miles to the sea and makes salt.
ثم يمشي حوالي 240 ميلاً إلى البحر ويصنع الملح.
Я говорю, не обращайте внимания.
I say ignore it.
أقول تجاهله.
Пусть поднимут свои проклятые флаги.
Let them raise their damned flags.
فليرفعوا أعلامهم اللعينة.
Пусть он сделает свою соль.
Let him make his salt.
فليصنع ملحه.
Это будет иметь лишь символическое значение, если мы решим сделать это так.
It's only symbolic if we choose to make it so.
إنه رمزي فقط إذا اخترنا أن نجعله كذلك.
Он прибудет к морю...
He'll arrive at the sea...
سيصل إلى البحر...
...в годовщину резни в Амритсаре.
...on the anniversary of the Massacre of Amritsar.
...في ذكرى مذبحة أمريتسار.
Генерал Эдгар прав. Не обращайте внимания.
General Edgar is right. lgnore it.
الجنرال إدغار على حق. تجاهله.
Господину Ганди придется приложить гораздо больше усилий...
Mr. Gandhi will find it takes a great deal more...
وسوف يجد السيد غاندي أن الأمر يتطلب الكثير من العمل...
...чем щепотка соли, чтобы разрушить Британскую империю.
...than a pinch of salt to bring down the British Empire.
...من قليل من الملح لإسقاط الإمبراطورية البريطانية.
Вы оказали мне большую услугу.
You've done me a great service.
لقد قدمت لي خدمة عظيمة.
Вовсе нет, сэр.
Not at all, sir.
لا على الإطلاق يا سيدي.
Было бы невежливо с нашей стороны позволить вам совершить столь дальнюю поездку просто так.
It would be uncivil for us to let you make such a long trip for nothing.
سيكون من غير اللائق من جانبنا أن نسمح لك بالقيام برحلة طويلة كهذه من أجل لا شيء.
Мы пойдем.
We'll go.
سوف نذهب.
Да здравствует Ганди! Да здравствует Ганди!
Long live Gandhiji!
عاش غاندي! عاش غاندي!
Если вас сейчас арестуют, все кончено?
Is it over if they arrest you now?
هل انتهى الأمر إذا ألقوا القبض عليك الآن؟
Нет, если меня арестуют...
Not if they arrest me...
لا إذا اعتقلوني...
...или 1 000 или 10 000.
...or 1 000 or 1 0,000.
...أو 1000 أو 10000.
Не только генералы умеют планировать кампании.
It's not only generals who know how to plan campaigns.
ليس الجنرالات فقط هم من يعرفون كيفية التخطيط للحملات.
А что, если они вас не арестуют? А что, если они вообще не отреагируют?
What if they don't arrest you?
What if they don't react at all?
ماذا لو لم يُعتقلوك؟ ماذا لو لم يُبادروا بأيّ ردّ فعل؟
Кое-что для вашего блокнота:
Something for your notebook:
شيء لدفتر ملاحظاتك:
Функция гражданского сопротивления — спровоцировать ответную реакцию.
The function of a civil resister is to provoke response.
وظيفة المقاوم المدني هي إثارة الاستجابة.
И мы продолжим провоцировать...
And we will continue to provoke...
وسنستمر في الاستفزاز...
...пока они не ответят или не изменят закон.
...until they respond or they change the law.
...حتى يستجيبوا أو يغيروا القانون.
Они не контролируют ситуацию. Мы контролируем.
They are not in control.
We are.
هم ليسوا مسيطرين، نحن المسيطرين.
В этом сила гражданского сопротивления.
That is the strength of civil resistance.
هذه هي قوة المقاومة المدنية.
Винс!
Vince!
فينس!
- Что он сказал? - Он сказал, что всё под контролем.
-What did he say?
-He said he's in control.
- ماذا قال؟ - قال أنه هو المسيطر.
Вы собираетесь пройти весь путь пешком?
Do you intend to walk all the way?
هل تنوي المشي طوال الطريق؟
Это единственный способ узнать эту историю.
It's the only way
I can get the story.
إنها الطريقة الوحيدة التي أستطيع من خلالها الحصول على القصة.
Кроме того, меня зовут Уокер.
Besides, my name is Walker.
وبالإضافة إلى ذلك، اسمي ووكر.
«Меня зовут Уокер».
"My name is Walker."
"اسمي ووكر."
-Моя дорогая госпожа Неру! -Бапу.
-My dear Mrs. Nehru!
-Bapu.
-عزيزتي السيدة نهرو!-بابو.
Человеку нужна соль...
Man needs salt...
الإنسان يحتاج الملح...
...так как ему нужны воздух и вода.
...as he needs air and water.
... لأنه يحتاج إلى الهواء والماء.
Эта соль добывается в Индийском океане.
This salt comes from the lndian Ocean.
يأتي هذا الملح من المحيط الهندي.
Пусть каждый индиец заявит об этом, как о своем праве.
Let every lndian claim it as his right.
فليطالب كل هندي بهذا باعتباره حقه.
Итак, еще раз, человек ненасилия...
And so, once more, the man of nonviolence...
وهكذا، مرة أخرى، رجل اللاعنف...
...бросил вызов могуществу Британской империи.
...has challenged the might of the British Empire.
...لقد تحدى قوة الإمبراطورية البريطانية.
Они делают это везде, сэр. Их толпы.
They're making it everywhere, sir.
Mobs of them.
إنهم يفعلون ذلك في كل مكان، يا سيدي. حشود منهم.
Публично.
Publicly.
علناً.
Лидеры Конгресса продают это на улицах Дели.
Congress leaders are selling it on the streets of Delhi.
زعماء المؤتمر يبيعونها في شوارع دلهي.
Нас дурачат, сэр, по всему миру.
We're being made fools of, sir, around the world.
نحن نتعرض للسخرية، يا سيدي، في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Нет ли каких-либо указаний из Лондона?
Isn't there any instruction from London?
هل لا يوجد أي تعليمات من لندن؟
Мы обязаны это остановить. И мы это остановим!
We're required to stop it.
And stop it we will!
نحن مطالبون بإيقافه، وسنوقفه!
Мне все равно, если мы заполним тюрьмы. Прекратите это!
I don't care if we fill the jails.
Stop it!
لا يهمني إن امتلأت السجون. كفوا عن ذلك!
Арестуйте любого человека, любого звания, кроме Ганди.
Arrest anyone, any rank, except Gandhi.
إعتقلوا أي شخص، مهما كانت رتبته، باستثناء غاندي.
Мы лишим его опоры.
We'll cut the strength from under him.
سنقطع القوة من تحته.
А потом займемся Махатмой.
And then we'll deal with the Mahatma.
وبعد ذلك سنتعامل مع المهاتما.
Бегите! Очистите этот пляж!
Jump to it! Clear this beach!
اقفز إليه! أزل هذا الشاطئ!
Не отвечайте тем же! Никакого насилия!
Don't hit back! No violence!
لا ترد بالضرب! لا للعنف!
Под арестом, должно быть, 100 000 человек. И это продолжается.
There must be 1 00,000 under arrest.
And it still goes on.
لا بد أن هناك 100 ألف شخص قيد الاعتقال. وما زال الأمر مستمرًا.
- Кто ими руководит? - Не знаю. Неру, Патель...
-Who's leading them?
-l don't know. Nehru, Patel...
من يقودهم؟ لا أعلم. نهرو، باتيل...
...большинство конгрессменов в тюрьме. И их жены, и дети.
...most congress officials are in jail.
And their wives and children.
...معظم مسؤولي الكونغرس في السجن، وكذلك زوجاتهم وأطفالهم.
Мы даже арестовали мать Неру.
We've even arrested Nehru's mother.
لقد قمنا حتى باعتقال والدة نهرو.
Было ли какое-либо насилие?
Has there been any violence?
هل حدث أي عنف؟
В Пешаваре заместитель комиссара полиции...
In Peshawar, the deputy police commissioner...
وفي بيشاور، قال نائب مفوض الشرطة...
...потерял голову и открыл огонь из пулемета.
...lost his head and opened fire with a machine gun.
...فقد رأسه وفتح النار من مدفع رشاش.
Но ему грозит дисциплинарный суд.
But he's facing disciplinary court.
لكنه يواجه المحكمة التأديبية.
Нельзя ожидать, что такие вещи не произойдут.
You can't expect things like that not to happen.
لا يمكنك أن تتوقع أن مثل هذه الأشياء لن تحدث.
Целью вопроса было выяснить, применялось ли с их стороны насилие.
The question was intended to discover if there was any violence on their side.
وكان الهدف من السؤال هو اكتشاف ما إذا كان هناك أي عنف من جانبهم.
Нет, сэр.
No, sir.
لا سيدي.
Боюсь, что нет.
I'm afraid not.
لا للأسف.
Возможно, если бы мы арестовали Ганди, это могло бы...
Perhaps if we arrested Gandhi, it might....
ربما لو اعتقلنا غاندي، فقد...
Он адресовал это письмо непосредственно вам, не так ли?
He's addressed this letter directly to you, has he?
لقد وجه هذه الرسالة إليك مباشرة، أليس كذلك؟
Да, сэр, это так.
Yes, sir, he has.
نعم سيدي، لقد فعل.
Обычное дело:
The usual thing:
الشيء المعتاد:
«Соль Индии принадлежит Индии».
"India's salt belongs to lndia."
"ملح الهند ملك للهند."
Затем он категорически говорит...
Then he says flatly...
ثم يقول بصراحة...
...что завтра он возглавит рейд на соляные копи Дхарасаны.
...that he will lead a raid tomorrow on the Dharasana Salt Works.
...أنه سيقود غارة غدًا على مصنع ملح داراسانا.
Поблагодарите его за письмо...
Thank him for his letter...
اشكره على رسالته...
...и посадили его в тюрьму.
...and put him in jail.
...ووضعوه في السجن.
Да, сэр.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Да, сэр. С удовольствием.
Yes, sir. It'll be my pleasure.
نعم سيدي، سيكون من دواعي سروري.
- А Филдс? - Сэр?
-And Fields?
-Sir?
-و الحقول؟ -سيدي؟
Держите соляные фабрики открытыми.
Keep that salt works open.
ابقي أعمال الملح مفتوحة.
Да, сэр.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Извините, сэр.
I'm sorry, sir.
انا آسف سيدي.
Мне приказано пропускать через эти ворота только штатный персонал.
My orders are to allow regular staff only through these gates.
أوامري هي السماح للموظفين العاديين فقط بالمرور عبر هذه البوابات.
Очень хорошо.
Very well.
جيد جدا.
--от его имени.
--in his name.
--بإسمه.
И ради него мы не поднимем руку.
And for his sake, we will not raise a hand.
ومن أجله لن نرفع يداً.
Да здравствует Махатма Ганди!
Long live Mahatma Gandhi!
يعيش المهاتما غاندي!
Да здравствует Ганди!
Long live Gandhiji!
عاش غاندي!
Мы готовы!
We are ready!
نحن مستعدون!
Мне нужна твердость и дисциплина.
I want firmness and discipline.
أريد الحزم والانضباط.
- Хорошо, займите свои позиции. - Да, сэр.
-All right, take up your positions.
-Yes, sir.
-حسنًا، اتخذوا أماكنكم. -نعم سيدي.
На старт. Вперед!
To your mark. Forward!
إلى علامتك. إلى الأمام!
Вчера в полночь...
Last night at midnight...
الليلة الماضية في منتصف الليل...
...они забрали у нас Гандиджи.
...they took Gandhiji from us.
...لقد أخذوا غاندي منا.
Они ожидают, что мы падем духом...
They expect us to lose heart...
إنهم يتوقعون منا أن نفقد القلب...
...или дать отпор.
...or to fight back.
...أو القتال مرة أخرى.
Мы не сделаем ни того, ни другого!
We will do neither!
لن نفعل أياً منهما!
Будьте начеку!
On your guard!
على حذرك!
Нет, сэр. Ворота закрыты!
No, sir. The gate is closed!
لا يا سيدي، الباب مغلق!
«Они шли...
"They walked...
"لقد مشوا..."
...как индуисты, так и мусульмане...
...both Hindu and Muslim alike...
...كل من الهندوس والمسلمين على حد سواء...
...с высоко поднятой головой...
...with heads held high...
...مع رفع الرؤوس عاليا...
...без всякой надежды на спасение...
...without any hope of escape...
...دون أي أمل في الهروب...
...от травмы или смерти.
...from injury or death.
...من الإصابة أو الموت.
Это продолжалось до самой ночи».
It went on and on into the night."
واستمر الأمر حتى الليل.
Останавливаться.
Stop.
قف.
«Женщины выносили с дороги раненые и изломанные тела...
"Women carried the wounded and broken bodies from the road...
"حملت النساء الجثث الجريحة والمكسورة من الطريق...
...пока они не падали от изнеможения».
...until they dropped from exhaustion."
...حتى سقطوا من الإرهاق.
Стоп. «Но все равно, это продолжалось и продолжалось». Стоп.
Stop. "But still, it went on and on."
Stop.
توقف. "لكن مع ذلك، استمر الأمر." توقف.
«Какое бы моральное превосходство ни имел Запад...
"Whatever moral ascendancy the West held...
"مهما كانت السيادة الأخلاقية التي يتمتع بها الغرب...
...заблудился здесь сегодня.
...was lost here today.
...فقدت هنا اليوم.
Индия свободна... lndia is free...
الهند حرة...
...ибо она приняла на себя все, что могут дать сталь и жестокость...
...for she has taken all that steel and cruelty can give...
... لأنها تحملت كل ما يمكن للصلابة والقسوة أن تقدمه...
...и она не съежилась и не отступила." Стоп.
...and she has neither cringed nor retreated." Stop.
...ولم تتراجع أو تتراجع." توقف.
Я понимаю, что, должно быть, дал вам много поводов для раздражения...
I am aware that l must have given you much cause for irritation...
أنا أدرك أنني ربما أعطيتك الكثير من الأسباب للانزعاج ...
...Ваше Превосходительство.
...Your Excellency.
...صاحب السعادة.
Надеюсь, это не станет разделением нас, мужчин.
I hope it will not stand between us as men.
أتمنى أن لا يقف هذا بيننا كرجال.
Господин Ганди...
Mr. Gandhi...
السيد غاندي...
...мне поручено просить вас присутствовать...
...l am instructed to request your attendance...
...لقد أُمرت بطلب حضورك...
...на общеправительственной конференции в Лондоне...
...at an all-government conference in London...
...في مؤتمر حكومي شامل في لندن...
...чтобы обсудить возможную независимость...
...to discuss the possible independence...
... لمناقشة الاستقلال المحتمل...
...Индии.
...of India.
...من الهند.
Совсем недавно освободился из тюрьмы...
Only recently released from prison...
لقد تم إطلاق سراحه مؤخرا من السجن...
...Махатма Ганди покидает Бомбей на пароходе «Раджпутана»...
...Mahatma Gandhi leaves Bombay on the SS Rajputana...
...مهاتما غاندي يغادر بومباي على متن سفينة إس إس راجبوتانا...
...чтобы принять участие в конференции по независимости Индии...
...to attend the conference on lndian independence...
...لحضور مؤتمر استقلال الهند...
...по приглашению премьер-министра Рамси Макдональда.
...called by Prime Minister
Ramsay MacDonald.
...بدعوة من رئيس الوزراء رامزي ماكدونالد.
Г-н Ганди, единственный делегат Индийской партии Конгресса...
Mr. Gandhi, the sole
Indian Congress Party delegate...
السيد غاندي، المندوب الوحيد لحزب المؤتمر الهندي...
...остановился в Кингсли-холле в Ист-Энде Лондона...
...is staying at Kingsley Hall in London's East End...
...يقيم في Kingsley Hall في شرق لندن...
...на время переговоров.
...for the duration of the talks.
...طوال مدة المحادثات.
Его видели здесь среди местных кокни...
He's seen here amongst local cockneys...
لقد شوهد هنا بين سكان كوكني المحليين ...
...которые приняли его в свои сердца.
...who have taken him to their hearts.
...الذين أخذوه إلى قلوبهم.
Помимо посещения конференции...
Besides attending the conference...
بالإضافة إلى حضور المؤتمر...
...он нашел время для встреч с политическими и религиозными лидерами...
...he has found time to meet political and religious leaders...
...لقد وجد الوقت للقاء الزعماء السياسيين والدينيين...
...как мистер Ллойд Джордж...
...like Mr. Lloyd George...
... مثل السيد لويد جورج...
...архиепископ Кентерберийский Джордж Бернард Шоу...
...the Archbishop of Canterbury,
George Bernard Shaw...
... رئيس أساقفة كانتربري، جورج برنارد شو...
...и Чарли Чаплин.
...and Charlie Chaplin.
...و تشارلي شابلن.
На прошлой неделе он отправился из Кингсли-холла...
He journeyed last week from Kingsley Hall...
لقد سافر الأسبوع الماضي من قاعة كينغسلي...
...принять приглашение на чай от короля Георга и королевы Марии...
...to accept an invitation to tea from King George and Queen Mary...
...قبول دعوة لتناول الشاي من الملك جورج والملكة ماري...
...в Букингемском дворце перед посещением конференции.
...at Buckingham Palace before attending the conference.
...في قصر باكنغهام قبل حضور المؤتمر.
И я хотел бы подчеркнуть, что я считаю нашей первой обязанностью...
And l would emphasize that I think our first duty...
وأود أن أؤكد أنني أعتقد أن واجبنا الأول...
...значит признать, что нет единой Индии...
...is to recognize that there is not one India...
...هو الاعتراف بأنه لا توجد الهند واحدة...
...а несколько.
...but several.
...ولكن عدة.
Индийский индуист…
A Hindu lndia...
الهندوسية الهندية…
...мусульманская Индия...
...a Muslim lndia...
...الهند المسلمة...
...и Индия княжеств.
...and an India of princely states.
... والهند من الولايات الأميرية.
И все это нужно уважать...
And all these must be respected...
وكل هذا يجب احترامه...
...и заботились.
...and cared for.
...وتم الاهتمام بها.
И не один.
Not just one.
ليس واحد فقط.
Г-н Ганди, который присутствовал...
Mr. Gandhi, who has been attending...
السيد غاندي، الذي كان يحضر...
...Лондонская конференция за круглым столом по вопросу независимости Индии...
...the London Round Table
Conference on lndian lndependence...
...مؤتمر المائدة المستديرة في لندن بشأن استقلال الهند...
...отправился на север, чтобы посетить хлопчатобумажную фабрику.
...journeyed north to visit a cotton mill.
...سافرنا شمالاً لزيارة مصنع القطن.
Хотя я и не одета для климата Ланкашира...
Although not dressed for the Lancashire climate...
على الرغم من عدم ارتداء الملابس المناسبة لمناخ لانكشاير...
...Господин Ганди получил теплый прием от рабочих завода...
...Mr. Gandhi received a warm welcome from mill workers...
... تلقى السيد غاندي ترحيبا حارا من عمال المصنع...
...прежде чем отправиться обратно на юг...
...before heading back south...
...قبل العودة إلى الجنوب...
...для последней встречи с г-ном Макдональдом.
...for a final meeting with Mr. MacDonald.
...للقاء أخير مع السيد ماكدونالد.
Премьер-министр заявил, что переговоры были конструктивными и откровенными.
The prime minister said the talks were both constructive and frank.
وقال رئيس الوزراء إن المحادثات كانت بناءة وصريحة.
Прощайте, мистер Ганди.
So farewell, Mr. Gandhi.
وداعا سيد غاندي.
И счастливого пути!
And bon voyage!
وأتمنى لك رحلة سعيدة!
Так вот, правда в том, что после всех твоих путешествий...
So the truth is, after all your travels...
والحقيقة هي أنه بعد كل أسفارك...
...после всех твоих усилий...
...after all your efforts...
...بعد كل جهودك...
...они остановили кампанию и отправили вас обратно ни с чем.
...they've stopped the campaign and sent you back empty-handed.
... لقد أوقفوا الحملة وأرسلوك خالي الوفاض.
Они лишь цепляются за старые мечты...
They're only clinging to old dreams...
إنهم متمسكون فقط بالأحلام القديمة...
...и пытаются разделить нас по-старому.
...and trying to split us in the old way.
...ومحاولة تقسيمنا بالطريقة القديمة.
Но воля исчезла.
But the will has gone.
ولكن الإرادة ذهبت.
Независимость упадет, как спелое яблоко.
Independence will fall like a ripe apple.
إن الاستقلال سوف يسقط مثل التفاحة الناضجة.
Вопрос только в том, когда и как.
The only question is, when and how.
السؤال الوحيد هو متى وكيف.
Ну, я говорю, когда же это сейчас!
Well, l say, when is now!
حسنًا، أقول، متى الآن؟
И мы определим, как именно.
And we will determine how.
وسوف نحدد كيف.
Именно так.
Precisely.
بدقة.
Бапу, она снова хромает.
Bapu, she is limping again.
بابو، إنها تتعثر مرة أخرى.
Это всего лишь растяжение.
It's only a sprain.
إنها مجرد التواء.
Отведи ее к реке. Мы сделаем ей грязевую маску.
Take her to the river.
We'll make a mud pack for her.
خذها إلى النهر. سنصنع لها كيسًا من الطين.
Иди. Я через минуту.
Go. l won't be a moment.
اذهب. لن أتأخر لحظة.
Они готовятся к войне.
They are preparing for war.
إنهم يستعدون للحرب.
Я не поддержу это.
I will not support it.
لن ادعمه
Но я не собираюсь пользоваться их опасностью.
But l do not intend to take advantage of their danger.
ولكنني لا أنوي الاستفادة من خطرهم.
Вот тогда вы и воспользуетесь преимуществом.
That's when you take advantage.
هذا هو الوقت الذي يمكنك الاستفادة منه.
Это просто еще один способ нанести ответный удар.
That is just another way of hitting back.
هذه مجرد طريقة أخرى للرد.
Мы прошли долгий путь вместе с британцами.
We've come a long way together with the British.
لقد قطعنا شوطا طويلا مع البريطانيين.
Когда они уходят, мы хотим проводить их как друзей.
When they leave, we want to see them off as friends.
عندما يغادرون، نريد أن نراهم كأصدقاء.
А теперь, если позволите, мне нужно кое-что сделать.
Now, if you'll excuse me, there is something I must attend to.
الآن، إذا سمحت لي، هناك شيء يجب أن أنتبه إليه.
Грязевые обертывания.
Mud packs.
أكياس الطين.
Господин Ганди, сэр.
Mr. Gandhi, sir.
السيد غاندي، سيدي.
Мне поручено выяснить тему вашего сегодняшнего выступления.
I've been instructed to inquire as to the subject of your speech tonight.
لقد تم تكليفي بالاستفسار عن موضوع خطابك الليلة.
Ценность козьего молока в ежедневном рационе.
The value of goat's milk in daily diet.
قيمة حليب الماعز في الغذاء اليومي
Но можете быть уверены, что я также выступлю против войны.
But you can be sure that
I will also speak against war.
ولكن يمكنك أن تكون على يقين من أنني سوف أتحدث أيضا ضد الحرب.
Извините, это недопустимо.
Sorry, that can't be permitted.
عذرا، لا يمكن السماح بذلك.
Капрал!
Corporal!
عريف!
Все в порядке, миссис Ганди.
It's all right, Mrs. Gandhi.
لا بأس، سيدتي غاندي.
Мне приказано вернуться с вами и вашим спутником в ашрам.
I have orders to return with you and your companion to the ashram.
لقد صدرت لي أوامر بالعودة معك ورفيقك إلى الأشرم.
Если взять моего мужа, я намерен говорить вместо него.
If you take my husband,
I intend to speak in his place.
إذا أخذت زوجي، فإنني أنوي التحدث نيابة عنه.
Подождите секунду, ладно?
Hold it a second, will you?
انتظر لحظة، هل يمكنك ذلك؟
Это был дворец Ага-Хана до того, как его превратили в тюрьму.
It was the Aga Khan's palace before they turned it into a prison.
كان قصر الآغا خان قبل أن يحولوه إلى سجن.
Они держат там Ганди и политиков Конгресса.
They're holding Gandhi and congress politicians there.
إنهم يحتجزون غاندي وسياسيين من حزب المؤتمر هناك.
Пандит Неру и другие находятся в форте Ахмаднагар.
Pandit Nehru and the others are up at Ahmednagar Fort.
البانديت نهرو والآخرون موجودون في حصن أحمدناجار.
Неплохо для тюрьмы, а?
Not bad for a prison, eh?
ليس سيئا بالنسبة لسجن، أليس كذلك؟
Думаю, ни одно место не будет хорошим, если ты заперт.
I guess no place is good if you're locked in.
أعتقد أنه لا يوجد مكان جيد إذا كنت محبوسًا فيه.
Вам очень повезло.
Your timing's pretty lucky.
توقيتك محظوظ جدًا.
Они отрезали его от прессы.
They had him cut off from the press.
لقد قطعوه عن الصحافة.
Но его личный секретарь умер, и ограничения были ослаблены.
But his personal secretary died, so they let up on restrictions.
ولكن سكرتيره الشخصي توفي، لذا تم تخفيف القيود.
Да, я слышал о журнале LIFE.
Yes, l have heard of LIFE magazine.
نعم، لقد سمعت عن مجلة لايف.
Я даже слышал о Маргарет Бурк-Уайт.
I've even heard of
Margaret Bourke-White.
حتى أنني سمعت عن مارغريت بورك وايت.
Но я не понимаю, почему кто-то из них должен интересоваться стариком...
But l don't know why either should be interested in an old man...
ولكنني لا أعرف لماذا يجب على أي منهما أن يكون مهتمًا برجل عجوز ...
...сидя в тюрьме один...
...sitting alone in prison...
...يجلس وحيدا في السجن...
...в то время как остальной мир разлетается на куски.
...while the rest of the world is blowing itself to pieces.
...في حين أن بقية العالم يفجر نفسه إلى قطع.
Ну, ты единственный мужчина, которого я знаю, который шьет себе одежду сам.
Well, you're the only man I know who makes his own clothes.
حسنًا، أنت الرجل الوحيد الذي أعرفه والذي يصنع ملابسه بنفسه.
Но для меня это не такое уж большое достижение.
But for me, that's not much of an accomplishment.
ولكن بالنسبة لي، هذا ليس إنجازًا كبيرًا.
Нет, тюрьма для меня скорее приятна.
No, prison is rather agreeable to me.
لا، السجن هو المكان المناسب بالنسبة لي.
И нет никаких сомнений, что после войны...
And there is no doubt that after the war...
ولا شك أنه بعد الحرب...
...независимость придет.
...independence will come.
...الاستقلال سيأتي.
Единственное, что меня беспокоит...
My only worry...
قلقي الوحيد...
...какую форму оно примет.
...is what shape it will take.
...هو الشكل الذي سوف يتخذه.
- У Джинны... - Стоп!
-Jinnah has--
-Stop!
-جناح لديه-- -توقف!
Извините, но... Не могли бы вы выйти вперед?
I'm sorry, but--
Could you come forward, please?
أنا آسف، ولكن-- هل يمكنك أن تتقدم للأمام، من فضلك؟
- Иди, иди. - Только до перил.
-Come, come.
-Just up to the railing.
-تعال، تعال. -فقط حتى السور.
Большое спасибо.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
Спасибо.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
А теперь извините.
Now, sorry.
الآن، آسف.
Продолжайте. «Какую форму это примет...»
Go on. "What shape it will take...."
تابع. "ما هو الشكل الذي سيتخذه..."
Что есть у Джинны?
Jinnah has what?
جناح لديه ماذا؟
Джинна сотрудничал с британцами.
Jinnah has cooperated with the British.
وقد تعاون جناح مع البريطانيين.
Это дало ему власть и свободу слова.
It has given him power and the freedom to speak.
لقد أعطته القوة والحرية في الكلام.
И он вселил в мусульман страх...
And he's filled the Muslims with fears...
وملأ المسلمين بالخوف...
...что с ними случится...
...of what will happen to them...
...ماذا سيحدث لهم...
...в стране, где преобладает индуизм.
...in a country that is predominantly Hindu.
...في بلد ذي أغلبية هندوسية.
И это мне трудно вынести...
And that l find hard to bear...
وهذا ما أجد صعوبة في تحمله...
...даже в тюрьме.
...even in prison.
...حتى في السجن.
Мистер Ганди?
Mr. Gandhi?
السيد غاندي؟
Мне трудно рассматривать это как решение проблем 20-го века.
It's hard for me to see this as a solution to the 20th century's problems.
من الصعب بالنسبة لي أن أرى هذا كحل لمشاكل القرن العشرين.
У меня есть друзья, которые постоянно говорят мне...
I have friends who keep telling me...
لدي أصدقاء يخبرونني باستمرار...
...сколько им обходится содержание меня в нищете.
...how much it costs them to keep me in poverty.
...كم يكلفهم إبقاءي في فقر.
Но я знаю, что счастье не приходит с вещами...
But l know happiness does not come with things...
ولكنني أعلم أن السعادة لا تأتي مع الأشياء...
...даже вещи 20-го века.
...even 20th-century things.
...حتى الأشياء التي تعود للقرن العشرين.
Это может быть результатом работы и гордости за то, что вы делаете.
It can come from work and pride in what you do.
يمكن أن يأتي ذلك من العمل والفخر بما تفعله.
Индия живет в своих деревнях...
India lives in her villages...
الهند تعيش في قراها...
...и ужасную нищету там можно устранить только...
...and the terrible poverty there can only be removed...
...والفقر المدقع هناك لا يمكن إزالته إلا...
...если удастся возродить их местные навыки.
...if their local skills can be revived.
...إذا أمكن إحياء مهاراتهم المحلية.
Бедность — худшая форма насилия.
Poverty is the worst form of violence.
الفقر هو أسوأ أشكال العنف.
И конструктивная программа — это единственное...
And a constructive program is the only...
والبرنامج البناء هو الحل الوحيد...
...ненасильственное решение агонии Индии.
...nonviolent solution to lndia's agony.
...الحل السلمي لمعاناة الهند.
Это не обязательно будет прогрессом для Индии...
It will not necessarily be progress for lndia...
لن يكون بالضرورة تقدماً بالنسبة للهند...
...если она просто импортирует несчастья Запада.
...if she simply imports the unhappiness of the West.
...إذا كانت ببساطة تستورد تعاسة الغرب.
Вы действительно верите, что сможете использовать ненасилие против Гитлера?
Do you really believe you could use nonviolence against Hitler?
هل تعتقد حقا أنك يمكن أن تستخدم اللاعنف ضد هتلر؟
Не обошлось без поражений и большой боли.
Not without defeats and great pain.
ليس من دون هزائم وألم كبير.
Но разве в этой войне нет поражений?
But are there no defeats in this war?
ولكن هل لا يوجد هزائم في هذه الحرب؟
Боли нет?
No pain?
لا يوجد ألم؟
Чего нельзя делать...
What you cannot do...
ما لا تستطيع فعله...
...принять несправедливость от Гитлера или кого-либо ещё.
...is accept injustice from Hitler or anyone.
... هو قبول الظلم من هتلر أو أي شخص آخر.
Вы должны сделать несправедливость видимой.
You must make the injustice visible.
يجب عليك أن تجعل الظلم مرئيًا.
Будьте готовы умереть ради этого, как солдат.
Be prepared to die like a soldier to do so.
كن مستعدًا للموت كجندي من أجل القيام بذلك.
Это то, к чему я должен здесь прийти?
Is this what l'm meant to end up with here?
هل هذا ما أريد أن أنتهي به هنا؟
Нет.
No.
لا.
Вот что ты получаешь, отвлекая меня.
That's what you get for distracting me.
هذا ما تحصل عليه لتشتيت انتباهي.
Чего вы ожидаете, когда говорите такие вещи?
What do you expect when you talk like that?
ماذا تتوقع عندما تتحدث بهذه الطريقة؟
Я ожидаю от вас такого же терпения, как и от меня сейчас.
I expect you to show as much patience as l am now.
أتوقع منك أن تظهر نفس القدر من الصبر كما أفعل الآن.
Медленно поверните и осторожно потяните.
Turn slowly and pull it gently.
قم بإدارته ببطء ثم اسحبه بلطف.
И это касается и жизни женщин.
And that includes the life of women.
وهذا يشمل حياة المرأة.
Бапу всегда говорил...
Bapu has always said...
لقد قال بابو دائمًا...
...в Индии существовало два вида рабства:
...there were two kinds of slavery in lndia:
...كان هناك نوعان من العبودية في الهند:
Один для женщин, другой для неприкасаемых.
One for women, one for the untouchables.
واحد للنساء، وواحد للمنبوذين.
И он всегда боролся против обоих.
And he has always fought against both.
وقد حارب دائما ضد كليهما.
Вас раздражает такая разлука?
Does it rankle, being separated in this way?
هل يزعجك أن يتم فصلنا بهذه الطريقة؟
В индуистской философии...
In Hindu philosophy...
في الفلسفة الهندوسية...
...путь к Богу...
...the way to God...
...الطريق إلى الله...
...освободить себя от имущества...
...is to free yourself of possessions...
...هو تحرير نفسك من الممتلكات...
...и страстей.
...and of passions.
...ومن المشاعر.
Бапу всегда пытался найти путь к Богу.
Bapu has always struggled to find the way to God.
لقد ناضل بابو دائمًا من أجل العثور على الطريق إلى الله.
Вы имеете в виду, что он отказался от супружеской жизни?
Do you mean that he gave up married life?
هل تقصد أنه تخلى عن الحياة الزوجية؟
Четыре раза он пытался...
Four times he tried...
حاول أربع مرات...
...и потерпел неудачу.
...and failed.
...وفشلت.
Но затем он дал торжественную клятву.
But then he took a solemn vow.
ولكن بعد ذلك أخذ عهدا رسميا.
И он его ни разу не сломал?
And he's never broken it?
ولم يكسرها أبدًا؟
Еще нет.
Not yet.
ليس بعد.
- У меня есть разрешение переместить ее. - Мне очень жаль, сэр.
-l've got permission to move her.
-l'm very sorry, sir.
-لقد حصلت على الإذن لنقلها. -أنا آسف جدًا، سيدي.
У нее был обширный тромбоз. Это серьезный сердечный приступ.
She's had a massive thrombosis.
It's a serious heart attack.
لقد أصيبت بجلطة دموية حادة. إنها نوبة قلبية خطيرة.
Она не переживет эту поездку.
She'll never survive the trip.
لن تنجو من الرحلة أبدًا.
Лучше просто оставить ее здесь и надеяться.
It's better if we just keep her here and hope.
من الأفضل أن نبقيها هنا ونأمل.
Пришло время для моей прогулки.
It's time for my walk.
لقد حان وقت نزهتي.
Я не задержусь надолго.
I won't be long.
لن أبقى طويلاً.
Сторожить...
Guard...
يحمي...
...предъявить оружие!
...present arms!
...الأسلحة الحالية!
Мы пришли увенчать победу дружбой.
We have come to crown victory with friendship.
لقد وصلنا إلى تتويج النصر بالصداقة.
Чтобы помочь рождению независимой Индии...
To assist at the birth of an independent lndia...
للمساعدة في ولادة الهند المستقلة...
...и приветствовать ее как равноправного члена...
...and to welcome her as an equal member...
... والترحيب بها كعضو متساوٍ...
...в Британском Содружестве Наций.
...in the British Commonwealth of Nations.
...في الكومنولث البريطاني للأمم.
Я здесь для того, чтобы убедиться, что я последний британский вице-король...
I am here to see that I am the last British viceroy...
أنا هنا لأتأكد من أنني نائب الملك البريطاني الأخير...
...когда-либо удостоиться чести такого приема.
...ever to have the honor of such a reception.
...أن أحصل على شرف مثل هذا الاستقبال.
Меня не беспокоит независимость Индии.
I am not concerned about the independence of India.
أنا لا أشعر بالقلق بشأن استقلال الهند.
Меня беспокоит рабство мусульман.
I'm concerned about the slavery of Muslims.
أنا قلق بشأن عبودية المسلمين.
Пожалуйста, мистер Джинна.
Please, Mr. Jinnah.
من فضلك، السيد جناح.
Я не буду смотреть на мастерство британцев...
I won't watch the mastery of the British...
لن أشاهد إتقان البريطانيين...
...заменено господством индусов.
...replaced by the mastery of the Hindus.
...استبدلت بسيادة الهندوس.
Мусульмане и индуисты — это правый и левый глаз Индии.
Muslim and Hindu are the right and left eye of lndia.
المسلم والهندوسي هما العين اليمنى واليسرى للهند.
Никто не будет господином, никто не будет рабом.
No one will be master, no one slave.
لن يكون أحد سيدًا، ولن يكون أحد عبدًا.
Мир не состоит из Махатм Ганди.
The world is not made of
Mahatma Gandhis.
العالم ليس مصنوعًا من المهاتما غاندي.
Я говорю о реальном мире.
I'm talking about the real world.
أنا أتحدث عن العالم الحقيقي.
- Как... - Настоящая Индия...
-How the--
-The real India has...
-كيف----الهند الحقيقية لديها...
...мусульмане и индуисты в каждой деревне и каждом городе.
...Muslims and Hindus in every village and every city.
... المسلمون والهندوس في كل قرية وكل مدينة.
Как вы их разделите?
How will you separate them?
كيف ستفصلهم؟
Там, где мусульманское большинство...
Where there is a Muslim majority...
حيث توجد أغلبية مسلمة...
...это будет Пакистан.
...that will be Pakistan.
...هذه ستكون باكستان.
Остальное — ваша Индия.
The rest is your India.
والباقي هو الهند الخاصة بك.
Мой дорогой Джинна...
My dear Jinnah...
عزيزي جناح...
...мусульмане составляют большинство в двух разных частях страны.
...the Muslims are in a majority on two different sides of the country.
...المسلمون يشكلون أغلبية على جانبين مختلفين من البلاد.
Давайте беспокоиться о Пакистане. Вы беспокойтесь об Индии.
Let us worry about Pakistan.
You worry about India.
دعونا نقلق بشأن باكستان. وأنتم قلقون بشأن الهند.
Господа...
Gentlemen...
السادة المحترمون...
...я думаю, возможно, нам следует начать снова.
...l think perhaps we should recommence.
...أعتقد أنه ربما ينبغي لنا أن نبدأ من جديد.
Смерть Джинне! Смерть Джинне!
Death to Jinnah!
الموت لجناح! الموت لجناح!
Слава богу, они прекратились.
Thank God, they've stopped.
الحمد لله أنهم توقفوا.
Ману. Абха.
Manu. Abha.
مانو. أبها.
Я твой двоюродный дедушка...
I'm your granduncle...
أنا عمك الأكبر...
...но я все равно могу втоптать любого из вас в землю.
...but l can still walk either of you into the ground.
...لكنني لا أزال قادرًا على دفع أي منكما إلى الأرض.
Мне не нужно, чтобы меня так баловали.
I don't need to be pampered in this way.
لا أحتاج إلى أن أُدلل بهذه الطريقة.
Завершите свою норму прядения.
Finish your quota of spinning.
إنهاء حصتك من الغزل.
Отец. Отец.
Bapu. Bapu.
أب. أب.
Бапу, пожалуйста, не делай этого.
Bapu, please don't do it.
بابو، من فضلك لا تفعل ذلك.
Чего вы хотите, чтобы я не делал?
What do you want me not to do?
ماذا تريدني أن لا أفعل؟
Не встречаться с господином Джинной?
Not to meet with Mr. Jinnah?
عدم مقابلة السيد جناح؟
Я мусульманин...
I am a Muslim...
أنا مسلم...
...и индус...
...and a Hindu...
...وهندوسي...
...и христианин, и иудей.
...and a Christian and a Jew.
...و مسيحي و يهودي.
И вы все тоже.
And so are all of you.
وهكذا أنتم جميعا.
Когда вы размахиваете флагами и кричите...
When you wave those flags and shout...
عندما تلوح بتلك الأعلام وتصرخ...
...вы вселяете страх в сердца своих братьев.
...you send fear into the hearts of your brothers.
...ترسل الرعب في قلوب إخوانك.
Это не та Индия, которую я хочу.
That is not the India l want.
هذه ليست الهند التي أريدها.
Прекратите!
Stop it!
اوقفها!
Ради Бога, прекратите это.
For God's sake, stop it.
من أجل الله، توقف عن ذلك.
Если вы закончили молитвы...
If you've finished your prayers...
إذا انتهيت من صلاتك...
...возможно, мы могли бы начать наш бизнес.
...perhaps we could begin our business.
...ربما يمكننا أن نبدأ أعمالنا.
Мой дорогой Джинна...
My dear Jinnah...
عزيزي جناح...
...мы с тобой братья...
...you and l are brothers...
...أنت وأنا أخوة...
...рожденные от одной матери Индии. Если у вас есть страхи...
...born of the same mother India.
If you have fears...
...وُلِد من نفس الأم الهند. إذا كانت لديك مخاوف...
...я хочу их успокоить.
...l want to put them at rest.
...أريد أن أجعلهم يرتاحون.
Прошу понимания у моих друзей...
Begging the understanding of my friends...
أرجو تفهم أصدقائي...
...я прошу Пандитджи отступить.
...l am asking Panditji to stand down.
...أنا أطلب من البانديتجي أن يتنحى.
Я хочу, чтобы ты стал первым премьер-министром Индии...
I want you to be the first prime minister of lndia...
أريدك أن تكون أول رئيس وزراء للهند.
...чтобы назвать весь ваш кабинет...
...to name your entire cabinet...
...لتسمية خزانتك بأكملها...
...сделать главой каждого правительственного департамента мусульманина.
...to make the head of every government department a Muslim.
...أن نجعل رئيس كل دائرة حكومية مسلماً.
Бапу.
Bapu.
بابو.
Для меня и остальных...
For me and the rest...
بالنسبة لي وللبقية...
...если это то, чего вы хотите...
...if that is what you want...
...إذا كان هذا ما تريد...
...мы это примем.
...we will accept it.
...سوف نقبل ذلك.
Но там...
But out there...
ولكن هناك...
...уже начались беспорядки...
...already there is rioting...
...هناك بالفعل أعمال شغب...
...потому что индуисты боятся, что вы отдадите слишком много.
...because Hindus fear you are going to give too much away.
...لأن الهندوس يخافون من أنك سوف تكشف الكثير.
Если вы это сделали...
If you did this...
إذا فعلت هذا...
...никто не будет его контролировать.
...no one would control it.
...لا أحد يستطيع السيطرة عليه.
Никто.
No one.
لا احد.
Это ваш выбор.
It is your choice.
إنه اختيارك.
Хотите ли вы независимую Индию и независимый Пакистан...
Do you want an independent lndia and an independent Pakistan...
هل تريد الهند المستقلة وباكستان المستقلة؟
...или вы хотите гражданской войны?
...or do you want civil war?
... أم تريد حربا أهلية؟
Джинна! Джинна! Джинна!
Jinnah! Jinnah! Jinnah!
جناح! جناح! جناح!
То, что вы сделали в Ноакхали, Бапу, было чудом.
What you did in Noakhali, Bapu, was a miracle.
ما فعلته في نواخالي يا بابو كان معجزة.
Чудо.
Miracle.
معجزة.
Но миллионы людей находятся в движении...
But millions are on the move...
لكن الملايين يتحركون...
...и никто не может сосчитать мертвых.
...and no one can count the dead.
...ولا أحد يستطيع أن يحصي عدد الموتى.
В Калькутте происходит что-то вроде гражданской войны.
In Calcutta, it's like civil war.
في كالكوتا، الأمر أشبه بالحرب الأهلية.
Мусульмане восстали, и началась кровавая бойня.
The Muslims rose and there was a bloodbath.
ثار المسلمون وحدث حمام دم.
Теперь индусы мстят.
Now the Hindus are taking revenge.
والآن الهندوس ينتقمون.
Если мы не сможем это остановить...
If we can't stop it...
إذا لم نتمكن من إيقافه...
...для индусов, оставшихся в Пакистане, не будет никакой надежды.
...there'll be no hope for the Hindus left in Pakistan.
... لن يكون هناك أي أمل للهندوس المتبقين في باكستان.
Око за око, ослепляя весь мир.
An eye for an eye, making the whole world blind.
العين بالعين، مما يجعل العالم كله أعمى.
Неужели нет свободных войск?
Aren't there any troops to spare?
هل هناك قوات إضافية؟
Ничего.
Nothing.
لا شئ.
Разногласия в Бомбее и Дели теперь едва ли могут поддерживать мир.
The divisions in Bombay and Delhi can hardly keep the peace now.
إن الانقسامات في بومباي ودلهي لا يمكنها أن تحافظ على السلام الآن.
И каждая новая новость порождает новую волну безумия.
And each fresh bit of news creates another wave of madness.
وكل خبر جديد يخلق موجة أخرى من الجنون.
Мы могли бы прекратить все новости.
We could cut all news off.
يمكننا قطع كافة الأخبار.
Бапу, пожалуйста, куда ты идешь?
Bapu, please, where are you going?
بابو، من فضلك، إلى أين أنت ذاهب؟
Я не хочу больше слышать.
I don't want to hear more.
لا أريد أن أسمع المزيد.
Нам нужна ваша помощь.
We need your help.
نحن بحاجة لمساعدتكم.
Я ничего не могу дать.
There is nothing l can give.
لا يوجد شيء أستطيع أن أعطيه.
Куда ты идешь?
Where are you going?
إلى أين أنت ذاهب؟
Калькутта.
Calcutta.
كلكتا.
Если бы я избегал смерти или боялся ее, меня бы сейчас здесь не было...
If l had shunned death or feared it,
I would not be here now...
لو أنني تجنبت الموت أو خشيته، لم أكن هنا الآن...
...и ты не будешь обо мне беспокоиться.
...nor would you be concerned for me.
...ولا داعي للقلق علي.
Но, сэр, пожалуйста.
But, sir, please.
ولكن سيدي، من فضلك.
У меня нет людей, чтобы защитить тебя...
I don't have the men to protect you...
ليس لدي رجال لحمايتك...
...не в мусульманском доме, не в этом квартале.
...not in a Muslim house, not this quarter.
... ليس في بيت مسلم، وليس في هذا الحي.
Я остановился у друга моего друга и...
I'm staying with the friend of a friend and--
أنا أقيم مع صديق صديقي و--
Смерть мусульманам! Смерть мусульманам!
Death to Muslims!
الموت للمسلمين! الموت للمسلمين!
Почему вы остановились в доме мусульманина?
Why are you staying at the home of a Muslim?
لماذا تقيم في بيت مسلم؟
Они убийцы!
They are murderers!
إنهم قتلة!
Они убили мою семью!
They killed my family!
لقد قتلوا عائلتي!
Убирайся из Калькутты, Ганди!
Get out of Calcutta, Gandhi!
اخرج من كالكوتا يا غاندي!
Смерть мусульманам! Смерть мусульманам!
Death to Muslims!
الموت للمسلمين! الموت للمسلمين!
Премьер-министр.
Prime Minister.
رئيس الوزراء.
Почему я должен читать такие новости в газете?
Why must l read news like this in the paper?
لماذا يجب علي أن أقرأ أخبارًا مثل هذه في الصحيفة؟
Сообщить Сардару Пателю. Организовать самолет.
Inform Sardar Patel.
Arrange a plane.
أبلغ سردار باتيل. رتّب طائرة.
Мы поедем в пятницу.
We will go Friday.
سنذهب يوم الجمعة.
Четыре дня, сэр?
Four days, sir?
أربعة أيام يا سيدي؟
Бапу.
Bapu.
بابو.
Сардар, ты набрал вес.
Sardar, you have gained weight.
سردار، لقد اكتسبت وزناً.
Вы должны присоединиться ко мне в посте.
You must join me in the fast.
يجب عليك الانضمام إلي في الصيام.
Если я буду поститься, я умру.
If l fast, I die.
إذا صمت سأموت.
Если вы поститесь, люди попадают во всевозможные неприятности...
If you fast, people go to all sorts of trouble...
إذا صمت، فإن الناس يتعرضون لشتى أنواع المتاعب...
...чтобы сохранить вам жизнь.
...to keep you alive.
...لإبقائك على قيد الحياة.
Бапу, прости меня, я обманул.
Bapu, forgive me, I've cheated.
بابو، سامحني، لقد غششت.
Я мог бы прийти раньше...
I could have come earlier...
كان بإمكاني أن آتي في وقت سابق...
...но ваш пост помог.
...but your fast has helped.
...ولكن صيامك ساعد.
В последние дни люди стали чаще вспоминать эту кровать...
These last days, people's minds have begun to turn to this bed...
في هذه الأيام الأخيرة، بدأت عقول الناس تتجه نحو هذا السرير...
...и подальше от зверств.
...and away from the atrocities.
... وبعيدا عن الفظائع.
Но теперь...
But now...
ولكن الآن...
...этого достаточно.
...it is enough.
...هذا يكفي.
Единственное, что произошло, это то, что я немного похудела.
All that has happened is that
I've grown a little thinner.
كل ما حدث هو أنني أصبحت أنحف قليلاً.
Завтра 5000 студентов-мусульман...
Tomorrow, 5000 Muslim students...
غدا 5000 طالب مسلم...
...всех возрастов...
...of all ages...
...من جميع الأعمار...
...маршируют здесь, в Калькутте, за мир.
...are marching here, in Calcutta, for peace.
...يسيرون هنا في كلكتا من أجل السلام.
Вместе с ними маршируют 5000 студентов-индуистов.
And 5000 Hindu students are marching with them.
ويشارك في المسيرة 5000 طالب هندوسي.
Я рад.
I'm glad.
أنا سعيد.
Но этого будет недостаточно.
But it will not be enough.
ولكن هذا لن يكون كافيا.
Бапу, ты уже не так молод.
Bapu, you are not so young anymore.
بابو، أنت لم تعد صغيراً بعد الآن.
Не беспокойтесь обо мне.
Don't worry for me.
لا تقلق علي.
Я не могу смотреть на разрушение всего, ради чего я жил.
I cannot watch the destruction of all that l've lived for.
لا أستطيع أن أشاهد تدمير كل ما عشت من أجله.
Смерть Ганди!
Death to Gandhi!
الموت لغاندي!
Кто смеет говорить такие вещи?!
Who dares say such things?!
من يجرؤ على قول مثل هذا الكلام؟!
ВОЗ?!
Who?!
من؟!
Сначала ты убьешь меня!
You kill me first!
أنت تقتلني أولا!
Приходить!
Come!
يأتي!
Где ты?!
Where are you?!
أين أنت؟!
Сначала убей меня!
Kill me first!
اقتلني أولا!
Где ты?
Where are you?
أين أنت؟
Пульс очень нерегулярный. Почки не функционируют.
His pulse is very irregular.
The kidneys aren't functioning.
نبضه غير منتظم. كليتاه لا تعملان.
Бапу?
Bapu?
بابو؟
Я привел господина Сухраварди.
I have brought Mr. Suhrawardy.
لقد أحضرت السيد السهروردي.
Именно он призвал мусульман восстать.
It was he who called on the Muslims to rise.
وهو الذي دعا المسلمين إلى القيامة.
Теперь он им говорит...
He is now telling them...
وهو يقول لهم الآن...
...вернуться в свои дома...
...to go back to their homes...
...للعودة إلى منازلهم...
...сложить оружие.
...to lay down their arms.
...أن يلقوا أسلحتهم.
Подумайте, что вы можете сделать, живя...
Think what you can do by living...
فكر فيما يمكنك فعله من خلال العيش...
...чего нельзя сделать, умерев.
...that you cannot do by dying.
... وهذا لا يمكنك فعله بالموت.
Что ты хочешь?
What do you want?
ماذا تريد؟
Что боевые действия прекратятся.
That the fighting will stop.
أن القتال سوف يتوقف.
Что ты заставляешь меня верить...
That you make me believe...
أنك تجعلني أصدق...
...что это никогда больше не повторится.
...that it will never start again.
...أنه لن يبدأ مرة أخرى أبدًا.
Иногда...
Sometimes...
أحيانا...
...это когда ты совсем теряешь надежду...
...it is when you are quite without hope...
... يحدث ذلك عندما تكون بلا أمل على الإطلاق...
...и в полной темноте...
...and in utter darkness...
...وفي الظلام الدامس...
...что Бог приходит на помощь.
...that God comes to the rescue.
...أن الله يأتي للإنقاذ.
Ганди...
Gandhiji...
غاندي...
...умирает...
...is dying...
...يموت...
...из-за нашего безумия.
...because of our madness.
...بسبب جنوننا.
Отбрось свою месть.
Put away your revenge.
ضع انتقامك جانبا.
Какая польза от новых убийств?
What good will come of more killing?
ما الفائدة من مزيد من القتل؟
Имейте смелость сделать...
Have the courage to do...
امتلك الشجاعة للقيام بذلك...
...то, что вы знаете, правильно.
...what you know is right.
...ما تعرفه هو الصحيح.
Ради Бога...
For God's sake...
من أجل الله...
...давайте обнимемся, как братья.
...let us embrace like brothers.
... دعونا نحتضن بعضنا البعض مثل الإخوة.
Это наше обещание.
It's our promise.
إنه وعدنا.
Мы останавливаемся.
We stop.
نحن نتوقف.
Индуистские мечи.
Hindu swords.
سيوف هندوسية.
Это обещание.
It's a promise.
إنه وعد.
Идти.
Go.
يذهب.
Да пребудет с вами Бог.
God be with you.
الله يكون معك.
Вот, ешь!
Here, eat!
هنا، تناول الطعام!
Есть!
Eat!
يأكل!
Я попаду в ад...
I'm going to hell...
سأذهب إلى الجحيم...
...но не с твоей смертью на душе.
...but not with your death on my soul.
...ولكن ليس مع موتك على روحي.
Только Бог решает, кто отправится в ад.
Only God decides who goes to hell.
الله وحده هو الذي يقرر من يذهب إلى الجحيم.
Я убил ребенка.
I killed a child.
لقد قتلت طفلا.
Я разбил его голову о стену.
I smashed his head against a wall.
لقد حطمت رأسه بالحائط.
Почему?
Why?
لماذا؟
Они убили моего сына.
They killed my son.
لقد قتلوا ابني.
Мой мальчик.
My boy.
ابني.
Мусульмане убили моего сына!
The Muslims killed my son!
المسلمون قتلوا ابني!
Я знаю выход из ада.
I know a way out of hell.
أعرف طريقًا للخروج من الجحيم.
Найдите ребенка.
Find a child.
العثور على طفل.
Ребенок, мать и отец которого были убиты.
A child whose mother and father have been killed.
طفل قُتل والده ووالدته.
Маленький мальчик примерно такого роста...
A little boy about this high...
صبي صغير حول هذا الارتفاع...
...и воспитай его как своего собственного сына.
...and raise him as your own.
... وتربيه كأنه أحد أبنائك.
Только убедитесь, что он мусульманин...
Only be sure that he is a Muslim...
فقط تأكد أنه مسلم...
...и что вы воспитываете его как такового.
...and that you raise him as one.
... وأن تربيته كواحد منهم.
Идти.
Go.
يذهب.
Будьте здоровы.
God bless you.
يرحمك الله.
Бапу?
Bapu?
بابو؟
Никаких боевых действий не было...
There's been no fighting...
لم يكن هناك قتال...
...где угодно.
...anywhere.
...في أي مكان.
Он остановлен.
It's stopped.
لقد توقفت.
Безумие прекратилось.
The madness has stopped.
لقد توقف الجنون.
Это глупо...
It's foolish...
إنه أمر أحمق...
...хотя бы для того, чтобы спасти жизнь старика.
...if it's just to save the life of an old man.
...إذا كان الأمر فقط لإنقاذ حياة رجل عجوز.
Нет. В каждом храме и мечети...
No. In every temple and mosque...
لا. في كل معبد ومسجد...
...они поклялись умереть...
...they have pledged to die...
...لقد تعهدوا بالموت...
...прежде чем они поднимут руку друг на друга.
...before they lift a hand against each other.
... قبل أن يرفعوا أيديهم على بعضهم البعض.
Это правда, Бапу.
It is true, Bapu.
إنه صحيح يا بابو.
Повсюду.
Everywhere.
في كل مكان.
Маулана, мой друг...
Maulana, my friend...
مولانا صديقي...
...можно мне апельсинового сока?
...could I have some orange juice?
...هل يمكنني الحصول على بعض عصير البرتقال؟
Тогда мы с тобой...
Then you and l...
ثم أنت وأنا...
...вместе возьмем кусок хлеба.
...will take a piece of bread together.
...سوف نأخذ قطعة من الخبز معًا.
Он будет молиться в саду.
He will be saying prayers in the garden.
وسوف يقول الصلاة في الحديقة.
Вот как едят мули.
That is how you eat muli.
هذه هي الطريقة التي تأكل بها المولي.
Я не уверен, что хочу, чтобы меня запомнили именно таким.
I'm not sure that I want to be remembered that way.
أنا لست متأكدًا من أنني أريد أن أتذكر بهذه الطريقة.
Не волнуйтесь. Если повезет, то этого может и не произойти.
Don't worry.
With luck, you may not be.
لا تقلق، مع الحظ، قد لا تكون كذلك.
Нет, его будут помнить за то, что он искушал судьбу.
No, he will be remembered for tempting fate.
لا، سوف يتذكرونه لإغراء القدر.
Микки Маус!
Mickey Mouse!
ميكي ماوس!
Вы действительно собираетесь в Пакистан?
You're really going to Pakistan?
هل أنت ذاهب إلى باكستان حقا؟
Вы упрямый человек.
You are a stubborn man.
أنت رجل عنيد.
Я просто собираюсь доказать...
I'm simply going to prove...
أنا فقط سأثبت...
...индуистам здесь и мусульманам там...
...to Hindus here and Muslims there...
...إلى الهندوس هنا والمسلمين هناك...
...что единственные дьяволы в мире — это те...
...that the only devils in the world are those...
...أن الشياطين الوحيدين في العالم هم هؤلاء...
...бегающие в наших собственных сердцах.
...running around in our own hearts.
...يجري في قلوبنا.
И именно здесь должны происходить все наши битвы.
And that is where all our battles ought to be fought.
وهذا هو المكان الذي ينبغي أن نخوض فيه جميع معاركنا.
Бапу.
Bapu.
بابو.
Итак, каким воином вы были в этой войне?
So, what kind of warrior have you been in that warfare?
إذن، ما نوع المحارب الذي كنته في تلك الحرب؟
Не очень хороший.
Not a very good one.
ليس جيدا جدا.
Вот почему у меня столько терпимости...
That's why I have so much tolerance...
لهذا السبب لدي الكثير من التسامح...
...для других негодяев мира.
...for the other scoundrels of the world.
...للأشرار الآخرين في العالم.
Сардар?
Sardar?
سردار؟
Попросите Пандитджи обдумать то, что мы обсудили.
Ask Panditji to consider what we've discussed.
اطلب من البانديتجي أن يفكر فيما ناقشناه.
-Хватит! -Еще один.
-Enough!
-One more.
-كفى!-واحدة أخرى.
-Ты соблазнительница! -Просто поклонница.
-You're a temptress!
-Just an admirer.
-أنت مغرية! -مجرد معجبة.
Нет ничего опаснее...
Nothing's more dangerous...
لا يوجد شيء أكثر خطورة...
...особенно для пожилого человека.
...especially for an old man.
...وخاصة بالنسبة لرجل عجوز.
В нем есть что-то печальное.
There's a sadness about him.
هناك حزن عنه.
Он думает, что потерпел неудачу.
He thinks he's failed.
يعتقد أنه فشل.
Почему?
Why?
لماذا؟
Если что-то и доказало его правоту, так это последние месяцы.
If anything's proven him right, it's these last months.
إذا كان هناك شيء أثبت صحة كلامه، فهو هذه الأشهر الأخيرة.
Я, возможно, ослеплена своей любовью к нему...
I may be blinded by my love for him...
ربما أكون أعمى بسبب حبي له...
...но я верю...
...but l believe...
...ولكنني أعتقد...
...когда мы больше всего в этом нуждались...
...when we most needed it...
...عندما كنا في أمس الحاجة إليها...
...он предложил миру выход из безумия.
...he offered the world a way out of madness.
...لقد عرض على العالم طريقا للخروج من الجنون.
Но он этого не видит.
But he doesn't see it.
ولكنه لا يرى ذلك.
Мир тоже.
Neither does the world.
ولا العالم كذلك.
Брат, Бапу уже опаздывает на молитву.
Brother, Bapu is already late for prayers.
أخي، بابو متأخر بالفعل عن الصلاة.
О, Боже!
Oh, God!
يا إلهي!
О, Боже.
Oh, God.
يا إلهي.
Когда я отчаиваюсь...
When l despair...
عندما أيأس...
...Я помню...
...I remember...
...أتذكر...
...что на протяжении всей истории...
...that all through history...
...هذا طوال التاريخ...
...путь истины и любви всегда побеждал.
...the way of truth and love has always won.
...إن طريق الحقيقة والحب قد انتصر دائمًا.
Были тираны и убийцы...
There have been tyrants and murderers...
لقد كان هناك طغاة و قتلة...
...и какое-то время они могут казаться непобедимыми...
...and for a time, they can seem invincible...
...ولفترة من الوقت، قد يبدو الأمر وكأنهم لا يقهرون...
...но в конце концов они всегда падают.
...but in the end, they always fall.
...ولكن في النهاية، فإنهم يسقطون دائمًا.
Подумайте об этом.
Think of it.
فكر في الأمر.